<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="ORS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-or/act/ors/chapter-321"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-or/act/ors/chapter-321"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#oregon-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-or"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="321"/>
          <FRBRname value="ORS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-or/act/ors/chapter-321/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-or/act/ors/chapter-321/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-or/act/ors/chapter-321/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-or/act/ors/chapter-321/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="oregon-legislature" href="https://www.oregonlegislature.gov" showAs="Oregon State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <chapter eId="chp_321">
        <num>321</num>
        <heading>Timber and Forestland Tax</heading>
        <section eId="sec_321-005">
          <num>321.005</num>
          <heading>Definitions for ORS 321.005 to 321.185, 321.560 to 321.600 and 477.440 to 477.460</heading>
          <subsection eId="321-005__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Board” means the State Board of Forestry.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-005__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Protected forestlands” means those lands which are protected from the starting
or spread of fire thereon or therefrom by:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="321-005__subsec_2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The State Forester, with the approval of the board;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-005__subsec_2__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The United States of America through contract with the State Forester;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-005__subsec_2__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Any forest protective agency under contract with the State Forester or the
board pursuant to ORS 477.406; or</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-005__subsec_2__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Any forest protective agency, described in paragraph</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-005__subsec_2__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this subsection,
under an agreement with the United States of America wherein such agency agrees
to protect specific federal forestlands and, in return, the United States of
America agrees to protect specific lands of such agency.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-005__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Department” means the Department of Revenue.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-005__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Committee” means the Emergency Fire Cost Committee.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-005__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Forestland” means any land producing forest products.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-005__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Forest products” means products from harvested timber, but does not include
products from short rotation fiber grown under agricultural conditions as
described in ORS 321.267</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-005__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>or 321.824</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-005__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>, western juniper or products from
harvested western juniper.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-005__subsec_7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Harvest” means the point at which timber that has been cut, severed, or
removed for purposes of sale or use is first measured in the ordinary course of
business as determined by reference to common practice in the timber industry.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-005__subsec_8">
            <num>(8)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Merchantable stand of timber” means any stand on forestlands containing living
or dead timber which is being or can be harvested.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-005__subsec_9">
            <num>(9)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Taxpayer” means the owner of timber at time of harvest.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-005__subsec_10">
            <num>(10)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Taxes” means the taxes provided for in ORS 321.015.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-005__subsec_11">
            <num>(11)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Owner of timber” means any individual or combination of individuals,
partnership, firm, corporation or association of whatever nature holding title
to harvested timber by virtue of:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="321-005__subsec_11__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An instrument of conveyance;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-005__subsec_11__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The harvesting of the timber; or</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-005__subsec_11__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The harvesting of the timber and payment therefor.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-005__subsec_12">
            <num>(12)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Timber” means all logs which can be measured in board feet and other forest
products as determined by department rule.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-011">
          <num>321.011</num>
          <heading>Policy</heading>
          <subsection eId="321-011__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The forested areas situated within eastern Oregon predominate in Ponderosa pine
trees and associated species, and that the forested areas situated within
western Oregon predominate in Douglas fir and associated species;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-011__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Because of this difference in species, different forest fire protection
problems exist in eastern and western Oregon, and different logging conditions
and circumstances in each necessitate varied forest practices in the disposal
of forest slashings and debris; and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-011__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Therefore, in order to give recognition to such differences and their effect on
the accomplishment of the public policy stated in this section, certain
classifications of forestlands within the State of Oregon are established by
ORS 321.005 to 321.185 and 321.560 to 321.600.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-012">
          <num>321.012</num>
          <heading>Public to share cost of suppressing fires caused by public</heading>
          <content>
            <p>The Legislative
Assembly finds that it is in the interest of the State of Oregon that the
public as a whole share responsibility for protecting the forests of this
state, by making funds available from time to time for suppression of fires
caused by the public.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-015">
          <num>321.015</num>
          <heading>Levy of privilege taxes upon harvest of timber for certain purposes; exclusion</heading>
          <subsection eId="321-015__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For the
calendar years beginning January 1, 2024, and January 1, 2025, there is levied
a privilege tax of 90.00 cents per thousand feet, board measure, upon taxpayers
for the privilege of harvesting of all merchantable forest products harvested
on forestlands. Subject to ORS 321.145, the proceeds of the tax shall be
transferred as provided in ORS 321.152</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-015__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>to the Forest Research and
Experiment Account for use for the forest resource research, experimentation
and studies described in ORS 526.215 and for the Forest Research Laboratory
established under ORS 526.225.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-015__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Except as provided in ORS 477.760, in addition to the tax levied by subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-015__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section, there is levied a forest products harvest tax upon
taxpayers of 62.5 cents per thousand feet, board measure, for the privilege of
harvesting all merchantable forest products harvested on forestlands for the
payment of benefits related to fire suppression as provided in ORS 321.005 to
321.185, 321.560 to 321.600 and 477.440 to 477.460.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-015__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For the calendar years beginning January 1, 2024, and January 1, 2025, in
addition to the taxes levied under subsections</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-015__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-015__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section,
there is levied a privilege tax upon taxpayers for the privilege of harvesting
all merchantable forest products harvested on forestlands in the amount of
253.46 cents per thousand feet, board measure, for the purpose of administering
the Oregon Forest Practices Act in an amount not to exceed 40 percent of the
total expenditures approved by the Legislative Assembly for this purpose,
including salary adjustments approved by the Legislative Assembly for fiscal
years 2024 and 2025.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-015__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For the calendar years beginning January 1, 2024, and January 1, 2025, in
addition to the taxes levied by subsections</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-015__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>to</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-015__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section, there
is levied a privilege tax of 21 cents per thousand feet, board measure, upon
taxpayers for the privilege of harvesting all merchantable forest products
harvested on forestlands. Subject to ORS 321.145, the proceeds of the tax shall
be transferred as provided in ORS 321.152</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-015__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>to the subaccount established
pursuant to ORS 350.520 for use by Oregon State University for the purpose of
making investments in professional forestry education at the College of
Forestry.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-015__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-015__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section, the taxes shall be measured by and
be applicable to each per thousand feet, board measure, on the total quantity
of forest products harvested in this state measured by use of any log scale
which is or may be in general use in the logging industry and which is designed
to measure total volume of merchantable forest products in board feet. However,
if the Department of Revenue finds that the scale used by any taxpayer in
computing the taxes due under ORS 321.005 to 321.185 and 321.560 to 321.600
does not accurately reflect the total quantity of merchantable forest products
harvested by the taxpayer, it may require the taxpayer to adopt another log
scale in general use in the industry which in the department’s opinion will
accurately reflect merchantable harvest in board feet.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-015__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The first 25,000 feet, board measure, of forest products harvested annually by
any taxpayer during each calendar year shall be excluded from the total
quantity of harvested forest products that constitutes the measure of the taxes
under ORS 321.005 to 321.185 and 321.560 to 321.600.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-015__subsec_7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <paragraph eId="321-015__subsec_7__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Not later than March 10 of each odd-numbered year, the Legislative Assembly
shall begin considering the biennial forest products harvest tax rates levied
under subsections</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-015__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>,</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-015__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-015__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section.</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="321-015__subsec_4__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon request of the Legislative Revenue Officer or the Legislative Fiscal
Officer, the State Forestry Department shall provide the respective officers
with relevant timber harvest data for the purposes of paragraph</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-015__subsec_4__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this
subsection.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-017">
          <num>321.017</num>
          <heading>Levy of additional privilege tax; distribution to Oregon Forest Resources Institute Fund</heading>
          <subsection eId="321-017__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In addition to the taxes levied under ORS 321.015</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-017__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>to</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-017__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>, there hereby
is levied a privilege tax upon taxpayers on the harvesting of all merchantable
forest products harvested on forestlands in the amount provided in subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-017__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-017__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The rate of tax levied in subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-017__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section shall be established
annually at the beginning of each calendar year by the board of directors of
the Oregon Forest Resources Institute, at a rate not to exceed 75 cents per
thousand feet, board measure, adjusted annually for inflation since 1991 based
on the Consumer Price Index for All Urban Consumers, West Region (All Items),
as published by the Bureau of Labor Statistics of the United States Department
of Labor.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-017__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The tax shall be measured by and be applicable to each per thousand feet, board
measure, and such shall be subject to and determined by the procedures and
provisions of ORS 321.015</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-017__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-017__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-017__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The tax levied by subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-017__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section shall be due and payable to
the Department of Revenue in the manner and procedure, including penalties and
interest, as set forth for the collection of the privilege tax in ORS 321.005
to 321.185.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-017__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The revenue from the tax levied by subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-017__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section shall be
remitted to the State Treasurer who shall deposit it in a suspense account
established under ORS 321.145</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-017__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>. After payment of refunds, which shall be
paid in the same manner as other forest products harvest tax refunds are paid
in ORS 321.145</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-017__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>, the balance of the additional tax imposed under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-017__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section shall be deposited in the Oregon Forest Resources Institute
Fund. [1991 c.949 s22; 1993 c.653 s4; 1999 c.968 ss2,2a; 2001 c.872 s2; 2003
c.769 s2; 2013 c.639 s2; 2017 c.621 s2; 2019 c.57 s13]
(Temporary
provisions relating to forest products harvest tax to fund mitigation of
effects of forest practices on aquatic species)
Note: Sections 4 to 7,
chapter 31, Oregon Laws 2022, provide:
Sec.
4.
Section 5 of this 2022 Act is added to and made a part of ORS 321.005 to
321.185. [2022 c.31 s4]
Sec.
5.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-017__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In addition to the taxes levied under ORS 321.015 and 321.017, there is
levied a privilege tax upon taxpayers on the harvesting of all merchantable
forest products harvested on forestlands in the amount provided in subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-017__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-017__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <paragraph eId="321-017__subsec_2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in paragraph</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-017__subsec_2__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this subsection, at the beginning of
each calendar year, the Department of Revenue shall set the tax levied under
subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-017__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section at a rate estimated to collect $2.5 million per
year.</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="321-017__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Beginning with the first January following the issuance of an incidental take
permit by the federal National Marine Fisheries Service or the United States
Fish and Wildlife Service, pursuant to the federal Endangered Species Act (16
U.S.C. 1531 to 1544), that is consistent with the terms of the Private Forest
Accord Report dated February 2, 2022, and published by the State Forestry
Department on February 7, 2022, the Department of Revenue shall set the tax at
a rate estimated to collect $5 million per year.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-017__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The tax shall be measured by and be applicable to each per thousand feet, board
measure, and such shall be subject to and determined by the procedures and
provisions of ORS 321.015</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-017__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-017__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-017__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The tax levied under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-017__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section shall be due and payable to
the Department of Revenue in the manner and procedure, including penalties and
interest, as set forth for the collection of the privilege tax under ORS
321.005 to 321.185.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-017__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The revenue from the tax levied under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-017__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section shall be
remitted to the State Treasurer who shall deposit it in a suspense account
established under ORS 321.145</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-017__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>. After payment of refunds, which shall be
paid in the same manner as other forest products harvest tax refunds are paid
under ORS 321.145</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-017__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>, the balance of the additional tax imposed under
subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-017__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section shall be deposited in a subaccount of the Oregon
Conservation and Recreation Fund related to funding mitigation of the effects
of forest practices, as defined in ORS 527.620, on aquatic species. [2022 c.31 s5]
Sec.
6.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-017__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Section 5 of this 2022 Act applies to calendar years beginning on or after
January 1, 2023, and ending on December 31 of the earlier of the tax years in
which:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="321-017__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A cumulative total of at least $250 million of revenue from the tax imposed
under section 5 of this 2022 Act has been collected by the Department of
Revenue; or</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-017__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The incidental take permit described in section 5</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-017__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <paragraph eId="321-017__subsec_2__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this 2022 Act is
for any reason revoked or invalidated or otherwise withdrawn pursuant to a
final order, judgment or other decision that is not subject to further review
or appeal.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-017__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Director of the Department of Revenue shall notify the Legislative Counsel
and the Legislative Revenue Officer as soon as practicable following the end
date of the tax described in subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-017__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section. [2022 c.31 s6]
Sec.
7.
Section 5 of this 2022 Act is repealed on January 2, 2028, unless, before
January 1, 2028, the National Marine Fisheries Service or the United States
Fish and Wildlife Service, pursuant to the federal Endangered Species Act (16
U.S.C. 1531 to 1544):</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-017__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Approves a habitat conservation plan consistent with the terms of the Private
Forest Accord Report dated February 2, 2022, and published by the State
Forestry Department on February 7, 2022; and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-017__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Issues an incidental take permit related to the habitat conservation plan.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-035">
          <num>321.035</num>
          <heading>Determination of moneys available in Oregon Forest Land Protection Fund</heading>
          <subsection eId="321-035__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For purposes
of determining the moneys available in the Oregon Forest Land Protection Fund
described in ORS 477.750 as of February 16, such shall be the balance shown on
such date less the total of:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="321-035__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The unexpended balance as of February 16 of the amount budgeted to be expended
from the account for the fiscal year in which the determination is made; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-035__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The amount budgeted to be expended from the account for the following fiscal
year.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-035__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The insurance principle is recognized in providing funds for emergency forest
fire control.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-045">
          <num>321.045</num>
          <heading>Payment of tax; returns; estimated tax; payment</heading>
          <subsection eId="321-045__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The taxes
levied under ORS 321.015 shall be due and payable annually, on or before April
15, for the preceding calendar year. The tax shall be delinquent if not paid by
the due date, which shall be determined without regard to any extension of time
for filing the return.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-045__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the provisions relating to estimated tax payments provided in
subsections</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-045__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-045__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section, on or before April 15, each taxpayer
shall make out a return on the form prescribed by the Department of Revenue
showing the amount of the tax for which the taxpayer is liable for the
preceding calendar year and the other information the department considers
necessary to correctly determine the tax due and shall mail or deliver the
return, together with a remittance for the amount of the tax, to the office of
the department. The return shall be signed and verified by the taxpayer or a duly
authorized agent of the taxpayer. Whenever in its judgment good cause exists,
the department may allow upon written application made on or before the due
date further time not exceeding 30 days for filing a return.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-045__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All payments received under ORS 321.005 to 321.185 and 321.560 to 321.600 shall
be credited, first, to penalty and interest accrued, and then to tax due.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-045__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Each taxpayer expecting to incur a liability pursuant to this section in excess
of $1,500 for any calendar year shall, on forms prescribed by the Department of
Revenue, make and file with the department on or before the last day of the
month following the end of each calendar quarter an estimate of the taxpayer’s
tax liability for the year. At least one-quarter of the estimated tax shall be
remitted to the department with each estimated tax report and the balance shall
be remitted to the department on or before the last day of January of the
following calendar year, without regard to any extension of time for filing the
return.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-045__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the amount remitted with an estimated tax report filed on or before the due
date thereof is at least 25 percent of the tax of the taxpayer as due for the
calendar year preceding the year for which the report is made or at least 20
percent of the taxpayer’s tax liability as due for the year for which the
report is made, or 100 percent of the tax liability on the actual merchantable
forest products harvested for the calendar quarter preceding the due date of
the estimated tax report, no penalty or interest shall be charged. Otherwise a
penalty in the form of interest at the rate established under ORS 305.220 shall
be assessed for the period of delinquency calculated on the difference between
the payment made and the payment that would have been due had the taxpayer
estimated the liability for the quarter in an amount equal to the liability as
due for such quarter. The provisions of ORS chapters 305 and 314 relating to
penalties and interest shall not apply to the estimated tax payments described
in this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-145">
          <num>321.145</num>
          <heading>Tax revenue credited to suspense account; refunds</heading>
          <subsection eId="321-145__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The revenue
from the taxes levied by ORS 321.005 to 321.185 and 321.560 to 321.600 shall be
remitted to the State Treasurer who shall deposit it in a suspense account
established under the provisions of ORS 293.445.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-145__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding the provisions of ORS 291.238, the amount of moneys necessary
to pay refunds of the taxes levied under ORS 321.015</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-145__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>to</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-145__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>hereby is
appropriated continuously to the Department of Revenue from the suspense
account referred to in subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-145__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section, and shall be used by the
department for the payment of all refunds of taxes levied under ORS 321.015</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-145__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>to</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-145__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>that have been audited and approved by the department. Any penalties,
interest and taxes then due from the taxpayer shall be applied in that order in
computing any refund, and only the balance due the taxpayer, if any, shall be
refunded. The department shall on its records charge each refund against the
revenue from the tax with respect to which the refund is made.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-152">
          <num>321.152</num>
          <heading>Distribution of tax revenue</heading>
          <subsection eId="321-152__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to ORS 321.145</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-152__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>, moneys
remaining in the Department of Revenue’s suspense account referred to in ORS
321.145 on February 10, May 10, August 10 and November 10 of each year shall be
transferred to the respective appropriation accounts described in subsections</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-152__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>to</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-152__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-152__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>That part of the moneys derived from taxes levied by ORS 321.015</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-152__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>shall be
transferred to the Forest Research and Experiment Account described in ORS
321.185.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-152__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>That part of the moneys derived from taxes levied by ORS 321.015</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-152__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>shall be
transferred to the State Forestry Department Account referred to in ORS
526.060. Notwithstanding ORS 291.238, the moneys transferred to the State
Forestry Department Account under this section are appropriated continuously
for and shall be used by the State Forester, under the supervision and
direction of the State Board of Forestry, for the purposes of administering the
Oregon Forest Practices Act and the forest practices monitoring program.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-152__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>That part of the moneys derived from taxes levied by ORS 321.015</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-152__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>shall be
transferred to the Oregon Forest Land Protection Fund described in ORS 477.750.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-152__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>That part of the moneys derived from taxes levied by ORS 321.015</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-152__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>shall be
transferred to the subaccount established pursuant to ORS 350.520. [1985 c.759 s3;
1995 c.507 s2; 1999 c.968 s4; 2003 c.769 s4; 2013 c.639 s4]
Note: 321.152 was added
to and made a part of ORS chapter 321 by legislative action but was not added
to any smaller series therein. See Preface to Oregon Revised Statutes for
further explanation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-185">
          <num>321.185</num>
          <heading>Forest Research and Experiment Account; appropriation</heading>
          <subsection eId="321-185__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>There hereby
is established in the State Treasury in the General Fund an account to be known
as the Forest Research and Experiment Account, which account hereby is
appropriated continuously to the Higher Education Coordinating Commission for
distribution to Oregon State University for the purposes of ORS 526.215 and
526.225.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-185__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Forest Research and Experiment Account shall consist of allocations from
harvest taxes as provided in ORS 321.015</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-185__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-201">
          <num>321.201</num>
          <heading>Definition of “forestland” for ORS 321.201 to 321.222</heading>
          <content>
            <p>As used in ORS
321.201 to 321.222, “forestland” means either forestland, as defined in ORS
321.257, that is located in western Oregon or forestland, as defined in ORS
321.805, that is located in eastern Oregon.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-204">
          <num>321.204</num>
          <heading>Legislative findings and declarations</heading>
          <content>
            <p>The Legislative Assembly finds that an
accurate system of annually determining forestland values in this state is
vital to achieving a fair and equitable system of taxing the forest resources
of this state. The Legislative Assembly declares that an annual determination
of forestland values is the process that best achieves an accurate assessment
of forestland in this state.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-207">
          <num>321.207</num>
          <heading>Valuation models; rules</heading>
          <subsection eId="321-207__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Department of Revenue by rule shall develop
valuation models to be used to value forestland in western Oregon and eastern
Oregon.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-207__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The valuation models may consider forestland sales, stumpage values, immediate
harvest values, log prices or other commercially reasonable factors or data
that promote real market value analysis of forestland.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-210">
          <num>321.210</num>
          <heading>Proposed specially assessed values; notice; comments; hearing</heading>
          <subsection eId="321-210__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Pursuant to
the valuation models adopted by the Department of Revenue under ORS 321.207 and
for the purpose of certifying specially assessed values of forestland under ORS
321.354 and 321.833, for each tax year the Department of Revenue shall give notice
of proposed specially assessed values of forestland. The values shall be
proposed by the department on or before April 1 of the assessment year.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-210__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The specially assessed values proposed under this section and certified under
ORS 321.216 for forestland in western Oregon shall be for land classes FA, FB,
FC, FD, FE, FF, FG and FX. Specially assessed values also shall be proposed
under this section and certified under ORS 321.216 for forestland in eastern
Oregon.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-210__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department shall give notice of the proposed specially assessed values to:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="321-210__subsec_3__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>County assessors and associations, trade organizations and other persons that
the department, in its discretion, finds represent forestland owners; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-210__subsec_3__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Any other person that has made a written request to the department to be given
notice of proposed specially assessed values.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-210__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The notice required under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-210__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section must contain:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="321-210__subsec_3__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The proposed specially assessed values;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-210__subsec_3__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A description of the valuation model employed in determining the proposed
specially assessed values;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-210__subsec_3__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A summary of the market data used to determine the proposed specially assessed
values; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-210__subsec_3__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The date, time and location of the public hearing described in subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-210__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-210__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Following the giving of notice required under this section, members of the
public may submit written comments on the proposed specially assessed values to
the department. Written comments received by the department on or before May 1
of the assessment year for which the specially assessed values are proposed
shall be considered by the department prior to the department certifying
specially assessed values to the county assessors under ORS 321.216.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-210__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Prior to adopting specially assessed values of forestland for a tax year, the
department shall conduct a public hearing on the proposed specially assessed
values. Any person interested in providing testimony on the proposed specially
assessed values shall be given the opportunity to do so at the hearing.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-213">
          <num>321.213</num>
          <heading>Forestland value advisory committee</heading>
          <subsection eId="321-213__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>At any time, the Department of
Revenue may convene a forestland value advisory committee to assist the
department in developing a valuation model under ORS 321.207 or in determining
specially assessed values of forestland. If the department convenes a
committee, it shall be composed of members appointed by the Director of the
Department of Revenue. In appointing members, the director shall strive to
include representation of counties, the State Forestry Department and large and
small forestland owners from western Oregon and eastern Oregon.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-213__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Department of Revenue shall provide staff and administrative support to
facilitate the work of a committee convened by the department.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-216">
          <num>321.216</num>
          <heading>Certified specially assessed values</heading>
          <subsection eId="321-216__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>On or before June 1 of each
assessment year, the Department of Revenue shall adopt specially assessed
values of forestland, as of the assessment date for that year. The department
shall certify the specially assessed values of forestland in eastern Oregon to
the county assessors of eastern Oregon and the specially assessed values of
forestland in western Oregon to the county assessors of western Oregon.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-216__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The certified specially assessed values constitute:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="321-216__subsec_2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department’s determination of the real market value, as of the assessment
date for the tax year, of highest and best use forestland in the land class for
which the certification is being made; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-216__subsec_2__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The specially assessed values, as of the assessment date for the tax year, of
designated forestland that is assessed under ORS 321.354 and 321.833 in the
land class for which the certification is being made.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-216__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Upon receipt of the certified values, the county assessors shall develop tables
for each assessment year that reflect, for each class and area, the values
determined under this section and that express the values as values per acre.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-219">
          <num>321.219</num>
          <heading>Appeal of certified specially assessed values; notice; effect of decision modifying values; rules</heading>
          <subsection eId="321-219__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>At any time following certification of the
specially assessed values under ORS 321.216 and before July 1 of the tax year,
five or more taxpayers owning in the aggregate not less than five percent of
the total forestland in a single land market area may appeal any or all of the
specially assessed values so certified.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-219__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Appeals under this section shall be made to the Oregon Tax Court by filing a
joint petition with the tax court in the manner provided for appeals from
orders of the county property value appeals boards. The petition shall
designate one of the taxpayers as the representative of all of the taxpayers,
and all proceedings before the tax court and any appeal from its determination
shall be conducted procedurally as though the designated representative were
the only petitioner.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-219__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notice of the appeal shall be made in the manner prescribed by the Department
of Revenue by rule. The notice shall designate the specially assessed values
appealed and include a statement of the provisions of subsections</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-219__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-219__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-219__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Unless an appeal is resolved prior to September 15 of the tax year and results
in a change in a specially assessed value that was certified under ORS 321.216,
then notwithstanding the appeal of a certified specially assessed value, the
certified specially assessed values shall be entered on the assessment and tax
roll for the year and the property taxes for the tax year shall be imposed on
those values.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-219__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If a decision by the tax court, or by the Oregon Supreme Court following an
appeal of a tax court decision:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="321-219__subsec_5__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Results in a decrease in a specially assessed value certified under ORS
321.216, any refund of tax arising as a result of the decision shall be made by
reducing the tax imposed on forestland affected by the decision in the first
tax year following the decision.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-219__subsec_5__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Results in an increase in a specially assessed value certified under ORS
321.216, any additional taxes becoming due shall be payable without interest if
paid prior to the 16th day of the month following the month in which the final
order of the court is issued. If the additional taxes are not paid within this
period, the additional taxes shall thereafter be considered delinquent and
shall bear interest at the rate provided in ORS 311.505. [2001 c.860 s19; 2011
c.204 s11; 2023 c.29 s38]
Note: The amendments to
321.219 by section 38, chapter 29, Oregon Laws 2023, become operative July 1,
2024. See section 43, chapter 29, Oregon Laws 2023. The text that is operative
until July 1, 2024, is set forth for the user’s convenience.
321.219.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-219__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>At any time
following certification of the specially assessed values under ORS 321.216 and
before July 1 of the tax year, five or more taxpayers owning in the aggregate
not less than five percent of the total forestland in a single land market area
may appeal any or all of the specially assessed values so certified.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-219__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Appeals under this section shall be made to the Oregon Tax Court by filing a
joint petition with the tax court in the manner provided for appeals from
orders of the county boards of property tax appeals. The petition shall
designate one of the taxpayers as the representative of all of the taxpayers,
and all proceedings before the tax court and any appeal from its determination
shall be conducted procedurally as though the designated representative were
the only petitioner.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-219__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notice of the appeal shall be made in the manner prescribed by the Department
of Revenue by rule. The notice shall designate the specially assessed values
appealed and include a statement of the provisions of subsections</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-219__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-219__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-219__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Unless an appeal is resolved prior to September 15 of the tax year and results
in a change in a specially assessed value that was certified under ORS 321.216,
then notwithstanding the appeal of a certified specially assessed value, the
certified specially assessed values shall be entered on the assessment and tax
roll for the year and the property taxes for the tax year shall be imposed on
those values.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-219__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If a decision by the tax court, or by the Oregon Supreme Court following an
appeal of a tax court decision:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="321-219__subsec_5__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Results in a decrease in a specially assessed value certified under ORS
321.216, any refund of tax arising as a result of the decision shall be made by
reducing the tax imposed on forestland affected by the decision in the first
tax year following the decision.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-219__subsec_5__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Results in an increase in a specially assessed value certified under ORS
321.216, any additional taxes becoming due shall be payable without interest if
paid prior to the 16th day of the month following the month in which the final
order of the court is issued. If the additional taxes are not paid within this
period, the additional taxes shall thereafter be considered delinquent and
shall bear interest at the rate provided in ORS 311.505.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-222">
          <num>321.222</num>
          <heading>Jurisdiction of board of property tax appeals</heading>
          <content>
            <p>Any appeal of
forestland value that does not involve an appeal of a specially assessed value
certified under ORS 321.216 shall be made to the property value appeals board
in the manner prescribed in ORS 309.100. [2001 c.860 s20; 2023 c.29 s39]
Note: The amendments to
321.222 by section 39, chapter 29, Oregon Laws 2023, become operative July 1,
2024. See section 43, chapter 29, Oregon Laws 2023. The text that is operative
until July 1, 2024, is set forth for the user’s convenience.
321.222. Any appeal of
forestland value that does not involve an appeal of a specially assessed value
certified under ORS 321.216 shall be made to the board of property tax appeals
in the manner prescribed in ORS 309.100.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-257">
          <num>321.257</num>
          <heading>Definitions for ORS 321.257 to 321.390</heading>
          <subsection eId="321-257__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Department” means the Department of Revenue.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-257__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Forestland” means land in western Oregon that is being held or used for the
predominant purpose of growing and harvesting trees of a marketable species and
has been designated as forestland or land in western Oregon, the highest and
best use of which is the growing and harvesting of such trees. Trees of a
marketable species may vary in different areas in western Oregon and may change
as the utilization of forest trees changes. The size, age, location, quality
and condition of trees do not necessarily determine marketable species.
Forestland often contains isolated openings which because of rock outcrops,
river wash, swamps, chemical conditions of the soil, brush and other like
conditions prevent adequate stocking of such openings for the production of
trees of a marketable species. If the openings in their natural state are
necessary to hold the surrounding forestland in forest use through sound
management practices, the openings are deemed forestland. Forestland does not
include buildings, structures, machinery, equipment or fixtures erected upon,
under or above the soil. Forestland includes roads described in ORS 308.236.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-257__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Land class” or “land classes” means one of the eight classifications of
forestland, used for assessment purposes by the department, based upon State
Tax Commission Valuation Division Supplements published in 1967, and identified
in ORS 321.210.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-257__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“State Forester” means the State Forester or the authorized representative of
the State Forester.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-257__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Sustained yield management” means the growing and harvesting of timber crops
on a continuous basis on land that is primarily dedicated to timber production.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-257__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Taxing district” or “district” means each county, city, school district and
other corporation vested with the power to levy property taxes in western
Oregon.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-257__subsec_7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Timber” means all logs which can be measured in board feet and other forest
products as determined by department rule.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-257__subsec_8">
            <num>(8)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Western Oregon” means that portion of the state lying west of a line beginning
at the intersection of the northern boundary of the State of Oregon and the
western boundary of Wasco County, thence southerly along the western boundaries
of the counties of Wasco, Jefferson, Deschutes and Klamath to the southern
boundary of the State of Oregon.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-259">
          <num>321.259</num>
          <heading>Legislative findings</heading>
          <subsection eId="321-259__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Multiple taxation through a yearly ad valorem levy on both trees and forestland
managed in sustained yield timber operations discourages conservation, private
ownership and investment of capital.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-259__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The interests of this state, its residents and its future residents are best
served by sustained yield practices and taxing policies that encourage
production of forest resources for commerce, recreation and watersheds,
stabilize employment levels, prevent large population shifts and encourage
millage of timber products within Oregon.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-259__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Timber on private lands managed on a sustained yield basis should be treated as
a crop and not taxed as real property.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-259__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Forestland should be taxed based on the value of the forestland in timber
production.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-262">
          <num>321.262</num>
          <heading>Purposes</heading>
          <subsection eId="321-262__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>To impose with respect to forestlands in western Oregon a special assessment
program whereby the value of forestland is determined as prescribed in ORS
321.201 to 321.222.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-262__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>To establish a special assessment program as a means of:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="321-262__subsec_2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Recognizing the long-term nature of the forest crop and fostering the public
policy of Oregon to encourage the growing and harvesting of timber.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-262__subsec_2__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Protecting the public welfare by assuring that the people of this state and
future generations shall have the benefits to be derived from the continuous
production of forest products from private forestlands.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-262__subsec_2__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Promoting this state’s policy of encouraging forestry and the restocking of
forestlands to provide present and future benefits by enhancing the water
supply, preventing erosion, providing habitat for wildlife, providing scenic
and recreational opportunities and providing for needed products.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-267">
          <num>321.267</num>
          <heading>Lands not eligible for special assessment</heading>
          <subsection eId="321-267__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Forestland assessed by the Department of Revenue pursuant to ORS 308.505 to
308.674, 308.805 to 308.820 and 308.990.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-267__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Except as provided in ORS 321.347, land that is prepared using intensive
cultivation and tilling and on which all unwanted plant growth is controlled
continuously for the exclusive purpose of growing Christmas trees.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-267__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Land used for the purpose of growing hardwood timber, including but not limited
to hybrid cottonwood, if:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="321-267__subsec_3__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The land is prepared using intensive cultivation methods and is cleared of
competing vegetation for at least three years after tree planting;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-267__subsec_3__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The timber is of a species marketable as fiber for inclusion in the furnish for
manufacturing paper products;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-267__subsec_3__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The timber is harvested on a rotation cycle within 12 years after planting; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-267__subsec_3__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The land and timber are subject to intensive agricultural practices such as
fertilization, insect and disease control, cultivation and irrigation.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-267__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Small tract forestland qualified under ORS 321.700 to 321.754 and timber
harvested from small tract forestland qualified under ORS 321.700 to 321.754.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-272">
          <num>321.272</num>
          <heading>Exemption of timber from property taxation</heading>
          <content>
            <p>All timber in western Oregon shall
be exempt from ad valorem property taxation.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-347">
          <num>321.347</num>
          <heading>Land designations; classifications; certain election by landowners</heading>
          <subsection eId="321-347__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All land in western Oregon valued as forestland for ad valorem property tax
purposes on January 1, 1977, shall retain that classification for the purposes
of ORS 321.257 to 321.390 unless it is specifically excluded from the
provisions thereof or unless it is removed from that classification as provided
in ORS 321.359 or is no longer land the highest and best use of which is
forestland.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-347__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Land designated as forestland pursuant to ORS 321.605 to 321.680 (1975
Replacement Part) shall retain the original date of such designation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-347__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Lands classified as reforestation lands as of July 1, 1977, pursuant to ORS
321.255 to 321.360 (1975 Replacement Part) shall be considered to have been
designated as forestland from the date of original classification as
reforestation lands. Any lands so classified prior to February 1, 1972, shall
be presumed to have been designated not earlier than February 1, 1972.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-347__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Pursuant to the election of the owner, as provided in section 45, chapter 892,
Oregon Laws 1977, land which, as of January 1, 1977, was designated under the
provisions of ORS 321.705 to 321.765 (2001 Edition) shall be considered to have
been designated as forestland for the purposes of ORS 321.257 to 321.390 from
the date of the original designation under those provisions. Any lands so
designated prior to January 1, 1972, shall be presumed to have been designated
not earlier than January 1, 1972, for the purposes of additional taxes imposed
by ORS 308A.700 to 308A.733.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-348">
          <num>321.348</num>
          <heading>Assignment of forestland to land classes; change in class</heading>
          <subsection eId="321-348__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For each tax
year, forestland shall be assigned by the Department of Revenue to land classes
as defined in ORS 321.257.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-348__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Land classes assigned under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-348__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section may be changed
thereafter by the department upon the initiative of the department, or upon the
request of an owner, if further investigation reveals that the basis for the
land class determination was inaccurate. Any such redetermination of land class
shall be certified immediately to the county assessor.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-349">
          <num>321.349</num>
          <heading>Valuation of certain forestland at farm use value</heading>
          <subsection eId="321-349__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to
subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-349__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section, land that is changed from farm use special
assessment under ORS 308A.050 to 308A.128 to special assessment as forestland
under ORS 321.257 to 321.390, at the election of the owner made under rules
adopted by the Department of Revenue, shall not be valued under ORS 308.205,
308.232 and 321.257 to 321.390 for the tax year of the change and years
thereafter in which such special forestland assessment is in effect for the
land, but shall be valued under ORS 308A.050 to 308A.128, if:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="321-349__subsec_2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The land has been assessed under ORS 308A.050 to 308A.128 for at least the 10
consecutive years immediately prior to the year for which the change is first
effective;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-349__subsec_2__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The planting of the timber takes place after October 15, 1983, and qualifies
for the current tax year for special assessment as forestland under ORS 321.257
to 321.390;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-349__subsec_2__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The timber on the land is of an average age of less than 40 years; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-349__subsec_2__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The land is held by an owner having a total ownership of forestland in western
Oregon not in excess of 2,000 acres, as determined under subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-349__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this
section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-349__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If timber on land valued under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-349__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section reaches, for any
tax year, an average age of 40 years or more, this section shall cease to
apply. However, without application and without any additional tax, interest or
penalty, the land shall for that tax year and for each year thereafter for
which the land is qualified, be valued under ORS 308.205, 308.232 and 321.257
to 321.390.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-349__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In computing a forestland owner’s acreage for purposes of subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-349__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of
this section, total ownership of the owner’s forestland, as defined in ORS
321.257, in western Oregon shall be included.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-349__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <paragraph eId="321-349__subsec_4__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An owner may not have forestland valued under subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-349__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section if
the owner, or any individual having a share in the owner, has a spouse,
brother, sister, ancestor or lineal descendant who is an owner, or who holds a
share in an owner having forestland valued under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-349__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this
section.</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="321-349__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The county assessor may grant exceptions to paragraph</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-349__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this subsection if
the owner satisfactorily demonstrates that the combination of ownership with
the indicated relatives arose from bona fide business reasons other than a
desire to circumvent the 2,000 acre limitation imposed under subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-349__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of
this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-349__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>As used in this section, “total ownership” includes:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="321-349__subsec_5__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Forestland owned by an owner individually; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-349__subsec_5__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Forestland owned by any corporate or other group or entity in which an owner of
the corporation, group or entity owns a 10 percent or greater interest,
directly or indirectly, in the corporation, group or entity.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-354">
          <num>321.354</num>
          <heading>Common ownership minimum acreage requirements; specially assessed value and maximum assessed value of forestland of large landowners</heading>
          <subsection eId="321-354__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <paragraph eId="321-354__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The
Department of Revenue shall identify the forestland that is held in common
ownership of 5,000 acres or more as of the assessment date for each tax year.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-354__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Forestland that the department has identified under paragraph</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-354__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this
subsection that, for the previous tax year, was subject to small tract
forestland assessment shall be disqualified from small tract forestland
assessment and shall be subject to special assessment as provided in this
section as of the first tax year the forestland is held in common ownership of
5,000 acres or more.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-354__subsec_1__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For purposes of this subsection, “forestland” includes land that meets the
definition of forestland under ORS 321.805.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-354__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Forestland assessed under this section shall have a specially assessed value
per acre equal to the value certified to the county assessor for the tax year
under ORS 321.216 for the applicable land class of the forestland.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-354__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For each land class described in ORS 321.210, the forestland maximum assessed
value per acre shall equal 103 percent of the forestland assessed value per
acre for the preceding tax year or 100 percent of the forestland maximum
assessed value per acre for the preceding tax year, whichever is greater.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-354__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <paragraph eId="321-354__subsec_4__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The assessor shall compute the assessed value of forestland by multiplying the
acreage of the forestland in each land class by the lesser of:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="321-354__subsec_4__subsec_a__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The specially assessed value per acre; or</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="321-354__subsec_4__subsec_a__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The maximum assessed value per acre.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-354__subsec_4__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the forestland being assessed consists of different land classes, the
assessed value of the forestland shall be the sum of the assessed values
computed for each land class under paragraph</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-354__subsec_4__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this subsection.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-354__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-354__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section, the forestland shall be
assessed as provided in ORS 308.232 if the real market value of the forestland
is less than the value established under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-354__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-354__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For purposes of this section:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="321-354__subsec_6__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall certify to the county assessor of a county in which
forestland identified in subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-354__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section is located a list of
the property tax accounts containing forestland so identified.</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="321-354__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Forestland shall be considered to be in common ownership if the forestland is
owned by the person directly or is owned by a corporation, partnership,
association or other entity in which the person owns a majority interest.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-354__subsec_1__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Additional taxes may not be imposed as a result of a disqualification under
subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-354__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section.</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="321-354__subsec_1__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The notification requirements and other procedures that the county assessor
must follow in disqualifying forestland do not apply to a disqualification
occurring under subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-354__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section.</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="321-354__subsec_1__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall notify the county assessor of forestland identified under
subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-354__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <paragraph eId="321-354__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this section that is located in that county.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-358">
          <num>321.358</num>
          <heading>Application for designation as forestland; special filing date for change in highest and best use; contents; approval</heading>
          <subsection eId="321-358__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An owner of land desiring that
it be designated as forestland shall make application to the county assessor on
or before April 1 of the assessment year for which special assessment as
forestland is first desired, and the owner may also do so within 30 days of
receipt of notice of its assessment as omitted property.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-358__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-358__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section, an owner of land may apply to
the county assessor by December 15 to have the land designated as forestland
for the assessment year if:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="321-358__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For the prior assessment year the land had been forestland by reason of the
land being highest and best use forestland; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-358__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For the current assessment year the land is being assessed at a value
reflecting a use other than highest and best use forestland.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-358__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The application shall be made upon forms prepared by the Department of Revenue
and supplied by the county assessor, and shall include the following:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="321-358__subsec_3__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A description of all land the applicant desires to be designated as forestland.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-358__subsec_3__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Date of acquisition.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-358__subsec_3__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Whether the land is being held or used for the predominant purpose of growing
and harvesting trees of marketable species.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-358__subsec_3__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Whether there is a forest management plan for it.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-358__subsec_3__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If so, whether the plan is being implemented, and the nature and extent of
implementation.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-358__subsec_3__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Whether the land is used for grazing.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-358__subsec_3__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Whether the land has been platted under ORS chapter 92.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-358__subsec_3__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Whether the land is timberland subject to ORS chapter 477, and if it is not,
the reasons therefor.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-358__subsec_3__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Whether the land, or any of it, is subject to a lease or option which permits
it to be used for any purpose other than the growing and harvesting of trees.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-358__subsec_3__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A summary of past experience and activity of the applicant in growing and
harvesting trees.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-358__subsec_3__subsec_k">
              <num>(k)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A summary of current and continuing activity of the applicant in growing and
harvesting trees.</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="321-358__subsec_3__subsec_k__subsec_L">
                <num>(L)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>A statement that the applicant is aware of the potential tax liability involved
when the land ceases to be designated as forestland.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-358__subsec_3__subsec_m">
              <num>(m)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An affirmation that the statements contained in the application are true.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-358__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The county assessor shall approve an application for forestland designation if
the assessor finds that the land is properly classifiable as forestland. The
county assessor shall not find land properly classifiable as forestland if:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="321-358__subsec_4__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The application states the land is not being held or used for the predominant
purpose of growing and harvesting trees of marketable species; or</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-358__subsec_4__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Subject to the provisions of ORS 321.257, the land does not substantially meet
minimum stocking or acreage requirements under rules adopted by the department.
Otherwise, the determination whether the land is properly classifiable as
forestland shall be made with due regard to all relevant evidence and without
any one or more items of evidence necessarily being determinative.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-358__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The application shall be deemed to have been approved unless, within three
months of the date such application was delivered to the assessor or prior to
August 15, whichever is later, the assessor shall notify the applicant in
writing of the extent to which the application is denied. [Formerly 321.618;
1981 c.804 s93; 1983 c.462 s5; 1983 c.657 s2; 1989 c.1083 s9; 1991 c.459 s293;
1997 c.541 ss392,392a; 1999 c.314 s92; 1999 c.1078 s74; 2003 c.621 s17]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-359">
          <num>321.359</num>
          <heading>Removal of designation; appeal from reassessment or denial; requalification</heading>
          <subsection eId="321-359__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <paragraph eId="321-359__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When land
has once been designated as forestland either as a result of an application
being filed therefor or through the application of ORS 321.347</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-359__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>or</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-359__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>, it
shall be valued as such until the assessor removes the forestland designation
under paragraph</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="321-359__subsec_4__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this subsection.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-359__subsec_4__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The county assessor shall remove the forestland designation upon:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="321-359__subsec_4__subsec_b__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Notification by the taxpayer to the assessor to remove the designation;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="321-359__subsec_4__subsec_b__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Sale or transfer to an ownership making it exempt from ad valorem property
taxation;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="321-359__subsec_4__subsec_b__subsec_C">
                <num>(C)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Discovery by the assessor that the land is no longer forestland; or</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="321-359__subsec_4__subsec_b__subsec_D">
                <num>(D)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The act of recording a subdivision plat under ORS chapter 92.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-359__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A taxpayer whose application filed under ORS 321.358 has been denied in whole
or in part, or a taxpayer whose forestland has had the designation thereof
removed in whole or in part, may appeal to the tax court within the time and in
the manner provided in ORS 305.404 to 305.560.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-359__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If, under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-359__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <paragraph eId="321-359__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <subparagraph eId="321-359__subsec_1__subsec_b__subsec_D">
                <num>(D)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>of this section, the county assessor removes the
forestland designation upon the act of recording a subdivision plat, the land,
or a part of the land, may be requalified for forestland designation upon:</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-359__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Payment of all additional tax and applicable interest that remains due and
owing on the land;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-359__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Submission by the owner of an application for designation as forestland;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-359__subsec_1__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Meeting all of the qualifications for designation as forestland; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-359__subsec_1__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Meeting the requirements, if any, of applicable local government zoning
ordinances with regard to minimum lot or parcel acreage for forest use. [Formerly
321.619; 1983 c.462 s6; 1983 c.563 s2; 1985 c.759 s24a; 1987 c.158 s52; 1991
c.459 s294; 1995 c.650 s94; 1999 c.314 s51; 2003 c.621 s18]</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-362">
          <num>321.362</num>
          <heading>Notation of forestland on tax roll for potential additional tax liability</heading>
          <subsection eId="321-362__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>or</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-362__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>. That notation
shall not be made with respect to parcels of undesignated forestland.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-366">
          <num>321.366</num>
          <heading>Date on which disqualification of forestland is effective; timely notice of disqualification required</heading>
          <subsection eId="321-366__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding ORS 308.210, 311.405 or 311.410,
if land designated as forestland is subject to disqualification by the county
assessor as a result of the discovery that the land is no longer forestland,
the disqualification shall be deemed to occur as of the January 1 assessment
date of the assessment year in which the discovery occurs.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-366__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This section applies only if notice of the disqualification is mailed by the
county assessor prior to August 15 of the tax year for which the
disqualification of the land is asserted.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-367">
          <num>321.367</num>
          <heading>Forestland management; effect of failure to manage forestland in accordance with management plan; rules</heading>
          <subsection eId="321-367__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Forester shall identify all
of the forestlands that fail to meet the minimum stocking required under ORS
527.610 to 527.770 and that are therefore underproductive as described under
ORS 526.455.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-367__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>At any time the State Forester has reason to believe that forestland is not
being managed as forestland, the State Forester shall review the owner’s
management plan, if any, and inspect the property. Subject to subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-367__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of
this section, the State Forester shall advise the owner as prescribed in
subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-367__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section if the State Forester determines the land is not
being managed in accordance with a plan that provides for:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="321-367__subsec_3__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Regeneration of all suitable nonstocked land;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-367__subsec_3__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Maintenance of a free-to-grow condition;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-367__subsec_3__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Protection from fire, insects, disease, animal damage, undesirable vegetative
competition; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-367__subsec_3__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Final harvest.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-367__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <paragraph eId="321-367__subsec_3__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The State Forester shall advise the owner that the land is not being managed in
accordance with a plan that meets the criteria set forth in subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-367__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of
this section and that a plan for the land that does meet the criteria must be
developed and activated within one year after the date of the advisement.</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="321-367__subsec_2__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>At the request of the owner, the State Forester shall assign a forester or
provide a listing of foresters to assist the owner in developing and
implementing an appropriate management plan for the land.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-367__subsec_2__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>As soon as practicable after the time indicated in the advisement has expired,
the State Forester shall view the land to determine if the land is being
managed in accordance with a plan that meets the criteria set forth in
subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-367__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section. If, upon inspection, the State Forester finds
that the land is not being so managed, the State Forester shall notify the
owner and the county assessor.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-367__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The county assessor, upon receipt of the notice from the State Forester, shall
cease to treat that land as forestland under ORS 321.257 to 321.390 and shall
value the land as prescribed under ORS 308.146 and 308.232.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-367__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If at the time that the State Forester views the land under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-367__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <paragraph eId="321-367__subsec_3__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this section, it is determined that a change in ownership has occurred, the
State Forester shall notify the new owner as required under subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-367__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of
this section in the manner of the original notification.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-367__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When the owner of land disqualified from forestland assessment provides
satisfactory information to the State Forester of subsequent action taken to
correct the deficiency resulting in the disqualification of land, or provides an
acceptable management plan to correct such deficiency, the State Forester shall
so indicate to the county assessor. The assessor shall then assess the land
under ORS 321.257 to 321.390, if the land is otherwise qualified for such
assessment.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-367__subsec_7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Forester shall adopt rules necessary to carry out the purposes of
this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-390">
          <num>321.390</num>
          <heading>Land used to grow certain hardwood to be assessed as farm use land; application required for unzoned land</heading>
          <subsection eId="321-390__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Land described in ORS 321.267</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-390__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>(relating to
hardwood timberland, including hybrid cottonwood timberland) shall be assessed
as farm use land under ORS 308A.050 to 308A.128.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-390__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <paragraph eId="321-390__subsec_2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If land is or becomes land described under ORS 321.267</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-390__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>and the land is not
located within an exclusive farm use zone, the owner shall make application for
special valuation as farm use land in the manner provided under ORS 308A.077,
as follows:
(A)
If the change in use takes place on or after July 1, the owner shall file the
application on or before April 1 of the following year.
(B)
If the change in use takes place prior to July 1, the owner shall file the
application on or before August 1 of the same year.</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="321-390__subsec_3__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If an application is filed as provided under this subsection, the owner shall
have seven years beginning with the first year of classification to meet the
income requirements of ORS 308A.071 and need not meet the two-year farm use
requirements of ORS 308A.068.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-550">
          <num>321.550</num>
          <heading>Notice of intent to harvest; rules; effect of failure to file notice; penalty</heading>
          <subsection eId="321-550__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No person
shall harvest or cause to be harvested any timber from land in Oregon without
first having notified the State Forester in writing with a copy to the
Department of Revenue on forms prepared by the State Forester and the
department of intent to harvest pursuant to ORS 321.005 to 321.185, 321.560 to
321.600 and 321.700 to 321.754.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-550__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The notification shall specify where and when the harvest will take place and
the nature of the harvest and shall include maps and other data as required by
the State Forester and the department. The department shall establish by rule
procedures to assure the receipt of the tax returns sent out or a report of
nonharvest from the person. The department shall conduct field and office
audits to ascertain the correctness of any timber tax return.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-550__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <paragraph eId="321-550__subsec_3__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a person fails to file a written notice as required in subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-550__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of
this section with respect to any harvest over 5,000 board feet, the department
shall notify the person. If, after the person has been notified, the person
fails to file a written notice as required in subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-550__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section
with respect to any subsequent harvest over 5,000 board feet, there shall be
added to the amount of the timber tax required to be shown on the return as a
result of the subsequent harvest a delinquency penalty of $250 for each
violation occurring within a calendar year. The department shall collect the
penalty in the same manner as taxes are collected.</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="321-550__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>No penalty shall be imposed under this subsection if a penalty for failure to
file the notice with the State Forester has been imposed under ORS 527.992.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-550__subsec_1__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The delinquency penalty shall first be added to the small tract forestland
timber severance tax imposed under ORS 321.700 to 321.754, if applicable to the
harvest. If the small tract forestland timber severance tax is not applicable,
the delinquency penalty shall be added to the forest products harvest tax
imposed under ORS 321.005 to 321.185.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-560">
          <num>321.560</num>
          <heading>Audit of returns; interest and penalties upon failure to file return or pay tax</heading>
          <subsection eId="321-560__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The provisions of ORS chapters 305 and 314 as to the audit and examination
of reports and returns, determination of deficiencies, liens, assessments,
claims for refund, conferences and appeals to the Oregon Tax Court, and the
procedures relating thereto, apply to the determination of taxes, penalties and
interest imposed under ORS 321.005 to 321.185, 321.560 to 321.600 or 321.700 to
321.754, except where the context requires otherwise.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-560__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If a taxpayer fails to file a return required by ORS 321.045 or 321.700 to
321.754, or fails to pay a tax at the time the tax becomes due, there shall be
added to the amount of tax required to be shown on the return a delinquency
penalty of five percent of the amount of such tax.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-560__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the failure to file a return continues for a period in excess of three
months after the due date, there shall be added to the amount of tax required
to be shown on the return a failure to file penalty of 20 percent of the amount
of such tax. This penalty is in addition to the delinquency penalty imposed by
subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-560__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-560__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If all or any part of the delinquency or deficiency for which a determination is
made is due to fraud or an intent to evade the provisions of ORS 321.005 to
321.185, 321.560 to 321.600 or 321.700 to 321.754, or the rules adopted
thereunder, a penalty of 100 percent of such delinquency or deficiency shall be
added, plus interest at the rate established under ORS 305.220, computed on the
full amount of the delinquency or deficiency plus penalty, from the time the
return was due.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-560__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For purposes of this section, the amount of tax required to be shown on the
return shall be reduced by the amount of any part of the tax that is paid on or
before the date prescribed for payment of the tax and by the amount of any
credit against the tax that may be lawfully claimed upon the return.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-560__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A delinquent tax or a deficiency shall bear interest at the rate established
under ORS 305.220 from the time the return was due. [Formerly 321.055; 1991
c.459 s306; 1995 c.53 s4; 1995 c.350 s5; 1995 c.650 s95; 2003 c.454 s55; 2003
c.621 s40a; 2017 c.278 s14]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-570">
          <num>321.570</num>
          <heading>Warrant for collection of delinquent taxes</heading>
          <subsection eId="321-570__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any tax imposed by ORS
321.005 to 321.185, 321.560 to 321.600 or 321.700 to 321.754, or any portion of
the tax, is not paid within 30 days after the date that the written notice and
demand for payment required under ORS 305.895 is mailed, the Department of
Revenue may issue a warrant for the payment of the amount of the tax, with the
added penalties, interest and cost of executing the warrant. A copy of the
warrant shall be mailed or delivered to the taxpayer by the department at the
taxpayer’s last-known address.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-570__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>At any time after issuing a warrant under this section, the department may
record the warrant in the County Clerk Lien Record of any county of this state.
Recording of the warrant has the effect described in ORS 205.125. After recording
a warrant, the department may direct the sheriff for the county in which the
warrant is recorded to levy upon and sell the real and personal property of the
taxpayer found within that county, and to levy upon any currency of the
taxpayer found within that county, for the application of the proceeds or
currency against the amount reflected in the warrant and the sheriff’s cost of
executing the warrant. The sheriff shall proceed on the warrant in the same
manner prescribed by law for executions issued against property pursuant to a
judgment, and is entitled to the same fees as provided for executions issued
against property pursuant to a judgment. The fees of the sheriff shall be added
to and collected as a part of the warrant liability.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-570__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the discretion of the department a warrant under this section may be
directed to any agent authorized by the department to collect this tax. In the
execution of the warrant the agent has the powers conferred by law upon
sheriffs, but is entitled to no fee or compensation in excess of actual
expenses paid in the performance of such duty.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-570__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Until a warrant issued under this section is satisfied in full, the department
has the same remedies to enforce the claim for taxes against the taxpayer as if
the state had recovered judgment against the taxpayer for the amount of the
tax. [Formerly 321.075; 1989 c.625 s78; 2003 c.454 s56; 2003 c.576 s203; 2003
c.621 s41a; 2011 c.389 s3; 2011 c.661 s6]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-580">
          <num>321.580</num>
          <heading>Effect of failure or refusal to make return</heading>
          <content>
            <p>If any taxpayer neglects or
refuses to make a return required to be made by ORS 321.005 to 321.185, 321.560
to 321.600 or 321.700 to 321.754, the Department of Revenue is authorized to
determine the tax due, based upon any information in its possession or that may
come into its possession. The department shall give the taxpayer written notice
of the tax and delinquency charges and the tax and delinquency charges shall be
a lien from the time of severance. If the tax and delinquency charges are not
paid within 30 days from the mailing of the notice, the department shall
proceed to collect the tax in the manner provided in ORS 321.570. [Formerly
321.092; 2003 c.454 s57; 2003 c.621 s42a]</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-600">
          <num>321.600</num>
          <heading>Tax as debt; collection; limitation</heading>
          <content>
            <p>All taxes, interest and penalties due and
unpaid under ORS 321.005 to 321.185, 321.560 to 321.600 or 321.700 to 321.754
constitute a debt due the State of Oregon and may be collected, together with
interest, penalty and costs, by appropriate judicial proceeding, which remedy
is in addition to all other existing remedies. However, no proceeding for the
collection of taxes under ORS 321.005 to 321.185, 321.560 to 321.600 or 321.700
to 321.754 shall be instituted after the expiration of six years from the date
the taxes were due. [Formerly 321.105; 2003 c.454 s58; 2003 c.621 s43a]</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-609">
          <num>321.609</num>
          <heading>Enforcement of certain statutes by department; rules</heading>
          <subsection eId="321-609__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>ORS 321.005
to 321.185, 321.560 to 321.600 and 321.700 to 321.754 shall be enforced and the
taxes imposed by ORS 321.005 to 321.185, 321.560 to 321.600 and 321.700 to
321.754 shall be collected by the Department of Revenue, which shall have the
power to prescribe forms and to adopt rules for the ascertainment, assessment
and collection of the taxes imposed by ORS 321.005 to 321.185, 321.560 to
321.600 or 321.700 to 321.754.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-609__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For the purpose of determining the taxes imposed by ORS 321.005 to 321.185,
321.560 to 321.600 or 321.700 to 321.754, the department may:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="321-609__subsec_2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Require any person to furnish any information deemed necessary.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-609__subsec_2__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Examine the books, records and files of such person.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-609__subsec_2__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Subpoena and examine witnesses and administer oaths.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-609__subsec_2__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Enter upon and inspect the land of any owner of the land from which any timber
has been harvested. [Formerly 321.135; 1999 c.21 s55; 2003 c.454 s59; 2003
c.621 s44a]</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-682">
          <num>321.682</num>
          <heading>Confidentiality of reports, returns and appraisal data</heading>
          <subsection eId="321-682__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Except as
otherwise specifically provided by law, it shall be unlawful for the Department
of Revenue or any officer or employee of the department to divulge or make
known in any manner the amount of the tax or any particulars set forth or
disclosed in any report or return required to be filed under ORS 321.045 or
321.741 or any appraisal data collected to make determinations of specially
assessed value of forestland pursuant to ORS 321.201 to 321.222. It shall be
unlawful for any person or entity to whom information is disclosed or given by
the department pursuant to ORS 321.684</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-682__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>or any other provision of state law
to divulge or use such information for any purpose other than that specified in
the provisions of law authorizing the use or disclosure. No subpoena or
judicial order shall be issued compelling the department or any of its officers
or employees, or any person who has acquired information pursuant to ORS
321.684</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-682__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>or any other provision of state law, to divulge or make known the
amount of tax or any particulars set forth or disclosed in any report or return
except where the taxpayer’s liability for timber tax is to be adjudicated by
the court from which such process issues.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-682__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>As used in this section, “officer,” “employee” or “person” includes an
authorized representative of the officer, employee or person, or any former
officer, employee or person, or an authorized representative of such former
officer, employee or person.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-684">
          <num>321.684</num>
          <heading>Authority of department to make certain disclosures</heading>
          <subsection eId="321-684__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The
Department of Revenue may:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="321-684__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Furnish to any taxpayer or authorized representative, upon request of the
taxpayer or authorized representative, a copy of the taxpayer’s forest products
harvest tax report or return required by ORS 321.045 or 321.741 that is filed
with the department for any year, or a copy of any report filed by the taxpayer
in connection with the return.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-684__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Publish a list of taxpayers who are entitled to unclaimed tax refunds.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-684__subsec_1__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Publish statistics classified so as to prevent the identification of taxable
value or any particulars contained in any report or return.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-684__subsec_1__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Disclose a taxpayer’s name, address and Social Security number or employer
identification number to the extent necessary in connection with the processing
and mailing of forms for any report or return required in the administration of
ORS 321.045 and 321.741.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-684__subsec_1__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Disclose to the State Forester, upon request of the forester, for the purpose
of soliciting nominations and recommendations referred to in ORS 526.610, the
names of producers meeting producer class qualifications established under ORS
526.610 who filed forest products harvest tax returns.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-684__subsec_1__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Disclose appraisal data collected to make determinations of specially assessed
value of forestland under ORS 321.201 to 321.222 to any member of a forestland
value advisory committee the department has convened under ORS 321.213.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-684__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department also may disclose and give access to information described in
ORS 321.682 to:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="321-684__subsec_2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Commissioner of Internal Revenue or authorized representative, for tax
purposes only.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-684__subsec_2__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The United States Forest Service, Bureau of Land Management and the State
Forestry Department pursuant to their regulatory programs and for investigative
purposes related to timber theft.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-684__subsec_2__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Attorney General, assistants and employees in the Department of Justice or
other legal representative of the State of Oregon, to the extent the department
considers disclosure or access necessary for the performance of the duties of
advising or representing the department pursuant to ORS 321.045 and 321.741.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-684__subsec_2__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Employees of the State of Oregon, other than the Department of Revenue or
Department of Justice, to the extent the department considers disclosure or
access necessary for such employees to perform their duties under contracts or
agreements between the department and any other department, agency or
subdivision of the State of Oregon in the department’s administration of the
tax laws.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-684__subsec_2__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Legislative Revenue Officer or the authorized representative of the
Legislative Revenue Officer upon compliance with ORS 173.850. The officer or
representative may not remove from the premises of the department any materials
that would reveal the identity of any taxpayer or any other person or the
volume of harvest and value reported on individual returns and reports.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-684__subsec_2__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Any agency of the State of Oregon, or any person, or any officer or employee of
the agency or person to whom disclosure or access is given by state law and not
otherwise referred to in this section, including but not limited to the
Secretary of State as Auditor of Public Accounts under section 2, Article VI of
the Constitution of the State of Oregon.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-684__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Each officer or employee of the department and each person described or
referred to in subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-684__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <paragraph eId="321-684__subsec_2__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>to</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-684__subsec_2__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this section to whom disclosure or
access to the tax information is given under subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-684__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section or
any other provision of state law, prior to beginning employment or the
performance of duties involving such disclosure or access, shall be advised in
writing of the provisions of ORS 321.682 and 321.686 relating to penalties for
the violation of ORS 321.682, and shall, as a condition of employment or
performance of duties, execute a certificate for the department, in a form
prescribed by the department, stating in substance that the person has read
these provisions of law, that the person has had them explained and that the
person is aware of the penalties for the violation of ORS 321.682.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-686">
          <num>321.686</num>
          <heading>Penalty for violation of ORS 321.682</heading>
          <content>
            <p>Violation of ORS 321.682 is subject to a
fine not exceeding $5,000 or, if committed by an officer or employee of the
state, dismissal or removal from office or employment, or both fine and
dismissal or removal from office or employment. [1989 c.1083 s20; 2005 c.94 s106]
SMALL
TRACT FORESTLAND PROGRAM</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-700">
          <num>321.700</num>
          <heading>Definitions for ORS 321.700 to 321.754</heading>
          <subsection eId="321-700__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Common ownership” means direct ownership by one or more individuals or
ownership by a corporation, partnership, association or other entity in which
an individual owns a majority interest.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-700__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Contiguous” means having a common boundary that is greater than a single
point.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-700__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Contiguous parcels”:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="321-700__subsec_3__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Includes parcels separated by public or county roads, state highways,
nonnavigable streams or nonnavigable rivers.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-700__subsec_3__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Does not include parcels that are separated by an interstate highway, a
navigable stream or a navigable river, unless there is an underpass, a bridge
or another direct access between the separated parcels.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-700__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Department” means the Department of Revenue.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-700__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Eastern Oregon” means that portion of the State of Oregon lying east of a line
beginning at the intersection of the northern boundary of the state and the
western boundary of Wasco County, thence southerly along the western boundaries
of the counties of Wasco, Jefferson, Deschutes and Klamath to the southern
boundary of the state.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-700__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Forestland” means land that meets the definition of forestland under ORS
321.257 if the land is located in western Oregon or land that meets the
definition of forestland in ORS 321.805 if located in eastern Oregon.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-700__subsec_7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Harvest” means the point at which timber that has been cut, severed or removed
for purposes of sale or use is first measured in the ordinary course of
business as determined by reference to common practice in the timber industry.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-700__subsec_8">
            <num>(8)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Land class” means a forestland land class described in ORS 321.210 or eastern
Oregon forestland.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-700__subsec_9">
            <num>(9)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Owner of timber” has the meaning given that term in ORS 321.005.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-700__subsec_10">
            <num>(10)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Parcel” means a quantity of land that is capable of being described in a
single description by a closed traverse, as one or more subsections or sections
of a township, as one or more lots, blocks or tracts in a subdivision or as one
or more tax lots.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-700__subsec_11">
            <num>(11)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Small tract forestland” means forestland subject to assessment under ORS
321.700 to 321.754 and from which the harvesting of timber is subject to
severance taxation under ORS 321.700 to 321.754.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-700__subsec_12">
            <num>(12)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Taxpayer” means the owner of timber at time of harvest.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-700__subsec_13">
            <num>(13)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Timber” includes logs that are capable of being measured in board feet and
that meet or exceed minimum sawmill grade and other forest products determined
by the Department of Revenue by rule.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-700__subsec_14">
            <num>(14)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Unit of proper measurement” means any unit of measurement commonly used in the
timber industry for measuring timber and harvested timber products.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-700__subsec_15">
            <num>(15)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Western Oregon” means that portion of the State of Oregon lying west of a line
beginning at the intersection of the northern boundary of the state and the western
boundary of Wasco County, thence southerly along the western boundaries of the
counties of Wasco, Jefferson, Deschutes and Klamath to the southern boundary of
the state.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-703">
          <num>321.703</num>
          <heading>Legislative findings and declarations</heading>
          <subsection eId="321-703__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Legislative Assembly finds that:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="321-703__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Oregon forests are dynamic ecosystems that make vital contributions to all
Oregonians. Environmental benefits of forests include habitats for diverse life
forms, clean and oxygenated air, clean, filtered and recycled water and
stabilized productive soil. Economic benefits of forests include renewable raw
material for paper and wood products used by everyone in daily living. Social
benefits of forests include scenic landscapes and vistas, open space, solitude
and outdoor recreation.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-703__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Healthy productive forests provide a sustainable flow of goods, services,
values and products.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-703__subsec_1__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Private family and nonindustrial forestlands are important parts of the forest
resource base of this state. Private family and nonindustrial forestlands make
major contributions to the economy of this state and provide many other social
and environmental benefits.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-703__subsec_1__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Because of the wide array of management goals and objectives that apply to
private family and nonindustrial forestlands, these forestlands provide a great
range of valuable forest diversity across the landscape of this state.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-703__subsec_1__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Many lower gradient streams, which are key components of numerous watersheds
and are extremely important for some aquatic species, flow through private family
and nonindustrial forestlands.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-703__subsec_1__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The interests of this state, its residents and its future residents are best
served by sustainable forest practices and taxing policies that encourage
maintaining and establishing diverse forest resources for watersheds, commerce,
recreation and stabilized employment levels. These practices and policies
prevent shifts in population and encourage the processing of forest products
within Oregon.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-703__subsec_1__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Timber on private land that is managed on a sustainable basis should be treated
as a crop and not taxed as real property.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-703__subsec_1__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A tax imposed at the time of harvest coincides with the cash flow of small
timber operations and recognizes the hazards and uncertainties involved in
growing a long-term timber crop on a sustainable basis.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-703__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Legislative Assembly declares the purposes of the small tract forestland
tax option program established under ORS 321.700 to 321.754 are to:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="321-703__subsec_2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Impose property taxes on forestland values that are annually determined and
adjusted as described in ORS 321.201 to 321.222 and then specially assessed;
and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-703__subsec_2__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Impose a severance tax on the harvesting of timber from small tract forestland
in order to:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="321-703__subsec_2__subsec_b__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Recognize the long-term nature of the forest crop and foster the public policy
of this state to encourage the growing and harvesting of timber;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="321-703__subsec_2__subsec_b__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Protect the public welfare by ensuring that the people of this state and future
generations will have the benefits to be derived from the continuous production
of forest products from privately held small tract forestland;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="321-703__subsec_2__subsec_b__subsec_C">
                <num>(C)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Promote the public policy of this state to encourage forestry and the
restocking of forestlands in order to provide present and future benefits,
including but not limited to water supply enhancement, erosion prevention,
wildlife habitat, scenic and recreational opportunities and needed forest
products;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="321-703__subsec_2__subsec_b__subsec_D">
                <num>(D)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Produce revenues for local taxing districts;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="321-703__subsec_2__subsec_b__subsec_E">
                <num>(E)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Match the incidence of taxation with the realization of the economic benefits
of harvest; and</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="321-703__subsec_2__subsec_b__subsec_F">
                <num>(F)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Encourage the establishment of new forests on denuded, nonstocked or
underproducing forestland.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-706">
          <num>321.706</num>
          <heading>Application for small tract forestland qualification; contents; filing deadlines; review; appeal</heading>
          <subsection eId="321-706__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An owner of forestland seeking to have the
forestland qualified under ORS 321.700 to 321.754 shall apply to the county
assessor of the county in which the forestland is located for qualification of
the forestland as small tract forestland. If the forestland to be qualified is
located in more than one county, the owner shall apply for qualification to the
county assessor of each county in which the forestland is located.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-706__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An application shall be made on a form prescribed by the Department of Revenue
and supplied by the county assessor that contains:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="321-706__subsec_2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The name and address of the forestland owner;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-706__subsec_2__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The taxpayer identification number of the forestland owner;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-706__subsec_2__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A statement listing the county and containing a description sufficient to
identify the location of all land for which small tract forestland
qualification is sought;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-706__subsec_2__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A statement describing the uses of the land for which qualification as small
tract forestland is sought;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-706__subsec_2__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A statement indicating the extent to which the land that has been the subject
of the application has been platted under ORS chapter 92;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-706__subsec_2__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The total acreage of Oregon forestland owned or held in common ownership by the
owner;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-706__subsec_2__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A statement that the applicant is aware of the potential tax liability that
arises under ORS 308A.707 upon disqualification of small tract forestland;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-706__subsec_2__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An affirmation that the statements contained in the application are true; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-706__subsec_2__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Any other relevant information the department may prescribe.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-706__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The applicant shall file the application with the county assessor on or before
the later of:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="321-706__subsec_3__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>April 1 of the first assessment year for which the forestland is to be
qualified as small tract forestland;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-706__subsec_3__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In the case of land that is omitted property, within 30 days of the notice of
assessment of the property as omitted property; or</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-706__subsec_3__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>December 15 of the first assessment year for which the forestland is to be
qualified as small tract forestland if:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="321-706__subsec_3__subsec_c__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>For the prior assessment year the land was highest and best use forestland; and</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="321-706__subsec_3__subsec_c__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>For the current assessment year the land is being assessed at a value
reflecting a use other than highest and best use forestland.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-706__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The county assessor shall review an application and qualify the forestland
under ORS 321.700 to 321.754 if the land meets the qualifications for small
tract forestland under ORS 321.709.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-706__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Land that qualifies as small tract forestland is also disqualified from any
other special assessment program as of the tax year for which the land first
qualifies as small tract forestland.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-706__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An application shall be deemed approved unless, within three months of the date
the application was made or before August 15 of the year in which the
application was filed, whichever is later, the county assessor notifies the
applicant in writing that the application has been wholly or partially denied.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-706__subsec_7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A taxpayer may appeal the decision of the county assessor to wholly or
partially deny an application for small tract forestland qualification to the
tax court in the time and manner prescribed under ORS 305.404 to 305.560.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-706__subsec_8">
            <num>(8)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the case of property that qualifies as small tract forestland, the county
assessor shall send to the department a written notification of the
qualification and a copy of the application.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-709">
          <num>321.709</num>
          <heading>Small tract forestland qualification requirements</heading>
          <subsection eId="321-709__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>To qualify
for small tract forestland assessment under ORS 321.700 to 321.754 for each tax
year:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="321-709__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The owner of the land that is the subject of an application filed under ORS
321.706 must own or hold common ownership interest in at least 10 acres of
Oregon forestland but less than 5,000 acres of Oregon forestland;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-709__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The land that is the subject of the application must constitute all forestland
within a single tax lot and all forestland within contiguous parcels owned or
held in common ownership by the owner; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-709__subsec_1__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The forestland that is the subject of the application must meet minimal
stocking and species requirements applicable to forestland under rules adopted
by the Department of Revenue.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-709__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <paragraph eId="321-709__subsec_2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Whether land qualifies for small tract forestland assessment shall be
determined as of January 1 of each assessment year.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-709__subsec_2__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If land qualified for small tract forestland assessment under this section as
of January 1 of an assessment year but is disqualified from small tract
forestland assessment prior to July 1 of the same assessment year, the land
shall be assessed as provided under ORS 308.146 or as otherwise provided by
law.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-709__subsec_2__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If land qualified for small tract forestland assessment under this section as
of January 1 of an assessment year but ceases to meet the qualifications for
small tract forestland assessment on or after July 1, the land shall continue
to be assessed as small tract forestland for the current tax year.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-709__subsec_2__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The land that is the subject of the application must not have been disqualified
from small tract forestland assessment under ORS 321.700 to 321.754 for any of the
five tax years preceding the year for which small tract forestland assessment
is sought under this section.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-709__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For each year that land qualifies for small tract forestland assessment, the
county assessor shall enter the notation “potential additional tax liability”
on the assessment and tax roll.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-712">
          <num>321.712</num>
          <heading>Circumstances under which notification is required; disqualification for failure to notify</heading>
          <subsection eId="321-712__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An owner of small tract forestland shall notify the county assessor:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="321-712__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When the owner acquires, either directly or through common ownership, one or
more tax lots that are contiguous to small tract forestland owned or held in
common ownership by the owner;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-712__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When the owner acquires, either directly or through common ownership,
additional forestland that results in the owner’s owning or holding in common
ownership more than 5,000 acres of Oregon forestland;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-712__subsec_1__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When the owner sells, either directly or through common ownership, small tract
forestland that results in the owner’s owning or holding in common ownership
less than 10 acres of Oregon forestland; or</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-712__subsec_1__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When there is a change in use of any portion of small tract forestland to a use
that is not a forestland use.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-712__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The notification under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-712__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section must be made in writing.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-712__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The county assessor may disqualify small tract forestland if the assessor
discovers an acquisition, sale or change in use described in subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-712__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of
this section for which the owner did not give written notification as required
under this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-712__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The county assessor shall send a copy of any notification made under this
section and received by the assessor to the Department of Revenue.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-716">
          <num>321.716</num>
          <heading>Disqualification; requalification under certain circumstances; notice; automatic qualification as forestland</heading>
          <subsection eId="321-716__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The county assessor shall disqualify
land as small tract forestland upon:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="321-716__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Sale or transfer of the small tract forestland;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-716__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Discovery by the assessor that the land is no longer forestland;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-716__subsec_1__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The owner’s owning or holding in common ownership more than 5,000 acres of
Oregon forestland;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-716__subsec_1__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The owner’s owning or holding in common ownership less than 10 acres of Oregon
forestland;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-716__subsec_1__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Written notice from the State Forestry Department that the land no longer meets
the stocking and species requirements applicable to small tract forestland
under rules adopted by the Department of Revenue;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-716__subsec_1__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The land’s qualifying for another special assessment listed in ORS 308A.706</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-716__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <paragraph eId="321-716__subsec_1__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <subparagraph eId="321-716__subsec_1__subsec_d__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>,</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="321-716__subsec_1__subsec_d__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>,</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="321-716__subsec_1__subsec_d__subsec_F">
                <num>(F)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>or</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="321-716__subsec_1__subsec_d__subsec_G">
                <num>(G)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>; or</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-716__subsec_1__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The recording of a subdivision plat under ORS chapter 92 that subdivides the
land.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-716__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If, pursuant to subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-716__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <paragraph eId="321-716__subsec_1__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this section, the county assessor
disqualifies small tract forestland upon the recording of a subdivision plat,
the land may requalify for small tract forestland assessment upon:</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-716__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Payment of all additional tax and interest that remains due and owing as a
result of the disqualification;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-716__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Submission of an application for small tract forestland assessment under ORS
321.706 and approval of the application by the county assessor; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-716__subsec_1__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Compliance with any applicable local government zoning ordinances governing
minimum lot or parcel acreage for forest use.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-716__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <paragraph eId="321-716__subsec_3__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a sale or transfer of small tract forestland is the basis for
disqualification under subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-716__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <paragraph eId="321-716__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this section, the land may not be
disqualified until 30 days after the county assessor issues a notice of intent
to disqualify to the purchaser or transferee of the small tract forestland. The
assessor shall issue a notice of intent to disqualify within 15 months after the
date of the sale or transfer.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-716__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The land shall automatically qualify for special assessment under ORS 321.257
to 321.390 or 321.805 to 321.855, whichever is applicable, unless the assessor
determines that the land does not constitute forestland.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-716__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Upon disqualification of land under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-716__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section, additional
taxes shall be determined as provided in ORS 308A.700 to 308A.733.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-719">
          <num>321.719</num>
          <heading>Continued qualification as small tract forestland following sale or transfer; requirements; late filing procedure and fee</heading>
          <subsection eId="321-719__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding ORS 321.716</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-719__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <paragraph eId="321-719__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>, if the sale or transfer of small tract forestland is to a person who,
following the date of the sale or transfer, does not own or hold in common ownership
less than 10 acres or 5,000 acres or more of forestland in Oregon, the sold or
transferred forestland may remain small tract forestland, if:</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-719__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Within 30 days after the date the county assessor issues the notice of intent
to disqualify under ORS 321.716, the purchaser or transferee has applied for
continued qualification of the small tract forestland;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-719__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The purchaser or transferee is otherwise eligible to be an owner of small tract
forestland under ORS 321.700 to 321.754; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-719__subsec_1__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Any forestland owned or held in common ownership by the purchaser or transferee
that is a contiguous parcel to the purchased or transferred forestland is:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="321-719__subsec_1__subsec_c__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Qualified as small tract forestland or is the subject of an application for
qualification under ORS 321.706; or</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="321-719__subsec_1__subsec_c__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Included as part of the application for continued qualification filed under
this section, and the additional information required in an application for
qualification of small tract forestland under ORS 321.706 is included in the
application for continued qualification filed under this section.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-719__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <paragraph eId="321-719__subsec_2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A purchaser or transferee described in subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-719__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section shall
apply for continued qualification to the county assessor of the county in which
the forestland that is the subject of the sale or transfer is located. If the
forestland is located in more than one county, the purchaser or transferee
shall apply for continued qualification to the county assessor of each county
in which the forestland is located.</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="321-719__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The application shall be on a form prescribed by the Department of Revenue and
supplied by the county assessor that contains:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="321-719__subsec_1__subsec_b__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The name and address of the seller or transferor of the small tract forestland;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="321-719__subsec_1__subsec_b__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The name, address and taxpayer identification number of the purchaser or
transferee of the small tract forestland;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="321-719__subsec_1__subsec_b__subsec_C">
                <num>(C)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>A statement listing the county and containing a description sufficient to
identify the location of the small tract forestland being purchased or
transferred;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="321-719__subsec_1__subsec_b__subsec_D">
                <num>(D)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>A statement listing the county and containing a description sufficient to
identify the location of all parcels of land owned or held in common ownership
by the purchaser or transferee that are contiguous to the small tract
forestland that is being purchased or transferred;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="321-719__subsec_1__subsec_b__subsec_E">
                <num>(E)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The total acreage of Oregon forestland owned or held in common ownership by the
purchaser or transferee;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="321-719__subsec_1__subsec_b__subsec_F">
                <num>(F)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>A statement that the applicant is aware of the potential tax liability that
arises under ORS 308A.707;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="321-719__subsec_1__subsec_b__subsec_G">
                <num>(G)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>An affirmation that the statements contained in the application are true; and</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="321-719__subsec_1__subsec_b__subsec_H">
                <num>(H)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Any other relevant information the department may prescribe.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-719__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The assessor shall review the application and grant the continued qualification
of the land as small tract forestland following the sale or transfer if the
purchaser or transferee satisfies the requirements of subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-719__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this
section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-719__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <paragraph eId="321-719__subsec_4__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the application for continued qualification is filed prior to July 1 of the
assessment year, the assessor shall process the application for continued qualification
for the tax year beginning that July 1.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-719__subsec_4__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the notice of intent to disqualify is issued on or after June 1 of the
assessment year, the assessor may not disqualify the land as small tract
forestland for the tax year beginning July 1, and shall process the application
for continued qualification for the tax year beginning the next succeeding July
1.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-719__subsec_4__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An application for continued qualification shall be deemed approved unless,
within three months of the date the application was made or before August 15 of
the year in which the application was filed, whichever is later, the county
assessor notifies the purchaser or transferee in writing that the application
has been wholly or partially denied.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-719__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A purchaser or transferee may appeal the decision of the county assessor to
wholly or partially deny an application for continued qualification to the tax
court in the time and manner prescribed under ORS 305.404 to 305.560.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-719__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the case of an application for continued qualification that is approved by
the county assessor, the assessor shall send a written notification of the
approval and a copy of the application to the department.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-719__subsec_7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For purposes of computing additional taxes under ORS 308A.707, upon a
subsequent disqualification of small tract forestland that is granted continued
qualification under this section, the small tract forestland is considered to
have been subject to small tract forestland assessment without interruption
from the period before the sale or transfer to the date of subsequent
disqualification from small tract forestland assessment.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-719__subsec_8">
            <num>(8)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-719__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section, a purchaser or transferee of
small tract forestland may file an application for continued qualification of
the small tract forestland after the date prescribed in subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-719__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this
section if:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="321-719__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The application is filed on or before December 15 of the first tax year for
which the forestland would otherwise be disqualified from small tract
forestland assessment; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-719__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The applicant pays a $200 late filing fee at the time the application is filed.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-722">
          <num>321.722</num>
          <heading>Valuation</heading>
          <subsection eId="321-722__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Small tract forestland shall have a specially assessed value per acre:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="321-722__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Equal to 20 percent of the specially assessed value per acre determined under
ORS 321.354, if located in western Oregon; or</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-722__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Equal to 20 percent of the specially assessed value per acre determined under
ORS 321.833, if located in eastern Oregon.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-722__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For each land class, the maximum assessed value per acre of small tract
forestland shall equal 103 percent of the small tract forestland assessed value
per acre for the preceding tax year or 100 percent of the small tract
forestland maximum assessed value per acre for the preceding tax year,
whichever is greater.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-722__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The county assessor shall compute the assessed value of small tract forestland
by multiplying the acreage of the small tract forestland in each land class by
the lesser of:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="321-722__subsec_3__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The specially assessed value per acre; or</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-722__subsec_3__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The maximum assessed value per acre.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-722__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the small tract forestland being assessed consists of different land
classes, the assessed value of the small tract forestland shall be the sum of
the assessed values computed for each land class under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-722__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this
section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-726">
          <num>321.726</num>
          <heading>Severance tax upon harvest from small tract forestland</heading>
          <subsection eId="321-726__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A severance
tax is imposed at the time of the harvest of timber from small tract
forestland.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-726__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The tax is imposed on the owner of timber at the time of harvest, and remains a
liability of the owner of timber until paid.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-726__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The tax is imposed at the rate of:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="321-726__subsec_3__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>$3.89 per thousand feet, board measure, of timber harvested in western Oregon;
or</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-726__subsec_3__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>$3.03 per thousand feet, board measure, of timber harvested in eastern Oregon.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-726__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The tax shall be imposed on the net volume of timber harvested, determined by
unit of proper measurement for the kind of timber, species, quality class,
grade or product harvested.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-726__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For calendar years beginning on or after January 1, 2005, the tax rates imposed
under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-726__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section shall be indexed as follows:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="321-726__subsec_3__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For the rate that applies to the harvest of timber from small tract forestland
in western Oregon, the tax rate applicable to the harvest of timber from small
tract forestland in western Oregon for the previous calendar year shall be
multiplied by the ratio of the average assessed value per acre of small tract
forestland in western Oregon for the property tax year in which the current
calendar year begins over the average assessed value per acre of small tract
forestland in western Oregon for the previous property tax year. For purposes
of this paragraph, the average assessed value per acre of small tract
forestland in western Oregon is determined by adding the assessed values per
acre of small tract forestland for each land class in western Oregon and
dividing that number by the number of land classes in western Oregon.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-726__subsec_3__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For the rate that applies to the harvest of timber from small tract forestland
in eastern Oregon, the tax rate applicable to the harvest of timber from small
tract forestland in eastern Oregon for the previous calendar year shall be
multiplied by the ratio of the assessed value per acre of small tract
forestland in eastern Oregon for the property tax year in which the current
calendar year begins over the assessed value per acre of small tract forestland
in eastern Oregon for the previous property tax year.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-726__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The tax imposed under this section does not apply to an owner of forestland
totaling 5,000 acres or more that, on or after July 1 of an assessment year,
acquires ownership of small tract forestland and harvests timber from the
acquired small tract forestland.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-733">
          <num>321.733</num>
          <heading>Severance tax returns</heading>
          <subsection eId="321-733__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Department of Revenue shall:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="321-733__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Provide notice to an owner of timber harvested from lands assessed as small
tract forestland, as shown on a State Forestry Department Notification of
Operations permit issued during a calendar year, that a severance tax return is
required from the owner; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-733__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Make a severance tax return form available to the owner.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-733__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department shall provide the notice required under this section by mail
unless the owner of timber elects to be notified by an alternative method
allowed by the department.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-733__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any owner of timber receiving notice under this section that a severance tax
return is required shall complete the return and submit the return to the
department within the time prescribed in ORS 321.741, even if the owner has not
incurred severance tax liability during the calendar year.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-741">
          <num>321.741</num>
          <heading>Due dates for severance tax return and payment</heading>
          <subsection eId="321-741__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The severance
tax imposed under ORS 321.726 is due and payable annually, on or before April
15 of each year, with respect to all timber harvested during the previous
calendar year.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-741__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>At the time at which the severance tax is paid and on or before April 15 of
each year, each taxpayer who has harvested any timber during the previous
calendar year shall prepare a return on a form prescribed by the Department of
Revenue showing the amounts and kinds of timber harvested for the previous
calendar year, the amount of tax for which the taxpayer is liable for
harvesting during the previous calendar year and any other information that the
department considers necessary to correctly determine the tax due and shall
mail or deliver the return, together with a remittance for the unpaid balance
of the tax, to the department. The return shall be signed and certified by the
taxpayer or a duly authorized agent of the taxpayer, as provided in ORS
305.810. The department may allow, upon written application made on or before
April 15, further time not exceeding 30 days for filing a return. The tax shall
be delinquent if not paid by April 15, without regard to any extension of time
for filing the return.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-741__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All severance tax payments received under ORS 321.700 to 321.754 shall be
credited first to penalty and then to interest accrued on the tax being paid
and then to the tax.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-741__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A taxpayer incurring less than $10 total severance tax liability under ORS
321.700 to 321.754 in any calendar year is excused from the payment of the tax
but is required to file a return.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-746">
          <num>321.746</num>
          <heading>Severance tax revenues</heading>
          <subsection eId="321-746__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Revenue from the severance tax imposed in western
Oregon under ORS 321.726 shall be paid over by the Department of Revenue to the
State Treasurer and deposited in a suspense account established under ORS
293.445. After the payment of refunds, the balance of the suspense account
shall be transferred to the Western Oregon Timber Severance Tax Fund
established under ORS 321.751.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-746__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Revenue from the severance tax imposed in eastern Oregon under ORS 321.726
shall be paid over by the Department of Revenue to the State Treasurer and
deposited in a suspense account established under ORS 293.445. After the
payment of refunds, the balance of the suspense account shall be transferred to
the Eastern Oregon Timber Severance Tax Fund established under ORS 321.754.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-751">
          <num>321.751</num>
          <heading>Western Oregon Timber Severance Tax Fund; revenue distribution</heading>
          <subsection eId="321-751__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Western
Oregon Timber Severance Tax Fund is established in the State Treasury, separate
and distinct from the General Fund. Interest earned by the Western Oregon
Timber Severance Tax Fund shall be retained by the Western Oregon Timber
Severance Tax Fund.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-751__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Moneys are continuously appropriated from the Western Oregon Timber Severance
Tax Fund for use in reimbursing the General Fund for expenses incurred in the
collection of taxes imposed under ORS 321.700 to 321.754.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-751__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A working balance may be retained in the Western Oregon Timber Severance Tax
Fund for the payment of expenses described in subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-751__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section.
The balance of the Western Oregon Timber Severance Tax Fund, as of May 1 of
each calendar year, shall be distributed as follows:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="321-751__subsec_2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>60.5 percent to the State School Fund established under ORS 327.008. A
distribution made under this paragraph shall be made on or before May 15 of the
year.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-751__subsec_2__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>4.5 percent to the Community College Support Fund established under ORS
341.620. A distribution made under this paragraph shall be made on or before
May 15 of the year.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-751__subsec_2__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>35 percent to the Department of Revenue for further distribution to the
counties of this state that are located in western Oregon. Moneys distributed
to the department under this paragraph are continuously appropriated to the
department for the purpose of making the payments to counties described in this
paragraph. A distribution to the department made under this paragraph shall be
made on or before August 15 of the year. Each county’s share of the
distribution made under this paragraph shall equal the proportion of the
assessed value of all small tract forestland in western Oregon that is located
in that county. A distribution made by the department to a county under this
paragraph shall be deposited in the county general fund.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-754">
          <num>321.754</num>
          <heading>Eastern Oregon Timber Severance Tax Fund; revenue distribution</heading>
          <subsection eId="321-754__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Eastern
Oregon Timber Severance Tax Fund is established in the State Treasury, separate
and distinct from the General Fund. Interest earned by the Eastern Oregon
Timber Severance Tax Fund shall be retained by the Eastern Oregon Timber
Severance Tax Fund.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-754__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Moneys are continuously appropriated from the Eastern Oregon Timber Severance
Tax Fund for use in reimbursing the General Fund for expenses incurred in the
collection of taxes imposed under ORS 321.700 to 321.754.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-754__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A working balance may be retained in the Eastern Oregon Timber Severance Tax
Fund for the payment of expenses described in subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-754__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section.
The balance of the Eastern Oregon Timber Severance Tax Fund, as of May 1 of
each calendar year, shall be distributed as follows:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="321-754__subsec_2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>60.5 percent to the State School Fund established under ORS 327.008. A
distribution made under this paragraph shall be made on or before May 15 of the
year.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-754__subsec_2__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>4.5 percent to the Community College Support Fund established under ORS
341.620. A distribution made under this paragraph shall be made on or before
May 15 of the year.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-754__subsec_2__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>35 percent to the Department of Revenue for further distribution to the
counties of this state that are located in eastern Oregon. Moneys distributed
to the department under this paragraph are continuously appropriated to the
department for the purpose of making the payments to counties described in this
paragraph. A distribution to the department made under this paragraph shall be
made on or before August 15 of the year. Each county’s share of the
distribution made under this paragraph shall equal the proportion of the
assessed value of all small tract forestland in eastern Oregon that is located
in that county. A distribution made by the department to a county under this
paragraph shall be deposited in the county general fund.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-805">
          <num>321.805</num>
          <heading>Definitions for ORS 321.805 to 321.855</heading>
          <subsection eId="321-805__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Cultured Christmas trees” means trees:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="321-805__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Grown on lands used exclusively for that purpose, capable of preparation by
intensive cultivation methods such as plowing or turning over the soil;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-805__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Of a marketable species;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-805__subsec_1__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Managed to produce trees meeting U.S. No. 2 or better standards for Christmas
trees as specified by the Agriculture Marketing Services of the United States
Department of Agriculture; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-805__subsec_1__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Evidencing periodic maintenance practices of shearing for Douglas fir and pine
species, weed and brush control, and basal pruning, fertilizing, insect and
disease control, stump culture, soil cultivation or irrigation.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-805__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Department” means the Department of Revenue.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-805__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Eastern Oregon” means that portion of the state lying east of a line beginning
at the intersection of the northern boundary of the State of Oregon and the
western boundary of Wasco County, thence south along the western boundaries of
the counties of Wasco, Jefferson, Deschutes and Klamath to the southern
boundary of the State of Oregon.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-805__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Forestland” means land in eastern Oregon that is being held or used for the
predominant purpose of growing and harvesting trees of a marketable species and
that has been designated as forestland under ORS 321.805 to 321.855 or land in
eastern Oregon, the highest and best use of which is the growing and harvesting
of such trees. Forestland is the land alone. Forestland often contains isolated
openings that because of rock outcrops, river wash, swamps, chemical conditions
of the soil, brush and other like conditions prevent adequate stocking of such
openings for the production of trees of a marketable species. If such openings
in their natural state are necessary to hold the surrounding forestland in
forest use through sound management practices, the openings are deemed
forestland.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-805__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“State Forester” means the State Forester or the authorized representative of
the State Forester.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-805__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Summit of the Cascade Mountains” means a line beginning at the intersection of
the northern boundary of the State of Oregon and the western boundary of Wasco
County, thence southerly along the western boundaries of the counties of Wasco,
Jefferson, Deschutes and Klamath to the southern boundary of the State of
Oregon.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-805__subsec_7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Timber” means all logs which can be measured in board feet and other forest
products as determined by department rule, but does not include western juniper
or products from harvested western juniper.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-808">
          <num>321.808</num>
          <heading>Purposes</heading>
          <subsection eId="321-808__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>To impose with respect to forestland in eastern Oregon a special assessment
program whereby the assessed value of forestland is determined as prescribed in
ORS 321.201 to 321.222.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-808__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>To establish a special assessment program as a means of:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="321-808__subsec_2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Recognizing the findings in ORS 321.817 without discriminating in favor of
either eastern or western Oregon.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-808__subsec_2__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Recognizing the long-term nature of the forest crop and fostering the public
policy of Oregon to encourage the growing and harvesting of timber.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-808__subsec_2__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Protecting the public welfare by assuring that the people of this state and
future generations shall have the benefits to be derived from the continuous
production of forest products from private forestland.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-808__subsec_2__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Promoting this state’s policy of encouraging forestry and the restocking of
forestland to provide present and future benefits by enhancing the water
supply, preventing erosion, providing habitat for wildlife, providing scenic
and recreational opportunities and providing for needed products. [Formerly
321.408; 2017 c.315 s29]</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-817">
          <num>321.817</num>
          <heading>Legislative findings</heading>
          <subsection eId="321-817__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Multiple taxation through a yearly ad valorem levy on both trees and forestland
managed in sustained yield timber operations discourages conservation, private
ownership and investment of capital.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-817__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The interests of this state, its residents and its future residents are best
served by sustained yield practices and tax policies that encourage production
of forest resources for commerce, recreation and watersheds, stabilize
employment levels, prevent large population shifts and encourage millage of
timber products within Oregon.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-817__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Timber on private lands managed on a sustained yield basis should be treated as
a crop and not taxed as real property.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-817__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The portion of this state lying east of the summit of the Cascade Mountains
differs greatly in forest tree types, soils, climate, growing conditions and
topography from western Oregon.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-817__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Eastern Oregon forests predominate in Ponderosa pine and associated species,
while western Oregon forests predominate in Douglas fir and associated species.
[Formerly 321.410; 2017 c.315 s30]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-824">
          <num>321.824</num>
          <heading>Lands not eligible for special assessment</heading>
          <subsection eId="321-824__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Lands assessed by the
Department of Revenue pursuant to ORS 308.505 to 308.674 or 308.805 to 308.820
may not be assessed under ORS 321.805 to 321.855.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-824__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Land used exclusively for growing cultured Christmas trees may not be assessed
under ORS 321.805 to 321.855.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-824__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Land that is used to grow hardwood timber, including but not limited to hybrid
cottonwood, may not be assessed under ORS 321.805 to 321.855 if:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="321-824__subsec_3__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The land is prepared using intensive cultivation methods and is cleared of
competing vegetation for at least three years after tree planting;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-824__subsec_3__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The timber is of a species marketable as fiber for inclusion in the furnish for
manufacturing paper products;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-824__subsec_3__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The timber is harvested on a rotation cycle within 12 years after planting; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-824__subsec_3__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The land and timber are subject to intensive agricultural practices such as
fertilization, insect and disease control, cultivation and irrigation.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-824__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Nothing contained in ORS 321.805 to 321.855 shall prevent:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="321-824__subsec_4__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The collection of ad valorem property taxes that became a lien against timber
prior to July 1, 1962.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-824__subsec_4__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The collection of taxes, charges or assessments made pursuant to law for
protection.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-824__subsec_4__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The collection of taxes levied under the provisions of ORS 321.005 to 321.185
and 321.560 to 321.600. [Formerly 321.415; 2005 c.94 s107]</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-829">
          <num>321.829</num>
          <heading>Exemption of timber from property taxation</heading>
          <content>
            <p>All timber in eastern Oregon shall
be exempt from ad valorem property taxation. [Formerly 321.420]</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-833">
          <num>321.833</num>
          <heading>Common ownership minimum acreage requirements; specially assessed value and maximum assessed value of forestland of large landowners</heading>
          <subsection eId="321-833__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <paragraph eId="321-833__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The
Department of Revenue shall identify the forestland that is held in common
ownership of 5,000 acres or more as of the assessment date for each tax year.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-833__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Forestland that the department has identified under paragraph</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-833__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this
subsection that, for the previous tax year, was subject to small tract
forestland assessment shall be disqualified from any small tract forestland
assessment and shall be subject to special assessment as provided in this
section as of the first tax year the forestland is held in common ownership of
5,000 acres or more.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-833__subsec_1__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For purposes of this subsection, “forestland” includes land that meets the
definition of forestland under ORS 321.257.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-833__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Forestland assessed under this section shall have a specially assessed value
per acre equal to the value certified to the county assessor for the tax year
under ORS 321.216.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-833__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Forestland assessed under this section shall have a maximum assessed value per
acre equal to 103 percent of the forestland assessed value per acre for the
preceding tax year or 100 percent of the forestland maximum assessed value per
acre for the preceding tax year, whichever is greater.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-833__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <paragraph eId="321-833__subsec_4__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The assessor shall compute the assessed value of forestland by multiplying the
acreage of the forestland by the lesser of:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="321-833__subsec_4__subsec_a__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The specially assessed value per acre; or</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="321-833__subsec_4__subsec_a__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The maximum assessed value per acre.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-833__subsec_4__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding paragraph</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-833__subsec_4__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this subsection, the forestland shall be
assessed as provided in ORS 308.232 if the real market value of the forestland
is less than the value established under paragraph</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-833__subsec_4__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this subsection.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-833__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For purposes of this section:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="321-833__subsec_5__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall certify to the county assessor of a county in which
forestland identified in subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-833__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section is located a list of
the property tax accounts containing forestland so identified.</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="321-833__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Forestland shall be considered to be in common ownership if the forestland is
owned by the person directly or is owned by a corporation, partnership,
association or other entity in which the person owns a majority interest.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-833__subsec_1__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Additional taxes may not be imposed as a result of a disqualification under
subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-833__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section.</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="321-833__subsec_1__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The notification requirements and other procedures that the county assessor
must follow in disqualifying forestland do not apply to a disqualification
occurring under subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-833__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section.</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="321-833__subsec_1__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall notify the county assessor of forestland identified under
subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-833__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <paragraph eId="321-833__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this section that is located in that county. [Formerly
321.812]</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-839">
          <num>321.839</num>
          <heading>Application for forestland designation; special filing date for change in highest and best use; contents; approval</heading>
          <subsection eId="321-839__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An owner of land desiring that
it be designated as forestland for purposes of ORS 321.805 to 321.855 shall
make application to the county assessor on or before April 1 of the assessment
year for which special assessment as forestland is first desired, and the owner
may also do so within 30 days of receipt of notice of its assessment as omitted
property.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-839__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-839__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section, an owner of land may apply to
the county assessor by December 15 to have the land designated as forestland
for the assessment year if:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="321-839__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For the prior assessment year the land had been forestland by reason of the
land being highest and best use forestland; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-839__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For the current assessment year the land is being assessed at a value
reflecting a use other than highest and best use forestland.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-839__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The application shall be made upon forms prepared by the Department of Revenue
and supplied by the county assessor, and shall include the following:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="321-839__subsec_3__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A description of all land the applicant desires to be designated as forestland.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-839__subsec_3__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Date of acquisition.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-839__subsec_3__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Whether the land is being held or used for the predominant purpose of growing
and harvesting trees of marketable species.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-839__subsec_3__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Whether there is a forest management plan for it.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-839__subsec_3__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If so, whether the plan is being implemented, and the nature and extent of
implementation.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-839__subsec_3__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Whether the land is being held or used for the predominant purpose of grazing
or raising of livestock.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-839__subsec_3__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Whether the land has been platted under ORS chapter 92.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-839__subsec_3__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Whether a permit has been granted for harvesting for excepted purposes under
the Oregon Forest Practices Act.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-839__subsec_3__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Whether the land is timberland subject to ORS chapter 477, and if it is not,
the reasons therefor.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-839__subsec_3__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Whether the land, or any of it, is subject to a lease or option which permits
it to be used for any purpose other than the growing and harvesting of trees.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-839__subsec_3__subsec_k">
              <num>(k)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A summary of past experience and activity of the applicant in growing and
harvesting trees.</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="321-839__subsec_3__subsec_k__subsec_L">
                <num>(L)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>A summary of current and continuing activity of the applicant in growing and
harvesting trees.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-839__subsec_3__subsec_m">
              <num>(m)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A statement that the applicant is aware of the potential tax liability involved
when the land ceases to be designated as forestland.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-839__subsec_3__subsec_n">
              <num>(n)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An affirmation that the statements contained in the application are true.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-839__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The county assessor shall approve an application for forestland designation if
the assessor finds that the land is properly classifiable as forestland. The
county assessor shall not find land properly classifiable as forestland if the
application states the land is not being held or used for the predominant
purpose of growing and harvesting trees of marketable species. Otherwise, the
determination whether the land is properly classifiable as forestland shall be
made with due regard to all relevant evidence and without any one or more items
of evidence necessarily being determinative.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-839__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The application shall be considered to have been approved unless, within three
months of the date such application was delivered to the assessor or prior to
August 15, whichever is later, the assessor shall notify the applicant in
writing of the extent to which the application is denied. [Formerly 321.815]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-842">
          <num>321.842</num>
          <heading>Removal of forestland designation; appeal; requalification</heading>
          <subsection eId="321-842__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <paragraph eId="321-842__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When land
has once been designated as forestland as a result of an application being
filed therefor it shall be valued as such until the county assessor removes the
forestland designation under paragraph</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-842__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this subsection.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-842__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The county assessor shall remove the forestland designation upon:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="321-842__subsec_1__subsec_b__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Notification by the taxpayer to the assessor to remove the designation;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="321-842__subsec_1__subsec_b__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Sale or transfer to an ownership making it exempt from ad valorem property
taxation;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="321-842__subsec_1__subsec_b__subsec_C">
                <num>(C)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Discovery by the assessor that the land is no longer forestland; or</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="321-842__subsec_1__subsec_b__subsec_D">
                <num>(D)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The act of recording a subdivision plat under ORS chapter 92.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-842__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A taxpayer whose application filed under ORS 321.839 has been denied in whole
or in part, or a taxpayer whose forestland has had the designation thereof
removed in whole or in part, may appeal to the Oregon Tax Court within the time
and in the manner provided in ORS 305.404 to 305.560.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-842__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If, under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-842__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <paragraph eId="321-842__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <subparagraph eId="321-842__subsec_1__subsec_b__subsec_D">
                <num>(D)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>of this section, the county assessor removes the
forestland designation upon the act of recording a subdivision plat, the land,
or a part of the land, may be requalified for forestland designation upon:</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-842__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Payment of all additional tax and interest that remains due and owing with
respect to the land;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-842__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Submission by the owner of an application for designation as forestland as
provided in this section;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-842__subsec_1__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Meeting all of the qualifications for designation as forestland as provided in
ORS 321.805 to 321.855; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="321-842__subsec_1__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Meeting the requirements, if any, of applicable local government zoning
ordinances with regard to minimum lot or parcel acreage for forest use. [Formerly
321.820]</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-845">
          <num>321.845</num>
          <heading>Date on which disqualification of forestland is effective; timely notice of disqualification required</heading>
          <subsection eId="321-845__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding ORS 308.210, 311.405 or 311.410,
if land designated as forestland is subject to disqualification by the county
assessor as a result of the discovery that the land is no longer forestland,
the disqualification shall be deemed to occur as of the January 1 assessment
date of the assessment year in which the discovery occurs.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-845__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This section applies only if notice of the disqualification is mailed by the
county assessor prior to August 15 of the tax year for which the
disqualification of the land is asserted. [Formerly 321.822; 2017 c.25 s2]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-848">
          <num>321.848</num>
          <heading>Disqualification</heading>
          <content>
            <p>ORS 308A.700 to 308A.733 apply whenever land designated as forestland as a
result of an application being filed therefor under ORS 321.805 to 321.855
thereafter becomes disqualified. [Formerly 321.825]</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-855">
          <num>321.855</num>
          <heading>Land used to grow certain hardwood to be assessed as farm use land; application required for unzoned land</heading>
          <subsection eId="321-855__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Land described in ORS 321.824</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-855__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>(relating to
hardwood timberland, including hybrid cottonwood timberland) shall be assessed
as farm use land under ORS 308A.050 to 308A.128.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-855__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <paragraph eId="321-855__subsec_2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If land is or becomes land described under ORS 321.824</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-855__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>and the land is not
located within an exclusive farm use zone, the owner shall make application for
special valuation in the manner provided under ORS 308A.077, as follows:
(A)
If the change in use takes place on or after July 1, the owner shall file the
application on or before April 1 of the following tax year.
(B)
If the change in use takes place prior to July 1, the owner shall file the
application on or before August 1 of the tax year.</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="321-855__subsec_3__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If an application is filed as provided under this subsection, the owner shall
have seven years beginning with the first year of classification to meet the
income requirements of ORS 308A.071 and need not meet the two-year farm use
requirements of ORS 308A.068. [Formerly 321.830]</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_321-991">
          <num>321.991</num>
          <heading>Penalty</heading>
          <subsection eId="321-991__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-991__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>formerly
528.990; subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-991__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>enacted as 1961 c.659 s9; subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-991__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>enacted as
1961 c.714 s15; subsections</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-991__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="321-991__subsec_7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>formerly part of 308.990; 1977 c.892 s50;
2003 c.454 s116; 2003 c.621 s101; 2011 c.597 s183]
CHAPTER 322 [Reserved for expansion]
_______________</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>