<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="ORS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-or/act/ors/chapter-319"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-or/act/ors/chapter-319"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#oregon-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-or"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="319"/>
          <FRBRname value="ORS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-or/act/ors/chapter-319/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-or/act/ors/chapter-319/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-or/act/ors/chapter-319/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-or/act/ors/chapter-319/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="oregon-legislature" href="https://www.oregonlegislature.gov" showAs="Oregon State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <chapter eId="chp_319">
        <num>319</num>
        <heading>Motor Vehicle and Aircraft Fuel Taxes</heading>
        <section eId="sec_319-010">
          <num>319.010</num>
          <heading>Definitions for ORS 319.010 to 319.430</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-010__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Aircraft” means every contrivance now known, or hereafter invented, used or
designed for navigation of or flight in the air, operated or propelled by the
use of aircraft fuel.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-010__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Aircraft fuel” means any gasoline and any other inflammable or combustible gas
or liquid by whatever name such gasoline, gas or liquid is known or sold,
usable as fuel for the operation of aircraft, except gas or liquid, the chief
use of which, as determined by the Department of Transportation is for purposes
other than the propulsion of aircraft.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-010__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Airport” means any area of land or water, except a restricted landing area,
which is designed for the landing and takeoff of aircraft.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-010__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Broker” means and includes every person other than a dealer engaged in
business as a broker, jobber or wholesale merchant dealing in motor vehicle
fuel or aircraft fuel.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-010__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Bulk transfer” means any change in ownership of motor vehicle fuel or aircraft
fuel contained in a terminal storage facility or any physical movement of motor
vehicle fuel or aircraft fuel between terminal storage facilities by pipeline
or marine transport.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-010__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Dealer” means any person who:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="319-010__subsec_6__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Imports or causes to be imported motor vehicle fuels or aircraft fuels for
sale, use or distribution in, and after the same reaches the State of Oregon,
but “dealer” does not include any person who imports into this state motor
vehicle fuel in quantities of 500 gallons or less purchased from a supplier who
is licensed as a dealer under ORS 319.010 to 319.430 and who assumes liability
for the payment of the applicable license tax to this state;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-010__subsec_6__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Produces, refines, manufactures or compounds motor vehicle fuels or aircraft
fuels in the State of Oregon for use, distribution or sale in this state;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-010__subsec_6__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Acquires in this state for sale, use or distribution in this state motor
vehicle fuels or aircraft fuels with respect to which there has been no license
tax previously incurred; or</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-010__subsec_6__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Acquires title to or possession of motor vehicle fuels or aircraft fuels in
this state and exports the product out of this state.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-010__subsec_7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Department” means the Department of Transportation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-010__subsec_8">
            <num>(8)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Distribution” means, in addition to its ordinary meaning, the delivery of
motor vehicle fuel or aircraft fuel by a dealer to any service station or into
any tank, storage facility or series of tanks or storage facilities connected
by pipelines, from which motor vehicle fuel or aircraft fuel is withdrawn
directly for sale or for delivery into the fuel tanks of motor vehicles whether
or not the service station, tank or storage facility is owned, operated or
controlled by the dealer.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-010__subsec_9">
            <num>(9)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“First sale, use or distribution of motor vehicle fuel or aircraft fuel” means
the first withdrawal, other than by bulk transfer, of motor vehicle fuel or
aircraft fuel from terminal storage facilities for sale, use or distribution. “First
sale, use or distribution of motor vehicle fuel or aircraft fuel” also means
the first sale, use or distribution of motor vehicle fuel or aircraft fuel
after import into this state if the motor vehicle fuel or aircraft fuel is delivered
other than to the terminal storage facilities of a licensed dealer.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-010__subsec_10">
            <num>(10)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Highway” means every way, thoroughfare and place, of whatever nature, open for
use of the public for the purpose of vehicular travel.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-010__subsec_11">
            <num>(11)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Motor vehicle” means all vehicles, engines or machines, movable or immovable,
operated or propelled by the use of motor vehicle fuel.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-010__subsec_12">
            <num>(12)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Motor vehicle fuel” means and includes gasoline and any other inflammable or
combustible gas or liquid, by whatever name such gasoline, gas or liquid is
known or sold, usable as fuel for the operation of motor vehicles, except gas
or liquid, the chief use of which, as determined by the department, is for
purposes other than the propulsion of motor vehicles upon the highways of this
state.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-010__subsec_13">
            <num>(13)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Person” includes every natural person, association, firm, partnership,
corporation or the United States.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-010__subsec_14">
            <num>(14)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Restricted landing area” means any area of land or water, or both, which is
used or made available for the landing and takeoff of aircraft, the use of
which, except in case of emergency, is provided from time to time by the
department.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-010__subsec_15">
            <num>(15)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Service station” means and includes any place operated for the purpose of
retailing and delivering motor vehicle fuel into the fuel tanks of motor
vehicles or aircraft fuel into the fuel tanks of aircraft.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-010__subsec_16">
            <num>(16)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Terminal storage facility” means any fuel storage facility that has marine or
pipeline access. [Amended by 1955 c.287 s19; 1955 c.730 ss1,15; 1957 c.209 s1;
1959 c.505 s1; 1963 c.226 s1; 1987 c.610 s1; 1989 c.664 s1; 1993 c.741 s28]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-020">
          <num>319.020</num>
          <heading>Monthly statement by dealer; license tax imposed; rules</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-020__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to
subsections</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-020__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>to</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-020__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section, in addition to the taxes otherwise
provided for by law, every dealer engaging in the dealer’s own name, or in the
name of others, in the first sale, use or distribution of motor vehicle fuel or
aircraft fuel or withdrawal of motor vehicle fuel or aircraft fuel for sale,
use or distribution within areas in this state within which the state lacks the
power to tax the sale, use or distribution of motor vehicle fuel or aircraft
fuel, shall:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="319-020__subsec_4__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Not later than the 25th day of each calendar month, render a statement to the
Department of Transportation of all motor vehicle fuel or aircraft fuel sold,
used, distributed or so withdrawn by the dealer in the State of Oregon as well
as all such fuel sold, used or distributed in this state by a purchaser thereof
upon which sale, use or distribution the dealer has assumed liability for the
applicable license tax during the preceding calendar month. The dealer shall
render the statement to the department in the manner provided by the department
by rule.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-020__subsec_4__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in ORS 319.270, pay a license tax computed on the basis of
34 cents per gallon on the first sale, use or distribution of such motor
vehicle fuel or aircraft fuel so sold, used, distributed or withdrawn as shown
by such statement in the manner and within the time provided in ORS 319.010 to
319.430.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-020__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When aircraft fuel is sold, used or distributed by a dealer, the license tax
shall be computed on the basis of 11 cents per gallon of fuel so sold, used or
distributed, except that when aircraft fuel usable in aircraft operated by
turbine engines (turbo-prop or jet) is sold, used or distributed, the tax rate
shall be three cents per gallon.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-020__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In lieu of claiming refund of the tax paid on motor vehicle fuel consumed by
such dealer in nonhighway use as provided in ORS 319.280, 319.290 and 319.320,
or of any prior erroneous payment of license tax made to the state by such
dealer, the dealer may show such motor vehicle fuel as a credit or deduction on
the monthly statement and payment of tax.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-020__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The license tax computed on the basis of the sale, use, distribution or
withdrawal of motor vehicle or aircraft fuel may not be imposed wherever such
tax is prohibited by the Constitution or laws of the United States with respect
to such tax. [Amended by 1955 c.730 s2; 1959 c.505 s2; 1967 c.463 s1; 1973
c.376 s1; 1977 c.293 s1; 1981 c.698 s1; 1983 c.727 ss1,5; 1985 c.209 s12; 1987
c.610 s2; 1987 c.899 ss8,10, 14; 1989 c.664 s2; 1989 c.865 s1; 1991 c.497 ss6,7;
1999 c.1037 ss1,3; 2009 c.865 s48; 2011 c.101 s1; 2015 c.700 ss1,4; 2017 c.750 ss40,41;
2021 c.526 s1]
Note: Section 45,
chapter 750, Oregon Laws 2017, provides:
Sec.
45.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-020__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <paragraph eId="319-020__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For calendar years beginning on or after January 1, 2020, the rates
determined under ORS 319.020</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-020__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <paragraph eId="319-020__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>and 319.530</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-020__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>shall each be increased by
two cents only if the Oregon Transportation Commission submits a report in the
manner provided by ORS 192.245 on or before December 1, 2019, to the Joint
Committee on Transportation established under ORS 171.858 stating that:
(A)
The commission has identified sufficient shovel-ready highway projects and
highway maintenance or operational uses of the increased fuel tax revenue to
justify the increase;
(B)
The set of uniform standards required under ORS 184.657</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-020__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>has been developed
and the standards are being followed;
(C)
The reports received from cities and counties under ORS 184.657</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-020__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>have been
submitted and posted by the commission as required under ORS 184.657</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-020__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>;
(D)
The Department of Transportation is implementing the registration fees and
title fees described in ORS 803.091 and 803.422; and
(E)
The Interstate 205 Active Traffic Management Project and the Interstate 205
Corridor Bottleneck Project have been completed.</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="319-020__subsec_3__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to the facts stated in the report required under paragraph</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-020__subsec_3__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of
this subsection, the Oregon Transportation Commission shall also submit with the
report:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="319-020__subsec_3__subsec_a__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>A list of the shovel-ready highway projects the commission expects to undertake
with the revenue that will become available as a result of the increase;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="319-020__subsec_3__subsec_a__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The amount of bonds the commission considers necessary to be issued to complete
shovel-ready highway projects scheduled to be commenced after January 1, 2020;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="319-020__subsec_3__subsec_a__subsec_C">
                <num>(C)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The construction and financial status of uncompleted in-progress projects
exceeding $20 million identified in chapter 750, Oregon Laws 2017;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="319-020__subsec_3__subsec_a__subsec_D">
                <num>(D)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The status of the Treasure Valley Intermodal Facility Project and the Value
Pricing Set-Up Project;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="319-020__subsec_3__subsec_a__subsec_E">
                <num>(E)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Design, cost analysis and construction option packages for the Interstate 5
Rose Quarter Project for consideration by the Legislative Assembly; and</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="319-020__subsec_3__subsec_a__subsec_F">
                <num>(F)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The design, construction, financial status and progress of projects costing
more than $20 million that are identified in chapter 750, Oregon Laws 2017,
including, but not limited to, the Interstate 205 Abernethy Bridge Project, the
Interstate 205 Freeway Widening Project, the State Highway 217 Northbound
Project and the State Highway 217 Southbound Project, and any other state
transportation projects implemented after October 6, 2017.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-020__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <paragraph eId="319-020__subsec_2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For calendar years beginning on or after January 1, 2022, the rates determined
under ORS 319.020</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-020__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <paragraph eId="319-020__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>and 319.530</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-020__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>and subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-020__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section
shall each be increased by two cents only if the Oregon Transportation
Commission submits a report in the manner provided by ORS 192.245 on or before
December 1, 2021, to the Joint Committee on Transportation established under
ORS 171.858 stating that:
(A)
The Continuous Improvement Advisory Committee appointed under ORS 184.665 has
reviewed and reported to the commission on all transportation projects costing
$50 million or more and completed not less than six months prior to the date of
the report required under this paragraph;
(B)
The recommendations for improvement reported by the Continuous Improvement
Advisory Committee to the commission at least six months prior to the date of
the report required under this paragraph, and approved by the commission, have
been implemented or plans for implementation have been developed;
(C)
The commission has identified sufficient shovel-ready highway projects and
highway maintenance or operational uses of the increased fuel tax revenue to
justify the increase;
(D)
The set of uniform standards required under ORS 184.657</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-020__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>has been developed
and the standards are being followed;
(E)
The reports received from cities and counties under ORS 184.657</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-020__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>have been
posted by the commission as required under ORS 184.657</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-020__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>;
(F)
Under ORS 184.657</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-020__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>, payments from the State Highway Fund have been withheld
from cities and counties that failed to submit reports as required under ORS
184.657</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-020__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>; and
(G)
The Department of Transportation is implementing the registration fees and
title fees described in ORS 803.091 and 803.422.</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="319-020__subsec_2__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to the facts stated in the report required under paragraph</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-020__subsec_2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of
this subsection, the Oregon Transportation Commission shall also identify in
the report:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="319-020__subsec_2__subsec_a__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>A list of the shovel-ready highway projects the commission expects to undertake
with the revenue that will become available as a result of the increase;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="319-020__subsec_2__subsec_a__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The amount of bonds the commission considers necessary to be issued to complete
shovel-ready highway projects scheduled to be commenced after January 1, 2022;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="319-020__subsec_2__subsec_a__subsec_C">
                <num>(C)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The construction and financial status of uncompleted in-progress projects
exceeding $50 million identified in chapter 750, Oregon Laws 2017; and</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="319-020__subsec_2__subsec_a__subsec_D">
                <num>(D)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The design, construction, financial status and progress of projects costing
more than $20 million that are identified in chapter 750, Oregon Laws 2017,
including, but not limited to, the Interstate 5 Rose Quarter Project, the
Interstate 205 Abernethy Bridge Project, the Interstate 205 Freeway Widening
Project, the State Highway 217 Northbound Project, the Newberg-Dundee Bypass
Project and the State Highway 217 Southbound Project, and any other state
transportation projects implemented after October 6, 2017.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-020__subsec_2__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the Commissioner of the Bureau of Labor and Industries has found substantial
evidence, under ORS 279C.306, that a contracting agency that would otherwise
receive increased amounts of fuel tax revenues pursuant to this section on or
after January 1, 2022, has violated ORS 279C.305 within the five years
immediately preceding the date of the commissioner’s finding, or has materially
breached an agreement entered into pursuant to ORS 279C.306, the Department of
Transportation shall withhold the increased amounts until the final resolution
of the violation or breach is determined under ORS 279C.306.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-020__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <paragraph eId="319-020__subsec_3__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For calendar years beginning on or after January 1, 2024, the rates determined
under ORS 319.020</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-020__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <paragraph eId="319-020__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>and 319.530</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-020__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>and subsections</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-020__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-020__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this
section shall each be increased by two cents only if the Oregon Transportation
Commission submits a report in the manner provided by ORS 192.245 on or before
December 1, 2023, to the Joint Committee on Transportation established under ORS
171.858 stating that:
(A)
The Continuous Improvement Advisory Committee appointed under ORS 184.665 has
reviewed and reported to the commission on all transportation projects costing
$50 million or more and completed not less than six months prior to the date of
the report required under this paragraph;
(B)
The recommendations for improvement reported by the Continuous Improvement
Advisory Committee to the commission at least six months prior to the date of
the report required under this paragraph, and approved by the commission, have
been implemented or plans for implementation have been developed;
(C)
The commission has identified sufficient shovel-ready highway projects and
highway maintenance or operational uses of the increased fuel tax revenue to
justify the increase;
(D)
The set of uniform standards required under ORS 184.657</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-020__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>has been developed
and the standards are being followed;
(E)
The reports received from cities and counties under ORS 184.657</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-020__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>have been
posted by the commission as required under ORS 184.657</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-020__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>; and
(F)
Under ORS 184.657</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-020__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>, payments from the State Highway Fund have been withheld
from cities and counties that failed to submit reports as required under ORS
184.657</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-020__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>.</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="319-020__subsec_2__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to the facts stated in the report required under paragraph</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-020__subsec_2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of
this subsection, the Oregon Transportation Commission shall also submit with
the report:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="319-020__subsec_2__subsec_a__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>A list of the shovel-ready highway projects the commission expects to undertake
with the revenue that will become available as a result of the increase;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="319-020__subsec_2__subsec_a__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The amount of bonds the commission considers necessary to be issued to complete
shovel-ready highway projects scheduled to be commenced after January 1, 2024;
and</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="319-020__subsec_2__subsec_a__subsec_C">
                <num>(C)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The design, construction, financial status and progress of projects costing
more than $20 million that are identified in chapter 750, Oregon Laws 2017,
including, but not limited to, the Interstate 5 Rose Quarter Project, the
Interstate 205 Abernethy Bridge Project, the Interstate 205 Freeway Widening Project,
the State Highway 217 Northbound Project, the Newberg-Dundee Bypass Project and
the State Highway 217 Southbound Project, and any other state transportation
projects implemented after October 6, 2017.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-020__subsec_2__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the Commissioner of the Bureau of Labor and Industries has found substantial
evidence, under ORS 279C.306, that a contracting agency that would otherwise
receive increased amounts of fuel tax revenues pursuant to this section on or
after January 1, 2024, has violated ORS 279C.305 within the five years
immediately preceding the date of the commissioner’s finding, or has materially
breached an agreement entered into pursuant to ORS 279C.306, the Department of
Transportation shall withhold the increased amounts until the final resolution
of the violation or breach is determined under ORS 279C.306.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-023">
          <num>319.023</num>
          <heading>Distribution of certain aircraft fuel tax moneys; applications; reports; rules</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-023__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The following
amounts shall be distributed in the manner prescribed in this section:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="319-023__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Any amount of tax on aircraft fuel usable in aircraft operated by turbine
engines that is computed on a basis in excess of one cent per gallon and any
amount of tax on all other aircraft fuel that is computed on a basis in excess
of nine cents per gallon, under ORS 319.020</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-023__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>; and</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="319-023__subsec_2__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Any amount of tax on aircraft fuel usable in aircraft operated by turbine
engines in excess of one cent per gallon and any amount of tax on all other
aircraft fuel in excess of nine cents per gallon, that is deducted before the
refunding of tax under ORS 319.330</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-023__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-023__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <paragraph eId="319-023__subsec_2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Applications for distributions under subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-023__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section may not be
approved unless the applicant demonstrates a commitment to contribute at least
five percent of the costs of the project to which the application relates. The
Oregon Department of Aviation shall adopt rules for purposes of this paragraph.</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="319-023__subsec_5__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may adopt rules that:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="319-023__subsec_5__subsec_b__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Set higher minimum contribution commitment requirements; or</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="319-023__subsec_5__subsec_b__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Establish maximum grant amounts.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-023__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <paragraph eId="319-023__subsec_3__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The State Aviation Board shall establish a review committee composed of one
member from each of the area commissions on transportation chartered by the
Oregon Transportation Commission.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-023__subsec_3__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The review committee shall meet as necessary to review applications for
distributions of amounts pursuant to this section. In reviewing applications,
the review committee shall consider:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="319-023__subsec_3__subsec_b__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Whether a proposed project:</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-023__subsec_3__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Reduces transportation costs for Oregon businesses or improves access to jobs
and sources of labor in this state;
(ii)
Results in an economic benefit to this state;
(iii)
Connects elements of Oregon’s aviation system in a way that will measurably
improve utilization and efficiency of the system;
(iv)
Is ready for construction or implementation; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-023__subsec_3__subsec_v">
              <num>(v)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Has a useful life expectancy that offers maximum benefit to this state; and</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="319-023__subsec_3__subsec_v__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>How much of the cost of the proposed project can be borne by the applicant from
sources other than Oregon Department of Aviation funds or the Connect Oregon
Fund.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-023__subsec_3__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The review committee shall recommend applications to the State Aviation Board
for approval.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-023__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <paragraph eId="319-023__subsec_4__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Five percent of the amounts described in subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-023__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section are
appropriated to the Oregon Department of Aviation for the costs of the
department and the State Aviation Board in administering this section.</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="319-023__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The remaining 95 percent of the amounts described in subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-023__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this
section shall be distributed pursuant to subsections</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-023__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-023__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this
section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-023__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <paragraph eId="319-023__subsec_5__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Seventy-five percent of the amounts described in subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-023__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <paragraph eId="319-023__subsec_4__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this
section shall be distributed for the following purposes:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="319-023__subsec_4__subsec_b__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>To assist airports in Oregon with match requirements for Federal Aviation
Administration Airport Improvement Program grants.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="319-023__subsec_4__subsec_b__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>To make grants for emergency preparedness and infrastructure projects, in
accordance with the Oregon Resilience Plan or the Oregon Aviation Plan.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="319-023__subsec_4__subsec_b__subsec_C">
                <num>(C)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>To make grants for:</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-023__subsec_4__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Services critical or essential to aviation, including, but not limited to,
fuel, sewer, water and weather equipment;
(ii)
Aviation-related business development, including, but not limited to, hangars,
parking for business aircraft and related facilities; or
(iii)
Airport development for local economic benefit, including, but not limited to,
signs and marketing.</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="319-023__subsec_4__subsec_i__subsec_D">
                <num>(D)</num>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-023__subsec_4__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To assist commercial air service to rural Oregon.
(ii)
The Oregon Department of Aviation may adopt a definition of “rural Oregon” for
purposes of this subparagraph.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-023__subsec_4__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The State Aviation Board may establish by rule priorities for the distributions
made pursuant to this subsection.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-023__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Twenty-five percent of the amounts described in subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-023__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <paragraph eId="319-023__subsec_4__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this
section shall be distributed to state-owned airports for the purposes of:</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-023__subsec_4__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Safety improvements recommended by the State Aviation Board and local community
airports.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-023__subsec_4__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Infrastructure projects at public use airports.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-023__subsec_7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <paragraph eId="319-023__subsec_7__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Not later than September 15 of each year, the State Aviation Board shall submit
the reports described in paragraph</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-023__subsec_7__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this subsection, in the manner
provided in ORS 192.245, to the interim committees, as applicable, of the
Legislative Assembly related to air transportation.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-023__subsec_7__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The reports required under this subsection shall describe in detail the
projects for which applications have been submitted and approved, the airports
affected, the names of the applicants and the persons who will perform the work
proposed in the applications, the progress of projects for which applications
have been approved and any other information the board considers necessary for
a comprehensive analysis of the implementation of this section. [2015 c.700 s7;
2017 c.750 s80a; 2019 c.485 s1; 2019 c.491 s26; 2021 c.526 s4]
Note: 319.023 was
enacted into law by the Legislative Assembly but was not added to or made a
part of ORS chapter 319 or any series therein by legislative action. See
Preface to Oregon Revised Statutes for further explanation.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-030">
          <num>319.030</num>
          <heading>License required for dealer in motor vehicle fuel</heading>
          <content>
            <p>No dealer shall
sell, use or distribute any motor vehicle fuel until the dealer has secured a
dealer’s license as required by ORS 319.010 to 319.430.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-040">
          <num>319.040</num>
          <heading>Application for and issuance of dealer’s license</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-040__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every person,
before becoming a dealer in motor vehicle fuel in this state, shall make an
application to the Department of Transportation for a license authorizing such
person to engage in business as a dealer.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-040__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Applications for the license must be made on forms prescribed, prepared and
furnished by the department.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-040__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The applications shall be accompanied by a duly acknowledged certificate
containing:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="319-040__subsec_3__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The name under which the dealer is transacting business within Oregon.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-040__subsec_3__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The places of business and location of distributing stations of the dealer in
Oregon.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-040__subsec_3__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The name and address of the managing agent, the names and addresses of the
several persons constituting the firm or partnership and, if a corporation, the
corporate name under which it is authorized to transact business and the names
and addresses of its principal officers and registered agent.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-040__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the dealer is an association of persons, firm, partnership or corporation
organized under the laws of another state, territory or country, if it has not
already done so, it must first comply with the laws of Oregon relating to the
transaction of its appropriate business in Oregon.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-040__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The application for a motor vehicle fuel dealer’s license having been accepted
for filing, and the bond required by ORS 319.050 having been accepted and
approved, the department may issue to the dealer a license in such form as the
department may prescribe to transact business as a dealer in the State of
Oregon. The license so issued is not assignable, and is valid only for the
dealer in whose name issued.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-040__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department shall keep and file all applications and bonds with an
alphabetical index thereof, together with a record of all licensed dealers. [Amended
by 1957 c.209 s2; 1999 c.769 s18]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-042">
          <num>319.042</num>
          <heading>Grounds for refusal to issue dealer license; hearing; records inspection</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-042__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The
Department of Transportation may refuse to issue a dealer license to a person
who applies as provided in ORS 319.040 if the department finds that the person:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="319-042__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Was the holder of a license revoked under ORS 319.100;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-042__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Is applying for a license on behalf of a real party in interest whose license
was revoked under ORS 319.100;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-042__subsec_1__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Was an officer, director, owner or managing employee of a nonindividual
licensee whose license was revoked under ORS 319.100;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-042__subsec_1__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Owes a debt to the state under ORS 319.010 to 319.430;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-042__subsec_1__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Had a license issued by a jurisdiction other than Oregon to sell or buy untaxed
motor vehicle fuel that was revoked or canceled for cause, whether the license
was held by the person as an individual or as an officer, director, owner or
managing employee or on behalf of a real party in interest;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-042__subsec_1__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In any jurisdiction, pleaded guilty to or was convicted of a crime directly
related to the sale, use or distribution of motor vehicle fuel, whether as an
individual or as an officer, director, owner or managing employee of a business
engaged in the sale or distribution of motor vehicle fuel;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-042__subsec_1__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Had a civil judgment imposed for conduct involving fraud, misrepresentation,
conversion or dishonesty, as an individual or as an officer, director, owner or
managing employee of a business engaged in the sale or distribution of motor
vehicle fuel;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-042__subsec_1__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Misrepresented or concealed a material fact in obtaining a license or in the
reinstatement thereof;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-042__subsec_1__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Violated a statute or administrative rule regarding fuel taxation or
distribution;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-042__subsec_1__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Failed to cooperate with the department’s investigations by:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="319-042__subsec_1__subsec_j__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Not furnishing requested documents;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="319-042__subsec_1__subsec_j__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Not furnishing when requested to do so a full and complete written explanation
of a matter under investigation by the department; or</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="319-042__subsec_1__subsec_j__subsec_C">
                <num>(C)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Not responding to a subpoena issued by the department; or</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-042__subsec_1__subsec_k">
              <num>(k)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Failed to comply with an order issued by the department.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-042__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In addition to refusal of a license for reasons specified in subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-042__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of
this section, the department may refuse to issue a dealer license for any other
reason the department deems sufficient.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-042__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Before refusing to issue a license under this section, the department shall
grant the applicant a hearing and shall give the applicant at least 10 days’
written notice of the time and place of the hearing. The hearing shall be a
contested case hearing under the provisions of ORS chapter 183.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-042__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For purpose of consideration of an application for a license, the department
may inspect or investigate the records of this state or of any other
jurisdiction to verify the information on the application and to verify the
applicant’s criminal and licensing history. [1999 c.769 s17]
Note: 319.042 was added
to and made a part of 319.010 to 319.430 by legislative action but was not
added to any smaller series therein. See Preface to Oregon Revised Statutes for
further explanation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-050">
          <num>319.050</num>
          <heading>Performance bond; hearing</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-050__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>At the time of filing the certificate and
application for a dealer’s license, the Department of Transportation shall
require the dealer to file with the department, in a form prepared by the
department, a bond executed by the dealer as principal with a corporate surety
authorized to transact business in this state. The bond shall be payable to the
State of Oregon conditioned upon performance of all the requirements of ORS
319.010 to 319.430, including the payment of all taxes, penalties and other
obligations of the dealer arising out of ORS 319.010 to 319.430.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-050__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Except as provided in ORS 319.051, 319.052 and 319.053, a bond under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-050__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section shall be in an amount that is equivalent to twice the
dealer’s estimated monthly license tax, as determined by the department, or
$250,000, whichever is less.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-050__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department may reduce or increase the required amount for a bond as
provided in ORS 319.051 and 319.052.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-050__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A bond given in connection with ORS 319.010 to 319.430 is a continuing
instrument and covers any and all periods of time including the first and all
subsequent periods for which a license may be granted in consequence of the
giving of the bond. The liability of the surety on the bond for the aggregate
of all claims that arise under the bond may not exceed the amount of the
penalty of the bond. No recoveries on any bond or any execution of any new bond
may invalidate any bond, but the total recoveries under any one bond may not
exceed the amount of the bond.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-050__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A dealer required under this section to obtain a bond may demand by proper
petition a hearing on the necessity of the bond or the reasonableness of the
amount required. The department shall grant the petition for a hearing and
shall hold the hearing within 10 days after the demand for the hearing. The
decision of the department becomes final 10 days after service of the order on
the dealer. The hearing is not subject to the requirements of ORS 183.413 to
183.470. [Amended by 1967 c.359 s690; 1999 c.769 s12; 2003 c.52 s1]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-051">
          <num>319.051</num>
          <heading>Conditions for reduced bond amount</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-051__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For a dealer described in subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-051__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section, the bond required by the Department of Transportation
under ORS 319.050 shall be in an amount that is equivalent to twice the dealer’s
estimated monthly license tax, as determined by the department, or $100,000,
whichever is less.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-051__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The provisions of subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-051__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section apply to a dealer who held a
valid dealer’s license on October 23, 1999, issued under ORS 319.010 to
319.430, and who, since October 23, 1999, has:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="319-051__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Not been required to file a bond greater than $100,000; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-051__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Performed, as determined by the department, the requirements of ORS 319.010 to
319.430, including the payment of all taxes, penalties and other obligations of
the dealer arising out of ORS 319.010 to 319.430. [2003 c.52 s3]
Note: 319.051 to
319.053 were added to and made a part of 319.010 to 319.430 by legislative
action but were not added to any smaller series therein. See Preface to Oregon
Revised Statutes for further explanation.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-052">
          <num>319.052</num>
          <heading>Conditions for increased bond amount; request and conditions for reduction; rules</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-052__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Department of Transportation shall increase a dealer’s bond filed under
ORS 319.050 to an amount that is equivalent to twice the dealer’s estimated
monthly license tax, as determined by the department, or $1 million, whichever
is less, if, within a 24-month period, the dealer:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="319-052__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Was late three or more times in filing reports or making payments to the
department;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-052__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Had three or more checks or electronic funds transfers to the department
dishonored for lack of funds or credit;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-052__subsec_1__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Failed to maintain or make available a record of all purchases, receipts, sales
and distribution of motor vehicle fuel as required under ORS 319.390; or</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-052__subsec_1__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Had a motor vehicle fuel dealer license issued in this state or another
jurisdiction revoked.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-052__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department may waive an increase in the bond amount under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-052__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of
this section if the department determines that the dealer did not intend to
avoid payment of license taxes when the dealer engaged in the conduct described
in subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-052__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <paragraph eId="319-052__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>,</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-052__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-052__subsec_1__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this section or when the dealer engaged in
the conduct that led to the license revocation described in subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-052__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <paragraph eId="319-052__subsec_1__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this section. If the department waives an increase in the bond amount, the
bond shall remain at an amount that is:</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-052__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Required under ORS 319.051 for a dealer described in ORS 319.051; or</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-052__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Required under ORS 319.050.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-052__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the department increases the bond amount as provided in subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-052__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of
this section, the dealer may, after 24 months, request in writing that the
department reduce the bond amount. The department shall reduce the bond amount
if the department determines that the dealer, in the 24 months prior to the
dealer’s written request:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="319-052__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Filed timely reports and made timely payments;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-052__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Had no checks or electronic funds transfers to the department dishonored for
lack of funds or credit;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-052__subsec_1__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Maintained and made available a record of all purchases, receipts, sales and
distribution of motor vehicle fuel as required under ORS 319.390; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-052__subsec_1__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Did not have a motor vehicle fuel dealer license issued in this state or
another jurisdiction revoked.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-052__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the department determines that the dealer met all of the requirements under
subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-052__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section, the department shall reduce the bond required
of a dealer described in ORS 319.050 or a dealer described in ORS 319.051 to an
amount that is equivalent to twice the dealer’s estimated monthly license tax,
as determined by the department, or $250,000, whichever is less.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-052__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the department determines that the dealer failed to meet the requirements
under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-052__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section and that the failure was not due to the
dealer’s intent to avoid payment of license taxes, the department may reduce
the bond required of a dealer described in ORS 319.050 or a dealer described in
ORS 319.051 to an amount that is equivalent to twice the dealer’s estimated
monthly license tax, as determined by the department, or $250,000, whichever is
less.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-052__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For purposes of this section, the department shall adopt rules establishing
what constitutes evidence that a dealer did not intend to avoid payment of
license taxes. [2003 c.52 s4]
Note: See note under
319.051.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-053">
          <num>319.053</num>
          <heading>Amount of bond when twice license tax is less than $1,000</heading>
          <content>
            <p>If the amount
that is equivalent to twice the amount of a dealer’s estimated monthly license
tax, as determined by the Department of Transportation, is an amount that is
less than $1,000, the bond amount required by ORS 319.050, 319.051 or 319.052
shall be $1,000. [2003 c.52 s5]
Note: See note under
319.051.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-060">
          <num>319.060</num>
          <heading>Deposit in lieu of bond</heading>
          <content>
            <p>In lieu of the bond or bonds in total amount as fixed
under ORS 319.050, 319.051, 319.052 or 319.053, any dealer may deposit with the
State Treasurer, under such terms and conditions as the Department of
Transportation may prescribe, a like amount of lawful money of the United
States or bonds or other obligations of the United States, the State of Oregon,
or any county of this state, of an actual market value not less than the amount
so fixed by the department. [Amended by 2003 c.52 s7]</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-070">
          <num>319.070</num>
          <heading>Release of surety</heading>
          <content>
            <p>Any surety on a bond furnished by a dealer as provided in ORS 319.050 shall be
released and discharged from any and all liability to the state accruing on
such bond after the expiration of 30 days from the date upon which the surety
has lodged with the Department of Transportation a written request to be
released and discharged, but this provision shall not operate to relieve,
release or discharge the surety from any liability already accrued or which
accrues before the expiration of the 30-day period. The department shall
promptly, upon receiving the request, notify the dealer who furnished the bond,
and unless the dealer, on or before the expiration of the 30-day period, files
a new bond, or makes a deposit in accordance with the requirements of ORS
319.050 and 319.060, the department forthwith shall cancel the dealer’s
license.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-080">
          <num>319.080</num>
          <heading>Additional bond or deposit</heading>
          <content>
            <p>The Department of Transportation may require a dealer
to give a new or additional surety bond or to deposit additional securities of
the character specified in ORS 319.060 if, in its opinion, the security of the
surety bond theretofore filed by the dealer, or the market value of the
properties deposited as security by the dealer, becomes impaired or inadequate.
Upon failure of the dealer to give the new or additional surety bond or to
deposit additional securities within 10 days after being requested so to do by
the department, the department forthwith shall cancel the license of the
dealer.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-090">
          <num>319.090</num>
          <heading>Immediate collection of tax and interest; penalties; waiver</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-090__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any dealer
sells, distributes or uses any motor vehicle fuel without first filing the
certificate and bond and securing the license required by ORS 319.030, the
license tax provided in ORS 319.020 shall immediately be due and payable on
account of all motor vehicle fuel so sold, distributed or used.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-090__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Except as otherwise provided in this subsection, the Department of
Transportation shall proceed forthwith to determine, from the best available
sources, the amount of such tax, and it shall immediately assess the tax and
interest in the amount found due, together with a penalty of 100 percent of the
tax, and shall make its certificate of such assessment and penalty. The
department may waive all or part of a penalty imposed under this subsection if
the department determines that a violation of the requirement under this
section to file the certificate and bond or to secure the license was due to
reasonable cause and without intent to avoid payment of the tax. In any suit or
proceeding to collect such tax, interest or penalty, the certificate is prima
facie evidence that the dealer therein named is indebted to the State of Oregon
in the amount of the tax, interest and penalty therein stated. [Amended by 1981
c.396 s1; 1989 c.664 s3; 1999 c.769 s5]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-096">
          <num>319.096</num>
          <heading>Suspension of license; liability for tax; reinstatement</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-096__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The
Department of Transportation may, prior to a hearing, suspend the license of a
motor vehicle fuel dealer who refuses or neglects to comply with the provisions
of ORS 319.010 to 319.430 until the dealer complies with the provisions of ORS
319.010 to 319.430.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-096__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Upon suspension of a dealer’s license under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-096__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section, the
department shall immediately notify:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="319-096__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The dealer by certified mail of the dealer’s license suspension and the dealer’s
right to request an immediate hearing to contest the license suspension; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-096__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>All other licensed motor vehicle fuel dealers by a method determined under ORS
319.102 that the authority of the dealer to purchase tax-deferred motor vehicle
fuel has been suspended.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-096__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If a licensed motor vehicle fuel dealer sells tax-deferred motor vehicle fuel
to a dealer whose license has been suspended under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-096__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this
section after the third day after the selling dealer receives notice of the
suspension under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-096__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section, the selling dealer and the
suspended dealer are jointly and severally liable for the tax owed on the sale
of the fuel.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-096__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <paragraph eId="319-096__subsec_4__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding the joint and several liability of the selling dealer and the
suspended dealer under subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-096__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section, the department shall
attempt to collect from the suspended dealer the tax owed on the fuel for a
period of 45 days from the date of the sale to the suspended dealer.</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="319-096__subsec_3__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>After the expiration of the 45-day period under this subsection, the department
shall collect from the selling dealer any tax not collected from the suspended
dealer under this subsection.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-096__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department shall waive the liability of a selling dealer under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-096__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section if the selling dealer establishes to the satisfaction of
the department that:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="319-096__subsec_3__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The sale of the motor vehicle fuel to the suspended dealer was due to
circumstances that were beyond the control of the selling dealer; or</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-096__subsec_3__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The dealer whose license was suspended engaged in fraud or deceit to avoid
timely payment of the tax to the selling dealer.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-096__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When a dealer whose license has been suspended under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-096__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this
section complies with the provisions of ORS 319.010 to 319.430, the department
shall reinstate the dealer’s license and shall notify by a method determined
under ORS 319.102 all licensed motor vehicle fuel dealers that the dealer’s
license has been reinstated and that the dealer is authorized to purchase
tax-deferred fuel.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-096__subsec_7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the department determines that a dealer whose license has been suspended
under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-096__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section is unwilling or unable to comply with the
provisions of ORS 319.010 to 319.430, the department shall revoke the license
of the dealer as provided in ORS 319.100. [2003 c.113 s2]
Note: 319.096, 319.098
and 319.102 were added to and made a part of 319.010 to 319.430 by legislative
action but were not added to any smaller series therein. See Preface to Oregon
Revised Statutes for further explanation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-098">
          <num>319.098</num>
          <heading>Contesting license suspension</heading>
          <content>
            <p>A dealer whose license has been suspended
by the Department of Transportation under ORS 319.096 may contest the
suspension as provided in ORS chapter 183. [2003 c.113 s3]
Note: See note under
319.096.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-100">
          <num>319.100</num>
          <heading>Revocation of license</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-100__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Department of Transportation shall revoke the
license of any dealer whose license has been suspended under ORS 319.096 and
who the department determines is unwilling or unable to comply with the
provisions of ORS 319.010 to 319.430.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-100__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department shall mail by certified mail addressed to the dealer at the
last-known address in the files of the department, a notice of intention to
revoke the dealer’s license. The notice shall give the reason for the
revocation of the license.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-100__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The license revocation becomes effective without further notice if within 10
days from the mailing of the notice the dealer has not complied with the
provisions of ORS 319.010 to 319.430.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-100__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department shall provide notice of the revocation of the license of a dealer
under this section to all other licensed motor vehicle fuel dealers by a method
determined under ORS 319.102.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-102">
          <num>319.102</num>
          <heading>Notice to dealers of suspension or revocation of another dealer’s license; rules</heading>
          <content>
            <p>The Department of Transportation shall establish by rule the most efficient
method of notifying licensed motor vehicle fuel dealers as required under ORS
319.096 and 319.100 that a dealer’s license has been suspended, revoked or
reinstated. The possible methods may include, but need not be limited to,
notice by telephone, electronic mail or regular mail. [2003 c.113 s5]
Note: See note under
319.096.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-110">
          <num>319.110</num>
          <heading>Cancellation of license on request of dealer or when licensee no longer a dealer</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-110__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Department of Transportation may, upon written request of a dealer,
cancel any license issued to such dealer, the cancellation to become effective
30 days from the date of receipt of the written request.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-110__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the department ascertains and finds that the person to whom a license has
been issued is no longer engaged in the business of a dealer, the department
may cancel the license of such dealer upon investigation after 30 days’ notice
has been mailed to the last-known address of the dealer.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-120">
          <num>319.120</num>
          <heading>Remedies cumulative</heading>
          <content>
            <p>Except as otherwise provided in ORS 319.180 and 319.200, the remedies of the
state provided in ORS 319.090, 319.100 and 319.110 are cumulative. No action
taken pursuant to those statutes shall relieve any person from the penal
provisions of ORS 319.010 to 319.430 and 319.990. [Amended by 1967 c.54 s1;
1999 c.769 s7]</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-125">
          <num>319.125</num>
          <heading>Change of ownership; cancellation of license</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-125__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the case of a corporation with more than 100 stockholders, transfer of stock
in normal trading is not considered a change in ownership.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-125__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the case of a corporation with 100 or fewer stockholders, transfer of less
than 50 percent of the stock in any period of 12 consecutive months is not
considered a change in ownership. [1987 c.610 s21]
Note: 319.125 was added
to and made a part of 319.010 to 319.430 by legislative action but was not
added to any smaller series therein. See Preface to Oregon Revised Statutes for
further explanation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-180">
          <num>319.180</num>
          <heading>Payment of tax; delinquency penalty; interest rates</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-180__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The license
tax imposed by ORS 319.020 shall be paid on or before the 25th day of each
month to the Department of Transportation which, upon request, shall receipt
the dealer therefor.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-180__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Except as provided in subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-180__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section, to any license tax not
paid as required by subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-180__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section there shall be added a
penalty of one percent of such license tax.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-180__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Except as provided in subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-180__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section, if the tax and penalty
required by subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-180__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section are not received on or before the
close of business on the last day of the month in which the payment is due, a
further penalty of 10 percent shall be paid in addition to the penalty provided
for in subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-180__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-180__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the department determines that the delinquency was due to reasonable cause
and without any intent to avoid payment, the penalties provided by subsections</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-180__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-180__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section may be waived. Penalties imposed by this section
shall not apply when the penalty provided in ORS 319.090 has been assessed and
paid.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-180__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <paragraph eId="319-180__subsec_5__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the license tax imposed by ORS 319.020 is not paid as required by subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-180__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section, interest shall be charged at the rate of 0.0329 percent
per day until the tax and interest have been paid in full.</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="319-180__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the license tax imposed by ORS 319.020 is overpaid, the department may
credit interest to the account of the taxpayer in the amount of 0.0329 percent
per day up to a maximum amount that equals any interest assessed against the
taxpayer under paragraph</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-180__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this subsection in any given audit period.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-180__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No dealer who incurs a tax liability as provided for in ORS 319.010 to 319.430,
shall knowingly and willfully fail to report and pay the same to the department
as required by ORS 319.010 to 319.430. [Amended by 1955 c.730 s3; 1957 c.209 s4;
1959 c.505 s5; 1963 c.226 s2; 1967 c.54 s2; 1979 c.344 s4; 1987 c.610 s6; 1989
c.664 s5; 1999 c.769 s6]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-182">
          <num>319.182</num>
          <heading>Collection of delinquent tax, interest or penalty; warrant; judgment lien</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-182__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If a person
fails to pay in full any tax, interest or penalty due under ORS 319.010 to
319.430, the Department of Transportation may issue a warrant for the amount
due, with the added penalties or charges, interest and the cost of executing
the warrant. A copy of the warrant shall be mailed or delivered to the taxpayer
by the department at the taxpayer’s last-known address.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-182__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>At any time after issuing a warrant under this section, the department may
record the warrant in the County Clerk Lien Record of any county of this state.
Recording of the warrant has the effect described in ORS 205.125. After
recording a warrant, the department may direct the sheriff for the county in
which the warrant is recorded to levy upon and sell the real and personal property
of the taxpayer found within that county, and to levy upon any currency of the
taxpayer found within that county, for the application of the proceeds or
currency against the amount reflected in the warrant and the sheriff’s cost of
executing the warrant. The sheriff shall proceed on the warrant in the same
manner prescribed by law for executions issued against property pursuant to a
judgment, and is entitled to the same fees as provided for executions issued
against property pursuant to a judgment. The fees of the sheriff shall be added
to and collected as a part of the warrant liability.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-182__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the discretion of the department a warrant under this section may be
directed to any agent authorized by the department to collect taxes, and in the
execution of the warrant the agent has all of the powers conferred by law upon
sheriffs, but is entitled to no fee or compensation in excess of actual
expenses paid in the performance of such duty. [1999 c.769 s2; 2003 c.576 s200;
2011 c.661 s3]
Note: 319.182, 319.184
and 319.186 were added to and made a part of 319.010 to 319.430 by legislative
action but were not added to any smaller series therein. See Preface to Oregon
Revised Statutes for further explanation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-184">
          <num>319.184</num>
          <heading>Use of collection agency</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-184__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Department of Transportation may engage the
services of a collection agency to collect any of the taxes, interest and
penalties due to the state under ORS 319.010 to 319.430. The department may
engage the services by entering into agreements to pay reasonable charges on a
contingent fee or other basis.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-184__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department may assign to the collection agency, for collection purposes
only, any of the taxes, interest and penalties due the state under ORS 319.010
to 319.430.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-184__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The collection agency may bring such actions or take such proceedings,
including attachment and garnishment proceedings, as may be necessary. [1999
c.769 s3]
Note: See note under
319.182.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-186">
          <num>319.186</num>
          <heading>Uncollectible tax, interest or penalty</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-186__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any tax, interest or penalty due the
state assigned to a collection agency pursuant to ORS 319.184 that remains
uncollected for two years after the date of the assignment meets the criteria
for uncollectibility formulated pursuant to ORS 293.240.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-186__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>ORS 293.245 applies to any tax, interest or penalty due the state and described
in subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-186__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section. [1999 c.769 s4; 2011 c.223 s2]
Note: See note under
319.182.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-190">
          <num>319.190</num>
          <heading>Monthly statement of dealer; penalty; rules</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-190__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every dealer in motor vehicle
fuel shall render to the Department of Transportation, on or before the 25th
day of each month, on forms prescribed, prepared and furnished by the
department, and in the manner provided by the department by rule, a signed
statement of the number of gallons of motor vehicle fuel sold, distributed or
used by the dealer during the preceding calendar month. The statement shall be
signed by one of the principal officers, or by an authorized agent in case of a
corporation; or by the managing agent or owner in case of a firm or
association.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-190__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The signed statement filed with the department as required by this section is a
public record. All other documents, including supporting schedules and
information received from other taxing jurisdictions and entities, shall be
kept confidential and exempt from public inspection except that such
information may be shared with tax collecting entities in other jurisdictions
on the condition that the receiving jurisdiction agrees to keep such information
confidential. If a statement is not received on or before the 25th day of each
month, a penalty shall be assessed pursuant to ORS 319.180 or, if the
department determines that no tax is due, a penalty of $25 shall be assessed. [Amended
by 1955 c.730 s4; 1957 c.209 s5; 1987 c.610 s7; 2011 c.101 s2]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-192">
          <num>319.192</num>
          <heading>Refund to dealer of uncollectible taxes; rules</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-192__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Upon
application to the Department of Transportation, a motor vehicle fuel dealer
may obtain a refund of the tax paid to the department on sales of motor vehicle
fuel if:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="319-192__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The dealer has received less than full consideration for the fuel from or on
behalf of a purchaser;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-192__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The account has been declared by the dealer to be an uncollectible account
receivable and meets all applicable standards for deductibility for federal
income tax purposes pursuant to the Internal Revenue Code; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-192__subsec_1__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The dealer has not previously received a refund from the department for motor
vehicle fuel taxes not paid by the same purchaser.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-192__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For purposes of determining the amount of a refund due under this section, the
amount of consideration received by the motor vehicle fuel dealer shall be
apportioned between the charges for the motor vehicle fuel and the tax for the
fuel. The amount of the tax refunded may not exceed the amount of tax paid
under ORS 319.020.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-192__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the motor vehicle fuel dealer who receives a refund under this section
subsequently collects any amount from any source for the account declared
uncollectible, the amount collected shall be apportioned between the charges
for the motor vehicle fuel and the corresponding tax for the fuel. The motor
vehicle fuel tax collected shall be returned to the department.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-192__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department shall adopt rules governing the process of applying for and
receiving refunds under this section. [2003 c.307 s2]
Note: 319.192 was added
to and made a part of 319.010 to 319.430 by legislative action but was not
added to any smaller series therein. See Preface to Oregon Revised Statutes for
further explanation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-200">
          <num>319.200</num>
          <heading>Assessing tax and penalty where dealer fails to report</heading>
          <content>
            <p>If any dealer,
except one subject to ORS 319.090, fails to file the report required by ORS
319.190, the Department of Transportation shall proceed forthwith to determine
from the best available source the amount of motor vehicle fuel sold,
distributed or used by such dealer for the period unreported, and such
determination shall be prima facie evidence of the amount of such fuel sold,
distributed or used. The department immediately shall assess the license tax in
the amount so determined, adding thereto a penalty of 10 percent for failure to
report. The penalty shall be cumulative of other penalties provided in ORS
319.010 to 319.430 and 319.990. In any suit brought to enforce the rights of
the state under this section, the certificate of the department showing the
amount of taxes, penalties, interest and costs unpaid by any dealer and that
the same are due and unpaid to the state is prima facie evidence of the facts
as shown. [Amended by 1967 c.54 s3; 1987 c.610 s8]</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-210">
          <num>319.210</num>
          <heading>Billing purchasers</heading>
          <content>
            <p>Bills shall be rendered to all purchasers of motor vehicle fuel by dealers in
motor vehicle fuel. The bills shall separately state and describe to the
satisfaction of the Department of Transportation the different products shipped
thereunder and shall be serially numbered except where other sales invoice
controls acceptable to the department are maintained. [Amended by 1955 c.730 s5;
1987 c.610 s9]</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-220">
          <num>319.220</num>
          <heading>Receipt, payment or sale of motor vehicle fuel without invoice or delivery tag prohibited</heading>
          <content>
            <p>No person shall receive and accept any shipment of motor vehicle fuel from any
dealer, or pay for the same, or sell or offer the shipment for sale, unless the
shipment is accompanied by an invoice or delivery tag showing the date upon
which shipment was delivered and the name of the dealer in motor vehicle fuel. [Amended
by 1955 c.730 s6; 1987 c.610 s10]</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-230">
          <num>319.230</num>
          <heading>Transporting motor vehicle fuel in bulk</heading>
          <content>
            <p>Every person operating any conveyance for
the purpose of hauling, transporting or delivering motor vehicle fuel in bulk
shall, before entering upon the public highways of this state with such
conveyance, have and possess during the entire time of hauling or transporting
such motor vehicle fuel an invoice, bill of sale or other written statement
showing the number of gallons, the true name and address of the seller or
consignor, and the true name and address of the buyer or consignee, if any, of
the same. The person hauling such motor vehicle fuel shall at the request of any
sheriff, deputy sheriff, constable, state police or other officer authorized by
law to inquire into or investigate such matters, produce and offer for
inspection the invoice, bill of sale or other statement. [Amended by 1957 c.209
s6]</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-240">
          <num>319.240</num>
          <heading>Exemption of export fuel</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-240__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <paragraph eId="319-240__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The license tax imposed under ORS 319.020 may
not be imposed on motor vehicle fuel that is exported from this state to
another state, territory or country where the motor vehicle fuel is unloaded by
a dealer who has a valid motor vehicle fuel dealer’s license or its equivalent
issued by the state, territory or country to which the fuel is exported and
where it is unloaded.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-240__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in ORS 319.245, paragraph</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-240__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this subsection does not
apply to motor vehicle fuel that is exported from this state to a federally
recognized Indian reservation located wholly or partially within the borders of
this state.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-240__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In support of any exemption from license taxes claimed under this section other
than in the case of stock transfers or deliveries in equipment, every dealer
must execute and file with the Department of Transportation an export
certificate in such form as shall be prescribed, prepared and furnished by the
department, containing a statement, made by some person having actual knowledge
of the fact of such exportation, that the motor vehicle fuel has been exported
from the State of Oregon, and giving such details with reference to such
shipment as the department may require. All export certificates in support of shipments
to other states, territories or countries must be completed and on file in the
principal office of the dealer in this state within three months after the
close of the calendar month in which the shipments to which they relate are
made, unless the state, territory or country of destination would not be
prejudiced with respect to its collection of taxes thereon if the certificate
is not filed within such time. The department may demand of any dealer such
additional data as is deemed necessary in support of any such certificate, and
failure to supply such data will constitute a waiver of all right to exemption
claimed by virtue of such certificate. The department may, in a case where it
believes no useful purpose would be served by filing of an export certificate,
waive the certificate.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-240__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any motor vehicle fuel carried from this state in the fuel tank of a motor
vehicle shall not be considered as exported from this state, except that a
refund of the tax may be paid on such fuel as provided in ORS 319.280</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-240__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <paragraph eId="319-240__subsec_1__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-240__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No person shall, through false statement, trick or device, or otherwise, obtain
motor vehicle fuel for export upon which the Oregon tax has not been paid and
fail to export the same, or any portion thereof, or cause the motor vehicle fuel
or any portion thereof not to be exported, or shall divert the motor vehicle
fuel or any portion thereof, or shall cause it to be diverted from interstate
or foreign transit begun in this state, or shall unlawfully return the motor
vehicle fuel or any portion thereof to be used or sold in this state and fail
to notify the department and the dealer from whom the motor vehicle fuel was
originally purchased of the person’s act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-240__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No dealer or other person shall conspire with any person to withhold from export,
or divert from interstate or foreign transit begun in this state, or to return
motor vehicle fuel to this state for sale or use so as to avoid any of the
taxes imposed under ORS 319.010 to 319.430. [Amended by 1953 c.82 s2; 1955
c.730 s7; 1959 c.186 s1; 1963 c.257 s1; 1987 c.610 s11; 2003 c.56 s1; 2021
c.630 s167]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-245">
          <num>319.245</num>
          <heading>Exemption of motor vehicle fuel purchased by Indian tribes; eligibility; dealer reports; rules</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-245__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>As used in this section:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="319-245__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>“Indian tribe” means a federally recognized Indian tribe in Oregon.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-245__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>“Tribal entity” means an entity wholly owned by an Indian tribe.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-245__subsec_1__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>“Tribal member entity” means an entity wholly owned and operated by an enrolled
member of an Indian tribe.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-245__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The first sale, use or distribution of motor vehicle fuel in this state is
exempt from the license tax imposed under ORS 319.020</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-245__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <paragraph eId="319-245__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>if:</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-245__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The motor vehicle fuel is purchased by an Indian tribe, tribal entity or tribal
member entity directly or from a dealer that purchased the motor vehicle fuel
in a transaction that would otherwise be subject to the tax; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-245__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The motor vehicle fuel is delivered to a service station that is owned by an
Indian tribe, tribal entity or tribal member entity and operated on the respective
Indian tribe’s reservation or trust land.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-245__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In order to be eligible for the exemption under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-245__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section,
the Indian tribe must:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="319-245__subsec_2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Impose a tax on the distribution of the motor vehicle fuel at the same rate as
the license tax imposed under ORS 319.020</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-245__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <paragraph eId="319-245__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-245__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Expend the revenue from the tax imposed pursuant to paragraph</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-245__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this
subsection solely for uses that are consistent with the requirements of Article
IX, section 3a, of the Oregon Constitution; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-245__subsec_1__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Certify annually to the Department of Transportation that the Indian tribe is
in compliance with this subsection.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-245__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A dealer described in subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-245__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <paragraph eId="319-245__subsec_2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this section shall report to the
department such sales of motor vehicle fuel to Indian tribes, tribal entities
and tribal member entities.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-245__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department shall adopt rules prescribing the processes, forms and
information that the forms must include for the certification required under
subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-245__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <paragraph eId="319-245__subsec_3__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this section and the reports required under subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-245__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section. [2021 c.630 s165]
Note: 319.245 was added
to and made a part of 319.010 to 319.430 by legislative action but was not
added to any smaller series therein. See Preface to Oregon Revised Statutes for
further explanation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-250">
          <num>319.250</num>
          <heading>Exemption of certain sales to Armed Forces; reports</heading>
          <content>
            <p>The license tax
imposed by ORS 319.020 shall not be imposed on any aircraft or motor vehicle
fuel sold to the Armed Forces of the United States for use in ships, aircraft
or for export from this state; but every dealer shall be required to report
such sales to the Department of Transportation in such detail as may be
required. A certificate by an authorized officer of such Armed Forces shall be
accepted by the dealer as sufficient proof that the sale is for the purpose
specified in the certificate. [Amended by 1955 c.730 s8; 1959 c.186 s2; 1961
c.43 s1; 1987 c.610 s12]</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-260">
          <num>319.260</num>
          <heading>Exemption of fuel in vehicles coming into or leaving state</heading>
          <content>
            <p>Any person coming
into or leaving Oregon in a motor vehicle may transport in the fuel tank of
such vehicle motor vehicle fuel for the purpose of operating such motor
vehicle, without complying with any of the provisions imposed upon dealers by
ORS 319.010 to 319.430. However, if motor vehicle fuel so brought into the state
is removed from the fuel tank of the vehicle or used for any purpose other than
the propulsion of the vehicle, the person so importing the fuel into this state
shall be subject to all the provisions of ORS 319.010 to 319.430 and 319.990
applying to dealers. [Amended by 1987 c.610 s12a]</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-270">
          <num>319.270</num>
          <heading>Exemption of fuel sold or distributed to dealers</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-270__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding ORS 319.020, if the first sale, use or distribution of motor
vehicle fuel or aircraft fuel is from one licensed dealer to another licensed
dealer, the selling or distributing dealer is not required to pay the license
tax imposed by ORS 319.020. When the purchasing or receiving dealer first
sells, uses or distributes the fuel, that dealer shall pay the license tax
regardless of whether the sale, use or distribution is to another licensed
dealer.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-270__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A dealer who renders monthly statements to the Department of Transportation as
required by ORS 319.020 and 319.190 shall show separately the number of gallons
of motor vehicle fuel sold or delivered to dealers. [Amended by 1987 c.610 s13]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-275">
          <num>319.275</num>
          <heading>Liability for taxes, interest and penalties when person importing fuel does not hold license</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-275__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A person who is not a licensed dealer shall not accept or receive motor
vehicle or aircraft fuel in this state from a person who imports motor vehicle
or aircraft fuel who does not hold a valid motor vehicle fuel dealer license in
this state. If a person who is not a licensed dealer accepts or receives motor
vehicle fuel or aircraft fuel from a person who imports motor vehicle fuel or
aircraft fuel and does not hold a valid motor vehicle fuel dealer license in
this state, the purchaser or receiver shall be liable for all taxes, interest
and penalties contained in ORS 319.010 to 319.430.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-275__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A licensed dealer who accepts or receives motor vehicle fuel or aircraft fuel
in this state from a person who imports motor vehicle or aircraft fuel who does
not hold a valid dealer license in this state shall pay the tax imposed by ORS
319.020 to the Department of Transportation upon the first sale, use or
distribution of the motor vehicle fuel or aircraft fuel.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-280">
          <num>319.280</num>
          <heading>Refunds generally</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-280__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any person who has paid any tax on motor vehicle fuel levied or directed to
be paid by ORS 319.010 to 319.430 either directly by the collection of the tax
by the vendor from the consumer, or indirectly by adding the amount of the tax
to the price of the fuel and paid by the consumer, shall be reimbursed and
repaid the amount of such tax paid, except as provided in ORS 319.290 to
319.330, if such person has:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="319-280__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Purchased and used such fuel for the purpose of operating or propelling a
stationary gas engine, a tractor or a motor boat, if the motor boat is used for
commercial purposes at any time during the period for which the refund is
claimed;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-280__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Purchased and used such fuel for cleaning or dyeing or other commercial use,
except when used in motor vehicles operated upon any highway;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-280__subsec_1__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Purchased and exported such fuel from this state, in containers other than fuel
supply tanks of motor vehicles, provided that the person:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="319-280__subsec_1__subsec_c__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Exports the motor vehicle fuel from this state to another state, territory or
country, not including a federally recognized Indian reservation located wholly
or partially within the borders of this state, where the motor vehicle fuel is
unloaded; and</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="319-280__subsec_1__subsec_c__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Has a valid motor vehicle fuel dealer’s license or its equivalent issued by the
state, territory or country to which the fuel is exported and where it is
unloaded;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-280__subsec_1__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Purchased and exported such fuel in the fuel supply tank of a motor vehicle and
has used such fuel to operate the vehicle upon the highways of another state,
if the user has paid to the other state a similar motor vehicle fuel tax on the
same fuel, or has paid any other highway use tax the rate for which is
increased because such fuel was not purchased in, and the tax thereon paid, to
such state; or</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-280__subsec_1__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Purchased and used such fuel for small engines that are not used to propel
motor vehicles on highways, including but not limited to those that power lawn
mowers, leaf blowers, chain saws and similar implements.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-280__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When a motor vehicle with auxiliary equipment uses fuel and there is no
auxiliary motor for such equipment or separate tank for such a motor, a refund
may be claimed and allowed as provided by subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-280__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section,
except as otherwise provided by this subsection, without the necessity of
furnishing proof of the amount of fuel used in the operation of the auxiliary
equipment. The person claiming the refund may present to the Department of
Transportation a statement of the claim and be allowed a refund as follows:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="319-280__subsec_4__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For fuel used in pumping aircraft fuel, motor vehicle fuel, fuel or heating
oils or other petroleum products by a power take-off unit on a delivery truck,
refund shall be allowed claimant for tax paid on fuel purchased at the rate of
three-fourths of one gallon for each 1,000 gallons of petroleum products
delivered.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-280__subsec_4__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For fuel used in operating a power take-off unit on a cement mixer truck or on
a garbage truck, claimant shall be allowed a refund of 25 percent of the tax
paid on all fuel used in such a truck.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-280__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When a person purchases and uses motor vehicle fuel in a vehicle equipped with
a power take-off unit, a refund may be claimed for fuel used to operate the
power take-off unit provided the vehicle is equipped with a metering device
approved by the department and designed to operate only while the vehicle is
stationary and the parking brake is engaged; the quantity of fuel measured by
the metering device shall be presumed to be the quantity of fuel consumed by the
operation of the power take-off unit.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-280__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Before any such refund may be granted, the person claiming such refund must
present to the department a statement, accompanied by the original invoices, or
reasonable facsimiles approved by the department, showing such purchases;
provided that in lieu of original invoices or facsimiles, refunds submitted
under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-280__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <paragraph eId="319-280__subsec_1__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this section shall be accompanied by information
showing source of the fuel used and evidence of payment of tax to the state in
which the fuel was used. The statement shall be made over the signature of the
claimant, and shall state the total amount of such fuel for which the claimant
is entitled to be reimbursed under subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-280__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section. The
department upon the presentation of the statement and invoices or facsimiles,
or other required documents, shall cause to be repaid to the claimant from the
taxes collected on motor vehicle fuel such taxes so paid by the claimant. [Amended
by 1959 c.186 s3; 1963 c.257 s2; 1969 c.465 s1; 1971 c.163 s1; 1973 c.135 s1;
1985 c.152 s1; 1997 c.364 s1; 2001 c.820 s4; 2003 c.56 s2; 2013 c.781 s19; 2019
c.428 s5]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-290">
          <num>319.290</num>
          <heading>Limitation on applications for refunds</heading>
          <content>
            <p>Applications for refunds made under ORS
319.280, 319.320 and 319.330 must be filed with the Department of
Transportation before the expiration of 15 months from the date of purchase or
invoice, except that unused fuel reported as an ending inventory on any claim
may be included in a subsequent claim if presented not later than 15 months
from the filing date of the claim which established the inventory. All
applications for refunds based upon exportation of motor vehicle fuel from this
state in the fuel supply tank of a motor vehicle must be filed with the
department before the expiration of 15 months from the last day of the month in
which the fuel was used, or before the expiration of 15 months from the date of
an assessment for unpaid tax by the state in which the fuel was used. [Amended
by 1955 c.730 s9; 1963 c.257 s3; 1979 c.344 s5]</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-300">
          <num>319.300</num>
          <heading>Seller to give invoice for each purchase made by person entitled to refund</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-300__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When motor
vehicle fuel is sold to a person who claims to be entitled to a refund of the
tax imposed, the seller of the motor vehicle fuel shall make and deliver at the
time of the sale separate invoices for each purchase in such form and
containing any information prescribed by the Department of Transportation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-300__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The invoices shall be legibly written and shall be void if any corrections or
erasures appear on the face thereof. Any person who alters any part of any
invoice that will tend to give to the claimant an illegal gain, shall have the
entire claim invalidated. The seller shall for a period of at least 18 months
retain copies of all invoices and make them available to the department upon
request. [Amended by 1953 c.77 s2; 1955 c.730 s10; 1957 c.209 s7]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-310">
          <num>319.310</num>
          <heading>Claims for refunds may be required to be under oath; investigation of claims</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-310__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The
Department of Transportation may require any person who makes claim for refund
of tax upon motor vehicle fuel to furnish a statement, under oath, giving the
occupation, description of the machines or equipment in which the motor vehicle
fuel was used, the place where used and such other information as the
department may require.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-310__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department may investigate claims and gather and compile such information
in regard to the claims as it considers necessary to safeguard the state and
prevent fraudulent practices in connection with tax refunds and tax evasions.
The department may, in order to establish the validity of any claim, examine
the books and records of the claimant for such purposes. The records shall be
sufficient to substantiate the accuracy of the claim and shall be in such form
and contain such information as the department may require. Failure of the
claimant to maintain such records or to accede to the demand for such
examination constitutes a waiver of all rights to the refund claimed on account
of the transaction questioned. [Amended by 1959 c.186 s4]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-320">
          <num>319.320</num>
          <heading>Refund of tax on fuel used in operation of vehicles over certain roads or private property</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-320__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Upon compliance with subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-320__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>or</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-320__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section the Department
of Transportation shall refund, in the manner provided in subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-320__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>or</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-320__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section, the tax on motor vehicle fuel that is used in the operation of
a motor vehicle:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="319-320__subsec_3__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>By any person on any road, thoroughfare or property in private ownership.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-320__subsec_3__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>By any person on any road, thoroughfare or property, other than a state
highway, county road or city street, for the removal of forest products, as
defined in ORS 321.005, or the products of such forest products converted to a
form other than logs at or near the harvesting site, or for the construction or
maintenance of the road, thoroughfare or property, pursuant to a written
agreement or permit authorizing the use, construction or maintenance of the
road, thoroughfare or property, with or by:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="319-320__subsec_3__subsec_b__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>An agency of the United States;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="319-320__subsec_3__subsec_b__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The State Board of Forestry;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="319-320__subsec_3__subsec_b__subsec_C">
                <num>(C)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The State Forester; or</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="319-320__subsec_3__subsec_b__subsec_D">
                <num>(D)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>A licensee of an agency named in subparagraph</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="319-320__subsec_3__subsec_b__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>,</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="319-320__subsec_3__subsec_b__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>or</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="319-320__subsec_3__subsec_b__subsec_C">
                <num>(C)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>of this
paragraph.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-320__subsec_3__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>By an agency of the United States or of this state or of any county, city or
port of this state on any road, thoroughfare or property, other than a state
highway, county road or city street.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-320__subsec_3__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>By any person on any county road for the removal of forest products, as defined
in ORS 321.005, or the products of such forest products converted to a form
other than logs at or near the harvesting site, if:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="319-320__subsec_3__subsec_d__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The use of the county road is pursuant to a written agreement entered into
with, or to a permit issued by, the State Board of Forestry, the State Forester
or an agency of the United States, authorizing such person to use such road and
requiring such person to pay for or to perform the construction or maintenance
of the county road;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="319-320__subsec_3__subsec_d__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The board, officer or agency that entered into the agreement or granted the
permit, by contract with the county court or board of county commissioners, has
assumed the responsibility for the construction or maintenance of such county
road; and</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="319-320__subsec_3__subsec_d__subsec_C">
                <num>(C)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Copies of the agreements or permits required by subparagraphs</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="319-320__subsec_3__subsec_d__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>and</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="319-320__subsec_3__subsec_d__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>of
this paragraph are filed with the department.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-320__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Except for a farmer subject to subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-320__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section, the person or
agency, as the case may be, who has paid any tax on such motor vehicle fuels
levied or directed to be paid, as provided by ORS 319.010 to 319.430, is
entitled to claim a refund of the tax so paid on such fuels or for the
proportionate part of tax paid on fuels used in the operation of such vehicles,
when part of the operations are over such roads, thoroughfares or property. The
proportionate part shall be based upon the number of miles traveled by any such
vehicle over such roads, thoroughfares or property as compared to the total
number of miles traveled by such vehicle. To be eligible to claim such refund
the person or agency, as the case may be, shall first establish and maintain a
complete record of the operations, miles traveled, gallons of fuel used and
other information, in such form and in such detail as the department may
prescribe and require, the source of supply of all fuels purchased or used, and
the particular vehicles or equipment in which used. Whenever any such claim is
received and approved by the department, it shall cause the refund of tax to be
paid to the claimant in like manner as provided for paying of other refund
claims.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-320__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A farmer who has paid any tax on motor vehicle fuels levied or directed to be
paid, as provided in ORS 319.010 to 319.430, is entitled to claim a refund of
the tax paid on such fuels used in farming operations in the operation of any
motor vehicle on any road, thoroughfare or property in private ownership. To be
eligible to claim such refund a farmer shall maintain in such form and in such
detail as the department may prescribe and require, a record, supported by
purchase invoices, of all such motor vehicle fuel purchased (including fuel
purchased to operate any motor vehicle on the highway) and, for each and every
motor vehicle operated on the highway, a record of all fuel used and of all
miles traveled on the highway. Whenever any such claim is received and approved
by the department, it shall cause the refund of tax to be paid to the claimant
in like manner as provided for paying of other refund claims.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-320__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>As used in subsections</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-320__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-320__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section, “farmer” includes any
person who manages or conducts a farm for the production of livestock or crops
but does not include a person who manages or conducts a farm for the production
of forest products, as defined in ORS 321.005, or the products of such forest
products converted to a form other than logs at or near the harvesting site, or
of forest trees unless the production of such forest products or forest trees
is only incidental to the primary purpose of the farming operation. [Amended by
1961 c.368 s1; 1965 c.64 s1; 1965 c.425 s2; 1967 c.367 s2; 1979 c.344 s6]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-330">
          <num>319.330</num>
          <heading>Refunds to purchasers of fuel for aircraft</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-330__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Whenever any statement and
invoices are presented to the Department of Transportation showing that motor
vehicle fuel or aircraft fuel has been purchased and used in operating aircraft
engines and upon which the full tax for motor vehicle fuel has been paid, the
department shall refund the tax paid, but only after deducting from the tax
paid 11 cents for each gallon of such fuel so purchased and used, except that
when such fuel is used in operating aircraft turbine engines (turbo-prop or
jet) the deduction shall be three cents for each gallon. No deduction provided
under this subsection shall be made on claims presented by the United States or
on claims presented where a satisfactory showing has been made to the
department that such aircraft fuel has been used solely in aircraft operations
from a point within the State of Oregon directly to a point not within any state
of the United States. The amount so deducted shall be paid on warrant of the
Oregon Department of Administrative Services to the State Treasurer, who shall
credit the amount to the State Aviation Account for the purpose of carrying out
the provisions of the state aviation law. Moneys credited to the account under
this section are continuously appropriated to the Oregon Department of
Aviation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-330__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If satisfactory evidence is presented to the Department of Transportation
showing that aircraft fuel upon which the tax has been paid has been purchased
and used solely in aircraft operations from a point within the State of Oregon
directly to a point not within any state of the United States, the department
shall refund the tax paid. [Amended by 1959 c.505 s6; 1973 c.575 s1; 1977 c.293
s2; 1999 c.935 s26; 1999 c.1037 ss2,4; 2005 c.755 s16; 2015 c.700 ss2,5; 2021
c.526 s2]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-370">
          <num>319.370</num>
          <heading>Examinations and investigations; correcting reports and payments</heading>
          <content>
            <p>The Department of
Transportation, or its duly authorized agents, may make any examination of the
accounts, records, stocks, facilities and equipment of dealers, brokers,
service stations and other persons engaged in storing, selling or distributing
motor vehicle fuel or other petroleum product or products within this state,
and such other investigations as it considers necessary in carrying out the
provisions of ORS 319.010 to 319.430. If the examinations or investigations
disclose that any reports of dealers or other persons theretofore filed with
the department pursuant to the requirements of ORS 319.010 to 319.430, have
shown incorrectly the amount of gallonage of motor vehicle fuel distributed or
the tax, penalty or interest accruing thereon, the department may make such
changes in subsequent reports and payments of such dealers or other persons, or
may make such refunds, as may be necessary to correct the errors disclosed by
its examinations or investigations. [Amended by 1987 c.610 s14]</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-375">
          <num>319.375</num>
          <heading>Limitation on credit for or refund of overpayment and on assessment of additional tax</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-375__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Except as otherwise provided in ORS 319.010 to 319.430, any credit for
erroneous overpayment of tax made by a dealer taken on a subsequent return or
any claim for refund of tax erroneously overpaid filed by a dealer must be so
taken or filed within three years after the date on which the overpayment was
made to the state.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-375__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Except in the case of a fraudulent report or neglect to make a report, every
notice of additional tax proposed to be assessed under ORS 319.010 to 319.430
shall be served on dealers within three years from the date upon which such
additional taxes become due.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-380">
          <num>319.380</num>
          <heading>Examining books and accounts of carrier of motor vehicle fuel</heading>
          <content>
            <p>The Department of
Transportation or its duly authorized agents may at any time during normal
business hours examine the books and accounts of any carrier of motor vehicle
fuel operating within this state for the purpose of checking shipments or use
of motor vehicle fuel, detecting diversions thereof or evasion of taxes on same
in enforcing the provisions of ORS 319.010 to 319.430.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-382">
          <num>319.382</num>
          <heading>Agreements for refunds to Indian tribes</heading>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding any other provision of
law, the Department of Transportation may enter into agreements with the
governing body of any Indian tribe residing on a reservation in Oregon to
provide refunds to the tribe of state motor vehicle fuel taxes for fuel
purchased on the reservation and used by tribal members on tribal reservation
lands, other than for motor vehicle fuel used on state highways, county roads
or city streets supported by the State Highway Fund. [1993 c.706 s2]
Note: 319.382 was added
to and made a part of 319.010 to 319.430 by legislative action but was not
added to any smaller series therein. See Preface to Oregon Revised Statutes for
further explanation.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-390">
          <num>319.390</num>
          <heading>Records to be kept by dealers; inspection of records</heading>
          <content>
            <p>Every dealer in
motor vehicle fuel shall keep a record in such form as may be prescribed by the
Department of Transportation of all purchases, receipts, sales and distribution
of motor fuel. The records shall include copies of all invoices or bills of all
such sales and shall at all times during the business hours of the day be
subject to inspection by the department or its deputies or other officers duly
authorized by the department. Upon request from the officials to whom is
entrusted the enforcement of the motor fuel tax law of another state,
territory, country or the federal government, the department shall forward to
such officials any information which it may have relative to the import or
export of any motor vehicle fuel by any dealer, provided such other state,
territory, country or federal government furnishes like information to this
state. [Amended by 1955 c.730 s11; 1987 c.610 s16]</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-400">
          <num>319.400</num>
          <heading>Records to be kept three years</heading>
          <content>
            <p>Every dealer shall maintain and keep,
within the State of Oregon, for a period of three years, all records of motor
vehicle fuel used, sold and distributed within this state by such dealer,
together with stock records, invoices, bills of lading and other pertinent
papers as may be required by the Department of Transportation. [Amended by 1955
c.730 s12; 1987 c.610 s17]</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-410">
          <num>319.410</num>
          <heading>Disposition of tax moneys</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-410__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Department of Transportation shall promptly
turn over the license tax to the State Treasurer to be disposed of as provided
in ORS 802.110.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-410__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The revenue from the license tax collected from the use, sale or distribution
of aircraft fuel as imposed by ORS 319.020</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-410__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>shall be transferred upon
certification of the department to the State Treasurer, who shall credit the
certified amount to the State Aviation Account for the purpose of carrying out
the provisions of the state aviation laws. [Amended by 1955 c.287 s20; 1961
c.146 s2; 1963 c.226 s3; 1969 c.70 s1; 1983 c.338 s909; 1993 c.741 s29; 1999
c.935 s27; 2005 c.755 s17]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-415">
          <num>319.415</num>
          <heading>Estimate of tax on fuel used for boats; transfer to specified funds and accounts; use</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-415__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>On or before July 15 of each year, the Oregon Department of Administrative
Services, after consultation with the Department of Transportation and the
State Marine Board, shall determine the amount of the motor vehicle fuel tax
imposed under ORS 319.010 to 319.430 during the preceding fiscal year with
respect to fuel purchased and used to operate or propel motor boats. The amount
determined shall be reduced by the amount of any refunds for motor boats used
for commercial purposes actually paid during the preceding year on account of
ORS 319.280</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-415__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <paragraph eId="319-415__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-415__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <paragraph eId="319-415__subsec_2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Oregon Department of Administrative Services shall estimate the amount of
fuel described in subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-415__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section that is used to operate or
propel motor boats by conducting a statistically valid, unbiased, independent
survey of boat owners. The survey shall be conducted once every four years and
shall be designed to estimate the average daily fuel consumption by motor boats
and the total days of motor boat use per year. The survey shall be used to
determine the amount of the transfer required by subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-415__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section
for the first transfer that occurs after the survey is completed. If the tax
rate changes during the fiscal year, the amount of tax to be transferred shall
be prorated based on the percentage of total motor boat use taking place during
each tax period.</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="319-415__subsec_3__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In years when no survey is conducted, the amount to be transferred under
subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-415__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section shall be calculated by multiplying the per boat
fuel consumption factors from the preceding survey by the number of motor boats
as shown by the annual actual count of boat registrations. The resulting
amount, in gallons per year, shall be the basis for the determination of the
amount to be transferred.</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="319-415__subsec_3__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The survey required by paragraph</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-415__subsec_3__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this subsection shall be developed by a
research department within Oregon State University, in consultation with the
State Marine Board and the Department of Transportation. The Oregon Department
of Administrative Services shall contract for the development and conduct of
the survey, and the costs shall be paid by the Department of Transportation.
Costs paid by the Department of Transportation may be deducted from the amount
transferred to the State Marine Board and to the Oregon Business Development
Department under subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-415__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-415__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Oregon Department of Administrative Services shall certify the amount of
the estimate made under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-415__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section, as reduced by refunds,
to the Department of Transportation, to the State Marine Board, to the Oregon
Business Development Department and to the State Treasurer. Thereupon, that
amount shall be transferred from the Department of Transportation Driver and
Motor Vehicle Suspense Account to the:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="319-415__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Boating Safety, Law Enforcement and Facility Account created under ORS 830.140,
and is continuously appropriated to the State Marine Board for the purposes for
which the moneys in the Boating Safety, Law Enforcement and Facility Account
are appropriated; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-415__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Marine Navigation Improvement Fund established under ORS 777.267, and is
continuously appropriated to the Oregon Business Development Department for the
Oregon Infrastructure Finance Authority for the purposes of paying for portions
of the cost of maintenance dredging projects undertaken with equipment owned by
the State of Oregon at publicly owned ports and marinas.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-415__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Of the amounts transferred under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-415__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section, two cents per
gallon of fuel shall first be transferred to the Marine Navigation Improvement
Fund and the remaining amounts shall be transferred to the Boating Safety, Law
Enforcement and Facility Account.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-417">
          <num>319.417</num>
          <heading>Estimate of tax on fuel used in aircraft; transfer to State Aviation Account; use</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-417__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>On or after October 3, 1989, and on or before July 15 of each year
thereafter, the Oregon Department of Administrative Services, after
consultation with the Department of Transportation and the Director of the
Oregon Department of Aviation shall estimate, using a methodology approved by
the Oregon Transportation Commission, the amount of the motor vehicle fuel tax
imposed under ORS 319.010 to 319.430 during the preceding fiscal year with
respect to motor vehicle fuel purchased and used in operating aircraft engines
and upon which the full tax for motor vehicle fuel has been paid. The estimate
shall be reduced by the amount of any refunds actually paid on motor vehicle
fuel, excluding those paid on aviation gasoline or jet fuel, during the
preceding fiscal year pursuant to ORS 319.330</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-417__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-417__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Oregon Department of Administrative Services shall certify the amount of
the estimate made under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-417__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section to the Department of
Transportation, the Director of the Oregon Department of Aviation and the State
Treasurer. Thereupon, the amount of the estimate shall be transferred from the
Department of Transportation Driver and Motor Vehicle Suspense Account to the
State Aviation Account and is continuously appropriated to the Oregon
Department of Aviation to carry out the purposes of ORS chapters 835, 836 and
837.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-420">
          <num>319.420</num>
          <heading>ORS 319.510 to 319.880 not affected</heading>
          <content>
            <p>ORS 319.010 to 319.410 do not affect or
repeal any of the provisions of ORS 319.510 to 319.880.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-430">
          <num>319.430</num>
          <heading>Savings clause</heading>
          <content>
            <p>All rights and obligations arising under the provisions of the statutes
repealed in section 38, chapter 413, Oregon Laws 1945, shall not in any way be
affected by such repeal. Such statutes shall be considered in full force and
effect for the purpose of carrying out all duties and obligations contracted or
arising under such statutes, prior to June 16, 1945.
USE
FUEL TAX</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-510">
          <num>319.510</num>
          <heading>Short title</heading>
          <content>
            <p>ORS 319.510 to 319.880 may be cited as the Use Fuel Tax Law. [Amended by 2007
c.71 s93]</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-520">
          <num>319.520</num>
          <heading>Definitions for ORS 319.510 to 319.880</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-520__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Cardlock card” means a fuel card:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="319-520__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Capable of generating an electronic invoice or electronic statement that
includes the information required by ORS 319.671 and the applicable fuel tax
amount;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-520__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Issued for a specific vehicle, a specific piece of equipment or a group of
equipment;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-520__subsec_1__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>That includes the qualifying information, as designated by the Department of
Transportation by rule, that is printed on the electronic invoice or electronic
statement;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-520__subsec_1__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>That allows the tax status of the cardlock card to be indicated on the
electronic invoice or electronic statement and includes state tax as a separate
item on the invoice or statement; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-520__subsec_1__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>That allows a cardlock card issuer to generate a statement recording, by fuel
type, gallons of fuel purchased for domestic and foreign customers each month.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-520__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Combined weight” means the total empty weight of all vehicles in a combination
plus the total weight of the load carried on that combination of vehicles.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-520__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Delinquent” means having failed to pay a tax or penalty within the time
provided by law.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-520__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Department” means the Department of Transportation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-520__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Domestic customer” means a customer making a purchase at a nonretail facility
owned by the cardlock card issuer.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-520__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Foreign customer” means a customer making a purchase at a nonretail facility
owned by a seller other than the cardlock card issuer.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-520__subsec_7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Fuel” means any combustible gas, liquid or material of a kind used for the
generation of power to propel a motor vehicle on the highways except motor vehicle
fuel as defined in ORS 319.010.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-520__subsec_8">
            <num>(8)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Highway” means every way, thoroughfare and place, of whatever nature, open to
the use of the public for the purpose of vehicular travel.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-520__subsec_9">
            <num>(9)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Light weight” means the weight of a vehicle when fully equipped for moving
over the highway.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-520__subsec_10">
            <num>(10)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Liquefied petroleum gas” includes propane, pentane and any mixture of propane
and pentane.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-520__subsec_11">
            <num>(11)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Motor vehicle” means every self-propelled vehicle operated on the highway,
except an implement of husbandry used in agricultural operations and only
incidentally operated or moved upon the highway.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-520__subsec_12">
            <num>(12)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Nonretail facility” means:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="319-520__subsec_12__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An unattended facility accessible only by cardlock card and not associated with
a retail facility; or</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-520__subsec_12__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An unattended portion of a retail facility separate from the retail operations
and accessible only by cardlock card.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-520__subsec_13">
            <num>(13)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Person” means any individual, firm, copartnership, joint venture, association,
corporation, trust, receiver or any group or combination acting as a unit.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-520__subsec_14">
            <num>(14)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Seller” means:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="319-520__subsec_14__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person that sells fuel to a user; or</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-520__subsec_14__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the fuel is dispensed at a nonretail facility, the person that owns the user’s
accounts and bills the user for fuel purchased at a nonretail facility.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-520__subsec_15">
            <num>(15)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“To sell fuel for use in a motor vehicle” means to dispense or place fuel for a
price into a receptacle on a motor vehicle, from which receptacle the fuel is
supplied to propel the motor vehicle.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-520__subsec_16">
            <num>(16)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“To use fuel in a motor vehicle” means to receive into any receptacle on a
motor vehicle, fuel to be consumed in propelling the motor vehicle on the
highways of this state; and, if the fuel is received into the receptacle
outside the taxing jurisdiction of the state, “to use fuel in a motor vehicle”
means to consume in propelling the motor vehicle on the highways of this state.
[Amended by 1955 c.287 s21; 1959 c.188 s1; 1977 c.429 s1; 1981 c.703 s1; 1989
c.992 s24a; 1991 c.284 s5; 1993 c.741 s32; 2003 c.99 s1; 2008 c.44 s1; 2023
c.400 s4]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-525">
          <num>319.525</num>
          <heading>Agreements with Indian tribes</heading>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding any other provision of
law, the Department of Transportation may enter into agreements with the
governing body of any Indian tribe residing on a reservation in Oregon to
provide for the administration of the tax imposed under ORS 319.510 to 319.880.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-530">
          <num>319.530</num>
          <heading>Imposition of tax; rate; fuel unit equivalents</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-530__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>To compensate
this state partially for the use of its highways, an excise tax hereby is
imposed at the rate of 34 cents per gallon on the use of fuel in a motor
vehicle.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-530__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Except as otherwise provided in subsections</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-530__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>to</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-530__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section, 100
cubic feet of fuel used or sold in a gaseous state, measured at 14.73 pounds
per square inch of pressure at 60 degrees Fahrenheit, is taxable at the same
rate as a gallon of liquid fuel.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-530__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>123.57 cubic feet, or 5.66 pounds, of compressed natural gas used or sold in a
gaseous state is taxable at the same rate as one gasoline gallon.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-530__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>1.353 gallons, or 5.75 pounds, of liquefied petroleum gas is taxable at the
same rate as one gasoline gallon.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-530__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>1.71 gallons, or 6.059 pounds, of liquefied natural gas is taxable at the same
rate as one diesel gallon.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-530__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>One kilogram of hydrogen is taxable at the same rate as one gasoline gallon. [Amended
by 1959 c.188 s2; 1967 c.463 s2; 1981 c.698 s2; 1981 c.703 s2; 1983 c.727 ss2,6;
1985 c.209 s13; 1987 c.899 ss9,11,15; 1989 c.865 s2; 1991 c.497 ss8,9; 1995
c.311 s1; 2009 c.865 s49; 2013 c.648 ss1,3; 2017 c.750 ss42,43; 2023 c.400 s5]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-535">
          <num>319.535</num>
          <heading>Special use fuel license fee; application; emblem</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-535__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In lieu of
paying the per-gallon tax on the use of fuel in a motor vehicle imposed under
ORS 319.530, a person may pay to the Department of Transportation annually, for
each motor vehicle that consumes natural gas or propane, a special use fuel
license fee computed under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-535__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section based on the
following schedule:
______________________________________________________________________________
COMBINED
WEIGHT BASE
(Pounds)
0 - 10,000 $60
10,001 -
26,000 $300
26,001 and
above $400
______________________________________________________________________________</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-535__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The special use fuel license fee equals the applicable base amount from the
schedule in subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-535__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section multiplied by the use fuel tax rate
imposed under ORS 319.530 in effect at the time of payment, divided by 12
cents.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-535__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <paragraph eId="319-535__subsec_3__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person wishing to pay the special use fuel license fee shall apply to the
department on a form prescribed by the department and shall include such
information as the department requires.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-535__subsec_3__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon receipt of a complete and valid application under this subsection, the
department shall issue to the applicant without charge an emblem for display on
the motor vehicle to which the application relates.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-535__subsec_3__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An emblem issued under this section that is displayed in a conspicuous place on
the motor vehicle for which the emblem is issued shall be accepted by a seller
of fuel as proof of exemption from the per-gallon tax imposed under ORS
319.530.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-550">
          <num>319.550</num>
          <heading>User’s license required to use fuel; exceptions</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-550__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Except as
provided in this section, a person may not use fuel in a motor vehicle in this
state unless the person holds a valid user’s license.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-550__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A nonresident may use fuel in a motor vehicle not registered in Oregon for a
period not exceeding 30 consecutive days without obtaining a user’s license or
the emblem issued under ORS 319.600, if, for all fuel used in a motor vehicle
in this state, the nonresident pays to a seller, at the time of the sale, the
tax provided in ORS 319.530.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-550__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A user’s license is not required for a person who uses fuel in a motor vehicle
if, for all fuel used in a motor vehicle in this state, the person pays to a
seller, at the time of the sale, the tax provided in ORS 319.530.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-550__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A user’s license is not required for a person who is subject to the weight-mile
tax described in ORS 825.474 and 825.476 or the flat fee rate described in ORS
825.480.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-550__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <paragraph eId="319-550__subsec_5__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A user’s license is not required for a person who uses fuel as described in ORS
319.520</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-550__subsec_7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>in the vehicles specified in this subsection if the person pays to
a seller, at the time of the sale, the tax provided in ORS 319.530.</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="319-550__subsec_7__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Paragraph</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-550__subsec_7__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this subsection applies to the following vehicles:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="319-550__subsec_7__subsec_a__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Motor homes as defined in ORS 801.350.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="319-550__subsec_7__subsec_a__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Recreational vehicles as defined in ORS 174.101.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-550__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A user’s license is not required for a person who uses fuel in a motor vehicle:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="319-550__subsec_6__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Metered use by which is subject to the per-mile road usage charge imposed under
ORS 319.885; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-550__subsec_6__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>That also uses fuels subject to ORS 319.510 to 319.880.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-550__subsec_7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A user’s license is not required for a person who uses fuel in a motor vehicle
on which an emblem issued for the motor vehicle pursuant to ORS 319.535 is
displayed. [Amended by 1959 c.188 s3; 1977 c.429 s2; 1985 c.265 s1; 1989 c.992 s25;
1991 c.284 s8; 2008 c.44 s3; 2013 c.781 s16; 2014 c.13 ss3,4; 2019 c.422 s31;
2023 c.400 s3]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-560">
          <num>319.560</num>
          <heading>Application for and issuance of user’s license</heading>
          <content>
            <p>A user of fuel in
a motor vehicle required to be licensed under ORS 319.550 shall apply to the
Department of Transportation for a user’s license upon forms prescribed by the
department and shall set forth such information as the department may require.
On receipt of the application, the department may issue to the applicant a user’s
license without charge authorizing the applicant to use fuel in a motor vehicle
in this state. The license is valid only for the person in whose name it is
issued and is valid until canceled or revoked. [Amended by 1959 c.188 s4; 1977
c.429 s3; 1999 c.769 s21]</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-570">
          <num>319.570</num>
          <heading>Faithful performance bond</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-570__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>At the time of filing the application for a user’s
license, the Department of Transportation may require the user of fuel in a motor
vehicle to file with the department, in such form as shall be prepared by the
department, a bond duly executed by the user as principal with a corporate
surety authorized to transact business in this state. The bond shall be payable
to the State of Oregon conditioned upon faithful performance of all the
requirements of ORS 319.510 to 319.880, including the payment of all taxes,
penalties and other obligations of such user arising out of ORS 319.510 to
319.880 and 319.990</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-570__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-570__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The total amount of the bond or bonds required of any user of fuel in a motor
vehicle shall be fixed by the department and may be increased or reduced by the
department at any time subject to the limitations provided in this section. The
total amount of the bond or bonds required of any user of fuel in a motor
vehicle shall be equivalent to twice the estimated monthly tax of the user,
determined in such manner as the department considers proper. However, the
total amount of the bond or bonds required of any user of fuel in a motor
vehicle shall never be less than $10. Any bond given in connection with ORS
319.510 to 319.880 shall be a continuing instrument and shall cover any and all
periods of time including the first and all subsequent periods for which a
license may be granted in consequence of the giving of the bond. The liability
of the surety on the bond for the aggregate of all claims which arise
thereunder shall not exceed the amount of the penalty of the bond. No recovery
on any bond or any execution of any new bond shall invalidate any bond, but the
total recoveries under any one bond shall not exceed the amount of the bond. [Amended
by 1959 c.188 s5; 1967 c.359 s692]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-580">
          <num>319.580</num>
          <heading>Deposit in lieu of bond</heading>
          <content>
            <p>In lieu of any bond or bonds in total amount as fixed
under ORS 319.570, any user may deposit with the Department of Transportation,
under such terms and conditions as the department may prescribe, a like amount
of lawful money of the United States or negotiable bonds or other obligations
of the United States, the State of Oregon, or any county of this state, of an
actual market value not less than the amount so fixed by the department. The
department shall turn over to the State Treasurer for safekeeping all such
deposits so received.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-590">
          <num>319.590</num>
          <heading>Release of surety</heading>
          <content>
            <p>Any surety on a bond furnished by a user as provided in ORS 319.570 shall be
released and discharged from any and all liability to the state accruing on the
bond after the expiration of 60 days from the date upon which the surety has
lodged with the Department of Transportation a written request to be released
and discharged, but this provision shall not operate to relieve, release or
discharge the surety from any liability already accrued or which accrues before
the expiration of the 60-day period. The department shall promptly, upon
receiving the request, notify the user who furnished the bond, and unless the
user, on or before the expiration of the 60-day period files a new bond, or
makes a deposit in accordance with the requirements of ORS 319.580, the
department forthwith shall cancel the user’s license.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-600">
          <num>319.600</num>
          <heading>Display of emblem</heading>
          <content>
            <p>Except as provided in ORS 319.550, a user of fuel in a motor vehicle shall
display an emblem in a conspicuous place on each motor vehicle in connection
with which fuel is used. Each such emblem shall be issued without charge by the
Department of Transportation upon application by a person holding an uncanceled
or unrevoked user’s license and shall be displayed only upon the motor vehicle
with respect to which it is issued. [Amended by 1959 c.188 s6]</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-611">
          <num>319.611</num>
          <heading>Penalty for unlicensed use of fuel or nondisplay of authorization or emblem; waiver</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-611__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any person required to be licensed under ORS 319.550 uses fuel in a
motor vehicle in this state at a time when the person does not hold a valid
user’s license or does not display a valid authorization or user’s emblem
issued by the Department of Transportation, a penalty of 25 percent of the tax
applicable to the fuel so used shall be imposed. The penalty so imposed shall
be in addition to any other penalty imposed under the provisions of ORS 319.510
to 319.990.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-611__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department may waive any penalty provided by subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-611__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section
that is imposed after January 1, 1998, if the department determines that there
was reasonable cause for the failure to hold a valid user’s license or display
a valid authorization or user’s emblem issued by the department and finds that
there was no intent to avoid payment.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-621">
          <num>319.621</num>
          <heading>Seller’s license</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-621__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No person shall sell fuel for use in a motor vehicle in this state unless
the person holds a valid seller’s license.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-621__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A person shall apply to the Department of Transportation for a seller’s license
upon forms prescribed, prepared and furnished by the department. No charge
shall be made for the license. The license is valid only for the person in
whose name it is issued and is valid until canceled or revoked.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-621__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department may require an applicant for a seller’s license to file with the
department a bond or deposit of not less than $100 under the same terms and
conditions prescribed for users in ORS 319.570, 319.580 and 319.590. [Formerly
319.670]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-628">
          <num>319.628</num>
          <heading>Grounds for refusal to issue user’s or seller’s license; hearing; records inspection</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-628__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Department of Transportation may refuse to issue a user’s license or a
seller’s license to a person who applies as provided in ORS 319.560 or 319.621
if the department finds that the person:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="319-628__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Was the holder of a license revoked under ORS 319.630;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-628__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Is applying for a license on behalf of a real party in interest whose license
was revoked under ORS 319.630;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-628__subsec_1__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Was an officer, director, owner or managing employee of a nonindividual
licensee whose license was revoked under ORS 319.630;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-628__subsec_1__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Owes a debt to the state under ORS 319.510 to 319.880;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-628__subsec_1__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Had a license issued by a jurisdiction other than Oregon to sell or use untaxed
use fuel that was revoked or canceled for cause, whether the license was held
by the person as an individual or as an officer, director, owner or managing
employee or on behalf of a real party in interest;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-628__subsec_1__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In any jurisdiction, pleaded guilty to or was convicted of a crime directly
related to the sale, use or distribution of use fuel, whether as an individual
or as an officer, director, owner or managing employee of a business engaged in
the sale or distribution of use fuel;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-628__subsec_1__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Had a civil judgment imposed for conduct involving fraud, misrepresentation,
conversion or dishonesty, as an individual or as an officer, director, owner or
managing employee of a business engaged in the sale or distribution of use
fuel;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-628__subsec_1__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Misrepresented or concealed a material fact in obtaining a license or in the
reinstatement thereof;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-628__subsec_1__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Violated a statute or administrative rule regarding fuel taxation or
distribution;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-628__subsec_1__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Failed to cooperate with the department’s investigations by:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="319-628__subsec_1__subsec_j__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Not furnishing requested documents;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="319-628__subsec_1__subsec_j__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Not furnishing when requested to do so a full and complete written explanation
of a matter under investigation by the department; or</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="319-628__subsec_1__subsec_j__subsec_C">
                <num>(C)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Not responding to a subpoena issued by the department; or</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-628__subsec_1__subsec_k">
              <num>(k)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Failed to comply with an order issued by the department.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-628__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In addition to refusal of a license for reasons specified in subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-628__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of
this section, the department may refuse to issue a user’s license or seller’s license
for any other reason the department deems sufficient.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-628__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Before refusing to issue a license under this section, the department shall
grant the applicant a hearing and shall give the applicant at least 10 days’
written notice of the time and place of the hearing. The hearing shall be a
contested case hearing under the provisions of ORS chapter 183.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-628__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For purpose of consideration of an application for a license, the department
may inspect or investigate the records of this state or of any other jurisdiction
to verify the information on the application and to verify the applicant’s
criminal and licensing history.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-630">
          <num>319.630</num>
          <heading>Revocation of license; reissue of license</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-630__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Department of
Transportation may revoke the license of a user or seller if the user or seller
fails to comply with any provision of ORS 319.510 to 319.880 or any rule or
regulation adopted under ORS 319.510 to 319.880. Before revoking the license
the department shall serve written notice on the person ordering the person to
appear before the department at a time not less than 10 days after such service
and show cause why the license should not be revoked. The notice shall be
served in the manner prescribed by ORS 319.760</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-630__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-630__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A new license shall not be issued to a person whose license has been revoked
unless it appears to the satisfaction of the department that the person will
comply with the provisions of ORS 319.510 to 319.880 and the rules and
regulations adopted under ORS 319.510 to 319.880. [Amended by 1959 c.188 s10]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-640">
          <num>319.640</num>
          <heading>Cancellation of license on request of user</heading>
          <content>
            <p>If any person to whom a license
has been issued pursuant to ORS 319.550 to 319.600 ceases using fuel within
this state for a period of six months, the person shall immediately request in
writing that the Department of Transportation cancel the license. On receipt of
the request the department shall cancel the license.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-650">
          <num>319.650</num>
          <heading>Notifying department upon ceasing to use fuel in connection with motor vehicle</heading>
          <content>
            <p>If any person
ceases using fuel within this state in connection with a motor vehicle with
respect to which an emblem has been issued pursuant to ORS 319.600 but
continues using fuel within this state in connection with another motor vehicle
or other motor vehicles, the person shall immediately notify the Department of
Transportation.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-660">
          <num>319.660</num>
          <heading>Removal of emblem</heading>
          <content>
            <p>Any person whose license has been revoked or canceled pursuant to ORS 319.630
or 319.640, or who is required by ORS 319.650 to notify the Department of
Transportation that such person has ceased using fuel within this state in
connection with a motor vehicle, immediately shall remove from the motor
vehicle on which it is displayed and shall destroy or, if the department so
requests, shall return to the department each emblem issued to such person
under ORS 319.600 or the emblem issued with respect to the motor vehicle in
connection with which such person has ceased using fuel within this state, as
the case may be.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-665">
          <num>319.665</num>
          <heading>Seller to collect tax; exceptions; deduction for purchase made with cardlock card</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-665__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The seller of fuel for use in a motor vehicle shall collect the tax
provided by ORS 319.530 at the time the fuel is sold, unless one of the
following situations applies:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="319-665__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Transportation has issued for the vehicle into which the
seller delivers or places the fuel a weight identifier under ORS 825.450 or a
valid user’s emblem under ORS 319.600.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-665__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The fuel is dispensed at a nonretail facility, in which case the seller shall
collect any tax owed at the same time the seller collects the purchase price
from the person to whom the fuel was dispensed at the nonretail facility. A
seller is not required to collect the tax under this paragraph from a person
who certifies to the seller that the use of the fuel is exempt from the tax
imposed under ORS 319.530.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-665__subsec_1__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A cardlock card is used for purchase of the fuel at an attended portion of a
retail facility equipped with a cardlock card reader, in which case the
cardlock card issuer licensed in this state is responsible for collecting and
remitting the tax unless the person making the purchase certifies to the seller
that the use of the fuel is exempt from the tax imposed under ORS 319.530.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-665__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If a cardlock card is used for purchase of fuel at an attended portion of a
retail facility equipped with a cardlock card reader, the seller at the retail
facility may deduct fuel purchases made with a cardlock card from the seller’s
retail transactions if the seller provides the department with the following
information:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="319-665__subsec_2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A monthly statement from a cardlock card issuer that details the cardlock card
purchases at the retail facility; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-665__subsec_2__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A listing of cardlock card issuers and gallons of fuel purchased at the retail
facility by the issuers’ customers.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-665__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department shall supply each seller of fuel for use in a motor vehicle with
a chart which sets forth the tax imposed on given quantities of fuel.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-671">
          <num>319.671</num>
          <heading>When invoices required; contents</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-671__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The seller of fuel for any purpose
shall make a duplicate invoice for every sale of fuel for any purpose and shall
retain one copy and give the other copy to the user. The Department of
Transportation may prescribe the form of the invoice. The invoice shall show:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="319-671__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The seller’s name and address;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-671__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The date;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-671__subsec_1__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The amount of the sale in gallons; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-671__subsec_1__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The name and address of the user.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-671__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In addition to the invoice entries listed in subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-671__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section,
the seller of fuel for use in a motor vehicle shall indicate on the invoice the
amount of the tax collected, if any, and:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="319-671__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The license plate number, if the vehicle bears a license plate issued by the
department or another jurisdiction;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-671__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The emblem number, if the vehicle bears a user’s emblem;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-671__subsec_1__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The temporary pass number, if the vehicle bears no valid user’s emblem; or</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-671__subsec_1__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The license plate number, if the vehicle bears no valid user’s emblem or
temporary pass number issued by the department.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-671__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-671__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section, this section does not require
any invoice to be prepared for any sale where fuel is delivered into the fuel
tank of a vehicle described in this subsection unless the operator of the
vehicle requests an invoice. If an invoice is prepared under this subsection,
the name and address of a user is not required to be shown on the invoice for
sales where the fuel is delivered into the fuel tanks of vehicles described in
this subsection. This subsection applies to vehicles:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="319-671__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>That have a combined weight of 26,000 pounds or less; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-671__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <subparagraph eId="319-671__subsec_1__subsec_b__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>For which the tax under ORS 319.530 must be paid at the time of sale under ORS
319.665; or</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="319-671__subsec_1__subsec_b__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>For which an emblem has been issued under ORS 319.535.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-675">
          <num>319.675</num>
          <heading>Seller’s report to department; rules</heading>
          <content>
            <p>Except as provided in ORS 319.692, the
seller of fuel for use in a motor vehicle shall report to the Department of
Transportation on or before the 20th day of each month, the amount of fuel
sold, during the preceding calendar month, subject to the tax imposed under ORS
319.530 or exempt from the tax imposed under ORS 319.530 pursuant to ORS
319.535 and such other information pertaining to fuel handled as the department
may require. The department may prescribe the form of the report. The seller
shall deliver the report to the department in the manner provided by the
department by rule.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-681">
          <num>319.681</num>
          <heading>Payment of tax by seller</heading>
          <content>
            <p>The seller of fuel for use in a motor vehicle shall
remit to the Department of Transportation with each report required by ORS
319.675 all the tax due on the amount of fuel sold less four percent, which the
seller shall retain.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-690">
          <num>319.690</num>
          <heading>Monthly report of user; remittance; credit against taxes; annual reports of certain users; rules</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-690__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Except as provided in subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-690__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section and ORS 319.692, each
user of fuel in a motor vehicle required to be licensed under ORS 319.550
shall, on or before the 20th day of each month, file with the Department of
Transportation a report showing the amount of fuel used during the immediately
preceding calendar month by the user and such other information as the
department may require for the purposes of ORS 319.510 to 319.880. The
department shall prescribe the form of the report. The user shall file the
report with the department in the manner provided by the department by rule.
Each report shall be accompanied by a remittance payable to the department for
the amount of all the tax shown by the report to be due and payable. Any tax
paid to a seller is a credit against the amount of tax otherwise due and
payable to the state under ORS 319.510 to 319.880 or 818.225, 825.474, 825.476
and 825.480. Also, when filing a monthly tax report, a user may, in lieu of
claiming a refund, take a deduction or credit for the tax on any fuel which
would otherwise be subject to refund under ORS 319.831</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-690__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-690__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Each user of fuel in a motor vehicle with a light weight of less than 8,000
pounds required to be licensed under ORS 319.550 may file an annual report of
all fuel used upon Oregon highways. The report for each calendar year shall be
filed on or before March 1 of the year following and shall be accompanied by a
remittance payable to the department of all the tax shown to be due and payable
on the amount of fuel used. [Amended by 1959 c.188 s16; 1963 c.226 s7; 1971
c.149 s2; 1977 c.429 s7; 2011 c.101 s4; 2015 c.77 s2]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-692">
          <num>319.692</num>
          <heading>Quarterly reports if average monthly tax under $300; when annual reports authorized</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-692__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Whenever in the judgment of the Department of Transportation the average
monthly tax to be paid by a use fuel seller or user will be less than $300, the
department may authorize the seller or user to file quarterly tax reports in
lieu of the monthly tax reports required by ORS 319.675 and 319.690. The
quarterly reports so authorized, and accompanying remittances as shown thereon
to be due and payable, shall be filed on or before the due dates as follows:
First quarter, April 20; second quarter, July 20; third quarter, October 20;
fourth quarter, January 20. Any provisions of ORS 319.675 and 319.690 otherwise
applicable to the filing of monthly reports and remittances shall be applicable
to the quarterly filings.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-692__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Whenever in the judgment of the department the average annual tax to be paid by
a use fuel seller or user will be less than $100, the department may authorize
the seller or user to file annual tax reports in lieu of the monthly tax
reports required by ORS 319.675 and 319.690. The annual reports authorized by
this subsection, and accompanying remittances as shown on the reports to be due
and payable, shall be filed on or before January 20 following the year for
which the reports are filed. Any provisions of ORS 319.675 and 319.690
otherwise applicable to the filing of monthly reports and remittances shall be
applicable to the annual filings.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-694">
          <num>319.694</num>
          <heading>Penalty for delinquency in remitting tax; waiver; interest rates</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-694__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Except as
provided in subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-694__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section, if any user or seller is delinquent
in remitting the tax provided by ORS 319.530 on the date specified in ORS
319.675, 319.681, 319.690 or 319.692, a penalty of 10 percent of the amount of
the tax due shall be added to the amount due and the total shall immediately be
due and payable.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-694__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the Department of Transportation determines that the delinquency was due to
reasonable cause and without any intent to avoid payment, the penalty provided
by subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-694__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section may be waived.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-694__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <paragraph eId="319-694__subsec_3__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the excise tax imposed by ORS 319.530 is not paid as required by ORS
319.675, 319.681, 319.690 or 319.692, interest shall be charged at the rate of
0.0329 percent per day until the tax and interest have been paid in full.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-694__subsec_3__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the excise tax imposed by ORS 319.530 is overpaid, the department may credit
interest to the account of the taxpayer in the amount of 0.0329 percent per day
up to a maximum amount that equals any interest assessed against the taxpayer
under paragraph</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-694__subsec_3__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this subsection in any given audit period.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-694__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No seller or user who incurs a tax liability as provided in ORS 319.510 to
319.880 shall knowingly and willfully fail to report and pay the tax liability
to the department as required by ORS 319.510 to 319.880.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-697">
          <num>319.697</num>
          <heading>Records required of sellers and users; alternative records for certain users</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-697__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every user of
fuel in a motor vehicle required to be licensed under ORS 319.550 shall keep a
record of fuel used and be prepared to prove that all the tax due and payable
on fuel used has been paid. An invoice, described in ORS 319.671, properly
filled out, is proof that any tax due which is shown on the invoice as paid was
paid for the fuel covered by the invoice. The user’s record of fuel used for
any purpose, other than fuel obtained from a seller who collected the tax,
shall indicate the date the fuel was obtained, the name and address of the
seller from whom the fuel was obtained, and the amount of fuel obtained, in
gallons.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-697__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In lieu of maintaining an actual record of fuel used, a user required to be
licensed under ORS 319.550 who operates a motor vehicle with a light weight of
less than 8,000 pounds may maintain an accurate record of miles operated upon
Oregon highways. The gallons of taxable fuel used shall be computed by applying
a reasonable miles per gallon figure to the Oregon miles operated. The Department
of Transportation shall determine whether the miles per gallon figure is
reasonable and its decision shall be final.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-697__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every seller of fuel for any purpose shall keep a record of fuel sold for any
purpose and shall be prepared to prove that all the tax provided by ORS 319.530
has been remitted to the department. The department may specify the form of the
seller’s record.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-697__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every seller, and every user of fuel in a motor vehicle required to be licensed
under ORS 319.550 shall preserve in this state for a period of three years all
records of fuel used or fuel sold, together with invoices and any other
relevant records or papers which may be specified by the department.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-697__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department or its authorized agent may examine every user’s or seller’s
records and papers required to be preserved by subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-697__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section
at any time during normal business hours.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-700">
          <num>319.700</num>
          <heading>Tax as lien against motor vehicle</heading>
          <content>
            <p>The tax and the penalty imposed upon a
user of fuel in a motor vehicle by ORS 319.510 to 319.880 shall constitute a
lien upon, and shall have the effect of an execution duly levied against, any
motor vehicle in connection with which the taxable use is made, attaching at
the time of such use. The lien shall not be removed until the tax has been paid
or the motor vehicle subject to the lien has been sold in payment of such tax.
The lien is paramount to all private liens or encumbrances of whatever character
upon the motor vehicle and to the rights of any conditional vendor or any other
holder of the legal title in or to the motor vehicle. [Amended by 1959 c.188 s23]</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-720">
          <num>319.720</num>
          <heading>Delinquency in payment; notice to debtors of user or seller; report to department</heading>
          <content>
            <p>If a user or seller is delinquent in the payment of any obligation imposed
under ORS 319.510 to 319.880, the Department of Transportation may give notice
of the amount of such delinquency by registered or certified mail to all
persons having in their possession or under their control any credits or other
personal property belonging to the user or seller, or owing any debts to such
user or seller, at the time of the receipt by them of the notice. Thereafter
any person so notified shall neither transfer nor make other disposition of
such credits, personal property or debts until the department has consented to
a transfer or other disposition or until 30 days have elapsed from and after
the receipt of the notice. All persons so notified shall, within five days
after the receipt of the notice, advise the department of all such credits,
personal property or debts in their possession, under their control or owing by
them, as the case may be. [Amended by 1959 c.188 s24]</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-730">
          <num>319.730</num>
          <heading>Collection of delinquent payment by seizure and sale of motor vehicle</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-730__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Whenever any
user is delinquent in the payment of any obligation imposed under ORS 319.510
to 319.880, the Department of Transportation may proceed to collect the amount
due from the user in the manner prescribed in this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-730__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department shall seize any motor vehicle subject to the lien provided for
by ORS 319.700 and thereafter sell it at public auction to pay such obligation
and any and all costs that may have been incurred on account of the seizure and
sale.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-730__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notice of the intended sale and the time and place thereof shall be given to
the delinquent user and to all persons appearing of record to have an interest
in the motor vehicle. The notice shall be given in writing at least 10 days
before the date set for the sale by enclosing it in an envelope addressed to
the user at the address as it appears in the records of the department and, in
the case of any person appearing of record to have an interest in the motor
vehicle, addressed to the person at the last-known residence or place of
business, and depositing the envelope in the United States mail, postage
prepaid. In addition, the notice shall be published at least three times, the
first of which shall be not less than 10 days before the date set for the sale,
in a newspaper of general circulation published in the county in which the
motor vehicle seized is to be sold. If there is no newspaper of general
circulation in the county, the notice shall be posted in three public places in
the county for such period of 10 days.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-730__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The notice shall contain a description of the motor vehicle to be sold,
together with a statement of the amount due under ORS 319.510 to 319.880, the
name of the user and the further statement that unless such amount is paid
before the time fixed in the notice the motor vehicle will be sold in
accordance with law and such notice.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-730__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department shall then proceed to sell the motor vehicle in accordance with
the law and the notice, and shall deliver to the purchaser a bill of sale which
shall vest title in the purchaser. If upon any such sale the moneys received
exceed the amount due to the state under ORS 319.510 to 319.880 from the
delinquent user, the excess shall be returned to the user and the receipt
obtained therefor. If any person having an interest in or lien upon the motor
vehicle has filed with the department prior to the sale notice of such interest
or lien, the department shall withhold payment of any such excess to the user
pending a determination of the rights of the respective parties thereto by a
court of competent jurisdiction. If for any reason the receipt of the user
shall not be available, the department shall deposit the excess with the State
Treasurer as trustee for the user or for the heirs, successors or assigns of
the user. [Amended by 1999 c.59 s79]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-740">
          <num>319.740</num>
          <heading>Action by Attorney General to collect delinquency; certificate of department as evidence</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-740__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Whenever any user or seller is delinquent in the payment of any obligation
under ORS 319.510 to 319.880, the Department of Transportation may transmit
notice of the delinquency to the Attorney General who shall at once proceed to
collect by appropriate legal action the tax and penalty due.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-740__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In any suit brought to enforce the rights of the state under ORS 319.510 to
319.880, a certificate by the department showing the delinquency is prima facie
evidence of the amount of the obligation, of the delinquency thereof and of
compliance by the department with all provisions of ORS 319.510 to 319.880
relating to the obligation. [Amended by 1959 c.188 s25]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-742">
          <num>319.742</num>
          <heading>Collection of delinquent obligation generally; warrant; judgment lien</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-742__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If a person
fails to pay in full any obligation due under ORS 319.510 to 319.880, the
Department of Transportation may issue a warrant for the amount of the
obligation and the cost of executing the warrant. A copy of the warrant shall
be mailed or delivered to the debtor by the department at the debtor’s
last-known address.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-742__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>At any time after issuing a warrant under this section, the department may
record the warrant in the County Clerk Lien Record of any county of this state.
Recording of the warrant has the effect described in ORS 205.125. After
recording a warrant, the department may direct the sheriff for the county in
which the warrant is recorded to levy upon and sell the real and personal
property of the debtor found within that county, and to levy upon any currency
of the debtor found within that county, for the application of the proceeds or
currency against the amount reflected in the warrant and the sheriff’s cost of
executing the warrant. The sheriff shall proceed on the warrant in the same
manner prescribed by law for executions issued against property pursuant to a
judgment, and is entitled to the same fees as provided for executions issued
against property pursuant to a judgment. The fees of the sheriff shall be added
to and collected as a part of the warrant liability.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-742__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the discretion of the department a warrant under this section may be
directed to any agent authorized by the department to collect obligations under
this section, and in the execution of the warrant the agent has all of the
powers conferred by law upon sheriffs, but is entitled to no fee or compensation
in excess of actual expenses paid in the performance of such duty.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-744">
          <num>319.744</num>
          <heading>Use of collection agency</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-744__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Department of Transportation may engage the
services of a collection agency to collect any obligation due to the state
under ORS 319.510 to 319.880. The department may engage the services by
entering into agreements to pay reasonable charges on a contingent fee or other
basis.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-744__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department may assign to the collection agency, for collection purposes
only, any of the obligations due the state under ORS 319.510 to 319.880.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-744__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The collection agency may bring such actions or take such proceedings,
including attachment and garnishment proceedings, as may be necessary.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-746">
          <num>319.746</num>
          <heading>Uncollectible obligation</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-746__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any obligation due the state assigned to a
collection agency pursuant to ORS 319.744 that remains uncollected for two
years after the date of the assignment meets the criteria for uncollectibility
formulated pursuant to ORS 293.240.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-746__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>ORS 293.245 applies to any obligation due the state and described in subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-746__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-760">
          <num>319.760</num>
          <heading>Assessment of deficiency; presumption that fuel subject to tax</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-760__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the
Department of Transportation is not satisfied that a report filed or amount of
tax or penalty paid to the state by any user or seller is correct, the
department may assess the tax and penalty due based upon any information
available to the department.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-760__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If a seller fails to account satisfactorily for any fuel sold or disposed of,
it shall be presumed that the fuel not accounted for was sold to users for use
in motor vehicles and the department shall assess the tax and penalty due
against the seller.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-760__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department shall give to the user or seller written notice of the
assessment. The notice may be served personally or by mail. If made by mail,
service shall be made by depositing the notice in the United States mail,
postage prepaid, addressed to the user or seller at the address as it appears
in the records of the department. [Amended by 1959 c.188 s26]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-780">
          <num>319.780</num>
          <heading>Assessing tax and penalty upon failure to make report</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-780__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any user
or seller fails to make a report required by ORS 319.510 to 319.880, the
Department of Transportation shall make an estimate, based upon any information
available to the department, for the month or months with respect to which the
user or seller failed to make a report, and assess the tax and penalty due from
the user or seller under ORS 319.510 to 319.880.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-780__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department shall give to the user or seller written notice of the
assessment in the manner prescribed by ORS 319.760</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-780__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>. [Amended by 1959 c.188 s27]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-790">
          <num>319.790</num>
          <heading>Petition for reassessment</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-790__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any user or seller against whom an assessment is
made under ORS 319.760 and 319.780 may petition for a reassessment within 30
days after service of notice of the assessment. If a petition is not filed
within the 30-day period, the amount of the assessment becomes conclusive.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-790__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If a petition for reassessment is filed within the 30-day period the Department
of Transportation shall reconsider the assessment and, if requested in the
petition, shall grant the user or seller an oral hearing and give the user or
seller 10 days’ notice of the time and place thereof. The department may
continue the hearing from time to time. The department shall serve on the
petitioner notice of its finding upon reassessment. If the finding is that a
tax or penalty is delinquent, the petitioner shall pay to the department,
within 30 days after notice is served, all the tax or penalty found to be
delinquent.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-790__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notice required by this section shall be served in the manner prescribed by ORS
319.760</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-790__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>. [Amended by 1959 c.188 s28]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-801">
          <num>319.801</num>
          <heading>Appeal to circuit court</heading>
          <content>
            <p>Any person aggrieved by a finding, order or
determination by the Department of Transportation under ORS 319.630 or 319.790
may appeal therefrom to the circuit court of the county in which the person
resides. Such appeal shall be taken within 60 days from the date of the entry
or making of such order, finding or determination and in the manner provided by
law for appeals in actions at law.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-810">
          <num>319.810</num>
          <heading>Time limitation on service of notice of additional tax</heading>
          <content>
            <p>Except in the
case of an alleged fraudulent report, or neglect or refusal to make a report,
no notice of assessment shall be served on the user or seller after three years
have expired since the alleged erroneous report was filed or a report should
have been filed. [Amended by 1959 c.188 s31]</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-820">
          <num>319.820</num>
          <heading>Refund of tax erroneously or illegally collected</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-820__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the
Department of Transportation determines any amount of tax or penalty has been
paid more than once or has been erroneously or illegally collected, the
department shall credit such amount against any amounts then due from the user
or seller under ORS 319.510 to 319.880 or 319.990</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-820__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>and shall refund any
balance to the user or seller, the successor, administrator or executor of the
user or seller.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-820__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A user or seller may claim a credit or refund for any amount of tax or penalty
which the user or seller has paid more than once or which the user or seller
has paid or which has been collected erroneously or illegally. No such claim
for a credit or refund shall be allowed unless the claim is filed with the
department within three years from the date of the payment or collection or,
with respect to an assessment made under ORS 319.760 and 319.780, within six
months after the assessment becomes conclusive, whichever period expires the
later. Every such claim must be in writing and must state the specific grounds
upon which it is founded. Failure to file such claim within the time prescribed
in this section shall constitute waiver of any and all demands against this
state on account of overpayments under ORS 319.510 to 319.880. Within 30 days
of allowing or disallowing any such claim in whole or in part, the department
shall serve notice of such action on the claimant. The service shall be made in
the manner prescribed by ORS 319.760</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-820__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>. [Amended by 1959 c.188 s32]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-831">
          <num>319.831</num>
          <heading>Refund of tax on fuel used in operation of vehicle over certain roads or private property</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-831__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If a user obtains fuel for use in a motor vehicle in this state and pays
the use fuel tax on the fuel obtained, the user may apply for a refund of that
part of the use fuel tax paid which is applicable to use of the fuel to propel
a motor vehicle:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="319-831__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In another state, if the user pays to the other state an additional tax on the
same fuel;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-831__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon any road, thoroughfare or property in private ownership;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-831__subsec_1__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon any road, thoroughfare or property, other than a state highway, county
road or city street, for the removal of forest products, as defined in ORS
321.005, or the products of such forest products converted to a form other than
logs at or near the harvesting site, or for the construction or maintenance of
the road, thoroughfare or property, pursuant to a written agreement or permit
authorizing the use, construction or maintenance of the road, thoroughfare or
property, with or by:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="319-831__subsec_1__subsec_c__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>An agency of the United States;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="319-831__subsec_1__subsec_c__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The State Board of Forestry;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="319-831__subsec_1__subsec_c__subsec_C">
                <num>(C)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The State Forester; or</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="319-831__subsec_1__subsec_c__subsec_D">
                <num>(D)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>A licensee of an agency named in subparagraph</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="319-831__subsec_1__subsec_c__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>,</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="319-831__subsec_1__subsec_c__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>or</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="319-831__subsec_1__subsec_c__subsec_C">
                <num>(C)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>of this
paragraph;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-831__subsec_1__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>By an agency of the United States or of this state or of any county, city or
port of this state on any road, thoroughfare or property, other than a state
highway, county road or city street;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-831__subsec_1__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>By any incorporated city or town of this state;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-831__subsec_1__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>By any county of this state or by any road assessment district formed under ORS
371.405 to 371.535;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-831__subsec_1__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon any county road for the removal of forest products as defined in ORS
321.005, or the products of such forest products converted to a form other than
logs at or near the harvesting site, if:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="319-831__subsec_1__subsec_g__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Such use upon the county road is pursuant to a written agreement entered into
with, or to a permit issued by, the State Board of Forestry, the State Forester
or an agency of the United States, authorizing such user to use such road and
requiring such user to pay for or to perform the construction or maintenance of
the county road;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="319-831__subsec_1__subsec_g__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The board, officer or agency that entered into the agreement or granted the
permit, by contract with the county court or board of county commissioners, has
assumed the responsibility for the construction or maintenance of such county
road; and</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="319-831__subsec_1__subsec_g__subsec_C">
                <num>(C)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Copies of the agreements or permits required by subparagraphs</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="319-831__subsec_1__subsec_g__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>and</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="319-831__subsec_1__subsec_g__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>of
this paragraph are filed with the Department of Transportation;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-831__subsec_1__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>By a school district or education service district of this state or the
contractors of a school district or education service district, for those
vehicles being used to transport students;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-831__subsec_1__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>By a rural fire protection district organized under the provisions of ORS
chapter 478;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-831__subsec_1__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>By any district, as defined in ORS chapter 198, that is not otherwise
specifically provided for in this section; or</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-831__subsec_1__subsec_k">
              <num>(k)</num>
              <content>
                <p>By any state agency, as defined in ORS 240.855.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-831__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An application for a refund under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-831__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section shall be filed
with the department within 15 months after the date the use fuel tax, for which
a refund is claimed, is paid.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-831__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The application for a refund provided by subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-831__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section shall
include a signed statement by the applicant indicating the amount of fuel for
which a refund is claimed, and the way in which the fuel was used which qualifies
the applicant for a refund. If the fuel upon which the refund is claimed was
obtained from a seller to whom the use fuel tax was paid, the application shall
be supported by the invoices which cover the purchase of the fuel. If the
applicant paid the use fuel tax directly to the department, the applicant shall
indicate the source of the fuel and the date it was obtained.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-831__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department may require any person who applies for a refund provided by
subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-831__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section to furnish a statement, under oath, giving the
person’s occupation, description of the machines or equipment in which the fuel
was used, the place where used and such other information as the department may
require.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-835">
          <num>319.835</num>
          <heading>Investigation of refund applications</heading>
          <content>
            <p>The Department of Transportation may
investigate refund applications and gather and compile such information in
regard to the applications as it considers necessary to safeguard the state and
prevent fraudulent practices in connection with tax refunds and tax evasions.
The department may, in order to establish the validity of any application, examine
the books and records of the applicant for such purposes. Failure of the
applicant to accede to the demand for such examination constitutes a waiver of
all rights to a refund on account of the transaction questioned.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-840">
          <num>319.840</num>
          <heading>Enforcement; rules and regulations</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-840__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>, and hereby is authorized to prescribe, adopt and enforce rules and
regulations relating to the administration and enforcement thereof.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-850">
          <num>319.850</num>
          <heading>Presumption of use; rules</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-850__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>and to prevent evasion of the tax imposed by
ORS 319.530, it shall be presumed, until the contrary is established under such
reasonable rules as the Department of Transportation may adopt, that all fuel
received into or delivered into any receptacle on a motor vehicle from which
receptacle fuel is supplied to propel such motor vehicle is consumed in
propelling such motor vehicle on the highways of this state. [Amended by 1959
c.188 s37]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-860">
          <num>319.860</num>
          <heading>Producers, distributors and others to keep records; examining books and records</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-860__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every person producing, manufacturing, importing, distributing, storing,
transporting or otherwise handling fuel shall maintain and keep in this state
for a period of not less than three years such records, receipts, invoices and
other pertinent papers in such form as the Department of Transportation may require.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-860__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department may examine during normal business hours the books, papers,
records and equipment of any person producing, manufacturing, importing,
distributing, storing, transporting or otherwise handling fuel and may
investigate the character of the disposition which any such person makes of
fuel in order to determine whether all taxes due under ORS 319.510 to 319.880
are being properly reported and paid. [Amended by 1959 c.188 s38]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-870">
          <num>319.870</num>
          <heading>Results of investigations to be private</heading>
          <content>
            <p>It is unlawful for the Department of
Transportation, or any person having an administrative duty under ORS 319.510
to 319.880, to divulge the business affairs, operations, or information
obtained by an investigation of records and equipment of any user or other person
visited or examined in the discharge of official duty, or the amount or source
of income, profits, losses, expenditures or any particular thereof, set forth
or disclosed in any report, or to permit any report or copy thereof or any book
containing any abstract or particulars thereof to be seen or examined by any
person except as provided by law. However, the department may authorize
examination of such reports by, and the giving of information therein contained
to other state officers, or tax officers of another state or the federal
government if a reciprocal arrangement exists.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-875">
          <num>319.875</num>
          <heading>Prohibitions</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-875__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No person shall intentionally make a false statement in any report,
petition or application required or permitted by ORS 319.510 to 319.880.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-875__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No person shall intentionally collect, or attempt to collect or receive a
refund of a tax or penalty paid to the Department of Transportation under ORS
319.510 to 319.880 to which the person is not entitled.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-875__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No person shall intentionally aid or assist another person to violate any
provision of ORS 319.510 to 319.880.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-880">
          <num>319.880</num>
          <heading>Disposition of moneys</heading>
          <content>
            <p>All money received by the Department of
Transportation pursuant to ORS 319.510 to 319.880 shall be turned over promptly
to the State Treasurer and shall be disposed of as provided in ORS 802.110. [Amended
by 1955 c.287 s22; 1961 c.146 s3; 1969 c.70 s2; 1983 c.338 s910]
PER-MILE
ROAD USAGE CHARGE</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-883">
          <num>319.883</num>
          <heading>Definitions for ORS 319.883 to 319.946</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-883__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Fuel taxes” means motor vehicle fuel taxes imposed under ORS 319.010 to
319.430 and taxes imposed on the use of fuel in a motor vehicle under ORS
319.510 to 319.880.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-883__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Highway” has the meaning given that term in ORS 801.305.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-883__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Lessee” means a person that leases a motor vehicle that is required to be
registered in Oregon.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-883__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <paragraph eId="319-883__subsec_4__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>“Motor vehicle” has the meaning given that term in ORS 801.360.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-883__subsec_4__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>“Motor vehicle” does not mean a motor vehicle designed to travel with fewer
than four wheels in contact with the ground.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-883__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Registered owner” means a person, other than a vehicle dealer that holds a
certificate issued under ORS 822.020, that is required to register a motor
vehicle in Oregon.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-883__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Subject vehicle” means a motor vehicle that is the subject of an application
approved pursuant to ORS 319.890.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-883__subsec_7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Vehicle dealer” means a person engaged in business in this state that is
required to obtain a vehicle dealer certificate under ORS 822.005. [2013 c.781 s2;
2019 c.428 s12]
Note: 319.883 to
319.946 were added to and made a part of ORS chapter 319 by legislative action
but were not added to any smaller series therein. See Preface to Oregon Revised
Statutes for further explanation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-885">
          <num>319.885</num>
          <heading>Per-mile road usage charge</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-885__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <paragraph eId="319-885__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in paragraph</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-885__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this
subsection, the registered owner of a subject vehicle shall pay a per-mile road
usage charge for metered use by the subject vehicle of the highways in Oregon.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-885__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>During the term of a lease, the lessee of a subject vehicle shall pay the
per-mile road usage charge for metered use by the subject vehicle of the
highways in Oregon.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-885__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The rate of the per-mile road usage charge is five percent of the rate of the
per-gallon license tax provided in ORS 319.020</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-885__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <paragraph eId="319-885__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>in effect at the time the
charge becomes due. [2013 c.781 s3; 2017 c.750 ss118,118a; 2019 c.428 ss3,4]
Note: See note under
319.883.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-890">
          <num>319.890</num>
          <heading>Application for road usage charge program; when additional registration fees to be collected; consultation with vehicle dealers to encourage participation; rules</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-890__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A person wishing to pay the per-mile road usage charge imposed under ORS
319.885 must apply to the Department of Transportation on a form prescribed by
the department.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-890__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department shall approve a valid and complete application submitted under
this section if:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="319-890__subsec_2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The applicant has applied for registration or is the registered owner or lessee
of a motor vehicle;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-890__subsec_2__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The motor vehicle is equipped with a method selected pursuant to ORS 319.900
for collecting and reporting the metered use by the motor vehicle of the
highways in Oregon;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-890__subsec_2__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The motor vehicle is classified as a passenger vehicle by the department; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-890__subsec_2__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The vehicle has a rating of at least 20 miles per gallon, such rating to be established
by the department.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-890__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An electric vehicle or a vehicle with a rating of 40 miles per gallon or
greater for which an application has been submitted or approved under this
section is not subject to the additional amount of registration fees imposed
under ORS 803.422.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-890__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Approval of an application under this section subjects the applicant to the
requirements of ORS 319.920 until the person ends the person’s voluntary
participation in the road usage charge program in the manner required under
subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-890__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-890__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A person may end the person’s voluntary participation in the road usage charge
program at any time by notifying the department, returning any emblem issued
under ORS 319.945 to the department and paying any outstanding amount of road
usage charge for metered use by the person’s subject vehicle.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-890__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <paragraph eId="319-890__subsec_6__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>This subsection applies to a person whose subject vehicle is described in
subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-890__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section and:
(A)
Who ends voluntary participation in the per-mile road usage charge program with
respect to the subject vehicle;
(B)
Whose application is not approved under this section; or
(C)
Whose subject vehicle has been removed from the per-mile road usage charge
program.</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="319-890__subsec_3__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to any amount due under subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-890__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section, the
department may collect an additional amount equal to the registration fees that
would otherwise have been due with respect to the subject vehicle for the
current registration period under ORS 803.422 or a portion of the fees.</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="319-890__subsec_5__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall establish by rule the circumstances in which a person
described in paragraph</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-890__subsec_5__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <subparagraph eId="319-890__subsec_5__subsec_a__subsec_C">
                <num>(C)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>of this subsection is required to pay an
additional amount under paragraph</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-890__subsec_5__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this subsection.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-890__subsec_5__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may deny registration for the subject vehicle until the
additional amount imposed under paragraph</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-890__subsec_5__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this subsection has been paid.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-890__subsec_7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Department of Transportation shall consult with vehicle dealers that sell
passenger vehicles to determine the most effective methods, at the point of
sale, to encourage participation in the per-mile road usage charge program. [2013
c.781 s4; 2015 c.716 s11; 2017 c.750 s118c; 2019 c.428 s1; subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-890__subsec_7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of
2019 Edition enacted as 2019 c.428 s10; 2021 c.630 s93]
Note: Section 2,
chapter 428, Oregon Laws 2019, provides:
Sec.
2.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-890__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <paragraph eId="319-890__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The amendments to ORS 319.890</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-890__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-890__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>by section 1 of this 2019 Act
apply to applications for participation in the per-mile road usage charge
program submitted on or after the operative date of this 2019 Act [January 1,
2020].</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="319-890__subsec_3__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding the amendments to ORS 319.890</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-890__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <paragraph eId="319-890__subsec_2__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>by section 1 of this 2019
Act and the date specified in subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-890__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section, a subject vehicle
with a rating of less than 20 miles per gallon that is approved for the per-mile
road usage charge program before the date specified in subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-890__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this
section may remain in the program on and after the date specified in subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-890__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-890__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The amendments to ORS 319.890</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-890__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>by section 1 of this 2019 Act apply to a
person that ends the person’s voluntary participation in the per-mile road
usage charge program on or after the operative date of this 2019 Act. [2019
c.428 s2]
Note: See note under
319.883.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-895">
          <num>319.895</num>
          <heading>Deposit and distribution of road usage charge moneys</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-895__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>50 percent to the Department of Transportation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-895__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>30 percent to counties for distribution as provided in ORS 366.762.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-895__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>20 percent to cities for distribution as provided in ORS 366.800. [2013 c.781 s5]
Note: See note under
319.883.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-900">
          <num>319.900</num>
          <heading>Department of Transportation to establish methods for recording and reporting mileage</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-900__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>As used in
this section, “open system” means an integrated system based on common
standards and an operating system that has been made public so that components
performing the same function can be readily substituted or provided by multiple
providers.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-900__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <paragraph eId="319-900__subsec_2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Transportation, in consultation with the Road User Fee Task
Force, shall establish the methods for recording and reporting the number of
miles that subject vehicles travel on highways.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-900__subsec_2__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When taking action under this subsection, the department shall consider:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="319-900__subsec_2__subsec_b__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The accuracy of the data collected;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="319-900__subsec_2__subsec_b__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Privacy options for persons liable for the per-mile road usage charge;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="319-900__subsec_2__subsec_b__subsec_C">
                <num>(C)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The security of the technology;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="319-900__subsec_2__subsec_b__subsec_D">
                <num>(D)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The resistance of the technology to tampering;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="319-900__subsec_2__subsec_b__subsec_E">
                <num>(E)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The ability to audit compliance; and</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="319-900__subsec_2__subsec_b__subsec_F">
                <num>(F)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Other relevant factors that the department deems important.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-900__subsec_2__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall establish at least one method of collecting and reporting
the number of miles traveled by a subject vehicle that does not use vehicle
location technology.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-900__subsec_2__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <subparagraph eId="319-900__subsec_2__subsec_d__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The department shall adopt standards for open system technology used in methods
established under this subsection.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="319-900__subsec_2__subsec_d__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>In adopting standards pursuant to this paragraph, the department shall
collaborate with agencies of the executive department as defined in ORS 174.112
to integrate information systems currently in use or planned for future use.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-900__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department shall provide the persons liable for the per-mile road usage
charge the opportunity to select a method from among multiple options for
collecting and reporting the metered use by a subject vehicle of the highways
in Oregon. [2013 c.781 s6]
Note: See note under
319.883.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-905">
          <num>319.905</num>
          <heading>Department of Transportation to adopt rules for collecting road usage charge</heading>
          <content>
            <p>The Department of
Transportation shall provide by rule for the collection of the road usage
charges imposed under ORS 319.885, including penalties and interest imposed on
delinquent charges. [2013 c.781 s7]
Note: See note under
319.883.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-910">
          <num>319.910</num>
          <heading>Department of Transportation to establish reporting periods for road usage charge</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-910__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Department of Transportation shall establish by rule reporting periods
for the road usage charges imposed under ORS 319.885.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-910__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Reporting periods established under this section may vary according to the
facts and circumstances applicable to classes of registered owners, lessees and
subject vehicles.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-910__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In establishing reporting periods, the department shall consider:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="319-910__subsec_3__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The effort required by registered owners or lessees to report metered use and
to pay the per-mile road usage charge;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-910__subsec_3__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The amount of the per-mile road usage charge owed;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-910__subsec_3__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The cost to the registered owner or lessee of reporting metered use and of
paying the per-mile road usage charge;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-910__subsec_3__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The administrative cost to the department; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-910__subsec_3__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Other relevant factors that the department deems important. [2013 c.781 s8]
Note: See note under
319.883.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-915">
          <num>319.915</num>
          <heading>Confidentiality of personally identifiable information used for reporting and collecting road usage charge; exceptions; records to be destroyed; exceptions; Department of Transportation to provide for penalties</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-915__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>As used in
this section:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="319-915__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>“Certified service provider” means an entity that has entered into an agreement
with the Department of Transportation under ORS 367.806 for reporting metered
use by a subject vehicle or for administrative services related to the
collection of per-mile road usage charges and authorized employees of the
entity.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-915__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>“Personally identifiable information” means any information that identifies or
describes a person, including, but not limited to, the person’s travel pattern
data, per-mile road usage charge account number, address, telephone number,
electronic mail address, driver license or identification card number,
registration plate number, photograph, recorded images, bank account
information and credit card number.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-915__subsec_1__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>“VIN summary report” means a monthly report by the department or a certified
service provider that includes a summary of all vehicle identification numbers
of subject vehicles and associated total metered use during the month. The
report may not include location information.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-915__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Except as provided in subsections</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-915__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-915__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section, personally
identifiable information used for reporting metered use or for administrative
services related to the collection of the per-mile road usage charge imposed
under ORS 319.885 is confidential within the meaning of ORS 192.355</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-915__subsec_9">
            <num>(9)</num>
            <paragraph eId="319-915__subsec_9__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>and
is a public record exempt from disclosure under ORS 192.311 to 192.478.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-915__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <paragraph eId="319-915__subsec_3__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department, a certified service provider or a contractor for a certified
service provider may not disclose personally identifiable information used or
developed for reporting metered use by a subject vehicle or for administrative
services related to the collection of per-mile road usage charges to any person
except:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="319-915__subsec_3__subsec_a__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The registered owner or lessee;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="319-915__subsec_3__subsec_a__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>A financial institution, for the purpose of collecting per-mile road usage
charges owed;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="319-915__subsec_3__subsec_a__subsec_C">
                <num>(C)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Employees of the department;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="319-915__subsec_3__subsec_a__subsec_D">
                <num>(D)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>A certified service provider;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="319-915__subsec_3__subsec_a__subsec_E">
                <num>(E)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>A contractor for a certified service provider, but only to the extent the
contractor provides services directly related to the certified service provider’s
agreement with the department;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="319-915__subsec_3__subsec_a__subsec_F">
                <num>(F)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>An entity expressly approved to receive the information by the registered owner
or lessee of the subject vehicle; or</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="319-915__subsec_3__subsec_a__subsec_G">
                <num>(G)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>A police officer pursuant to a valid court order based on probable cause and
issued at the request of a federal, state or local law enforcement agency in an
authorized criminal investigation involving a person to whom the requested
information pertains.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-915__subsec_3__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Disclosure under paragraph</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-915__subsec_3__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this subsection is limited to personally
identifiable information necessary to the respective recipient’s function under
ORS 319.883 to 319.946.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-915__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <paragraph eId="319-915__subsec_4__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Not later than 30 days after completion of payment processing, dispute
resolution for a single reporting period or a noncompliance investigation,
whichever is latest, the department and certified service providers shall
destroy records of the location and daily metered use of subject vehicles.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-915__subsec_4__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding paragraph</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-915__subsec_4__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this subsection:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="319-915__subsec_4__subsec_a__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>For purposes of traffic management and research, the department and certified
service providers may retain, aggregate and use information in the records
after removing personally identifiable information.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="319-915__subsec_4__subsec_a__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>A certified service provider may retain the records if the registered owner or
lessee consents to the retention. Consent under this subparagraph does not
entitle the department to obtain or use the records or the information
contained in the records.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="319-915__subsec_4__subsec_a__subsec_C">
                <num>(C)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Monthly summaries of metered use by subject vehicles may be retained in VIN
summary reports by the department and certified service providers.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-915__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department, in any agreement with a certified service provider, shall
provide for penalties if the certified service provider violates this section. [2013
c.781 s9]
Note: See note under
319.883.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-920">
          <num>319.920</num>
          <heading>Reporting requirement</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-920__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>On a date determined by the Department of
Transportation under ORS 319.910, the registered owner or lessee of a subject
vehicle shall report the metered use by the subject vehicle and pay to the
department the per-mile road usage charge due under ORS 319.885 for the
reporting period.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-920__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Unless a registered owner or lessee presents evidence in a manner approved by
the department by rule that the subject vehicle has been driven outside this
state, the department shall assume that all metered use reported represents
miles driven by the subject vehicle on the highways in Oregon. [2013 c.781 s10;
2015 c.716 s13]
Note: See note under
319.883.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-923">
          <num>319.923</num>
          <heading>Reconciliation of fuel taxes and per-mile road usage charge</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-923__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If, at the
end of a reporting period established pursuant to ORS 319.910, the amount that
a person has paid, directly or indirectly, in fuel taxes for the reporting
period with respect to a subject vehicle is less than the amount of the
per-mile road usage charge owing under ORS 319.885 for the reporting period
with respect to the subject vehicle, the Department of Transportation shall:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="319-923__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Debit the person’s per-mile road usage charge account for the reporting period
solely for the amount of the difference; or</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-923__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the person makes a direct payment in the amount of the difference to the
department, not debit the person’s account for the per-mile road usage charge
for the reporting period.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-923__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If, at the end of a reporting period established pursuant to ORS 319.910, the
amount that a person has paid, directly or indirectly, in fuel taxes for the
reporting period with respect to a subject vehicle exceeds the amount of the
per-mile road usage charge owing under ORS 319.885 for the reporting period
with respect to the subject vehicle, the department shall not:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="319-923__subsec_2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Debit the person’s account for the amount of the per-mile road usage charge
owing for the reporting period; or</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-923__subsec_2__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Issue a refund to the person or credit the person’s account for the amount of
the excess. [2019 c.428 s9]
Note: See note under
319.883.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-925">
          <num>319.925</num>
          <heading>Refunds for overpayment; grant of refund as credit</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-925__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The
Department of Transportation shall provide a refund to a registered owner or
lessee that has overpaid the per-mile road usage charge imposed under ORS
319.885.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-925__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department may provide by rule that the refund under this section be
granted as a credit against future per-mile road usage charges incurred by the
registered owner or lessee. [2013 c.781 s11]
Note: See note under
319.883.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-930">
          <num>319.930</num>
          <heading>Refund applications</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-930__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A registered owner or lessee that has paid the per-mile road usage charge
imposed under ORS 319.885 may apply to the Department of Transportation for a
refund for metered use of a road, thoroughfare or property in private
ownership.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-930__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An application for a refund under this section must be submitted to the
department within 15 months after the date on which the per-mile road usage
charge for which a refund is claimed is paid.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-930__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The application required under this section shall be in a form prescribed by
the department by rule and must include a signed statement by the applicant
indicating the number of miles for which the refund is claimed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-930__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department may require the applicant for a refund under this section to
furnish any information the department considers necessary for processing the
application. [2013 c.781 s12]
Note: See note under
319.883.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-935">
          <num>319.935</num>
          <heading>Investigation of refund applications</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-935__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Department of Transportation may
investigate a refund application submitted under ORS 319.930 and gather and
compile such information related to the application as the department considers
necessary to safeguard the state and prevent fraudulent practices in connection
with tax refunds and tax evasion.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-935__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department may, in order to establish the validity of an application,
examine the relevant records of the applicant for such purposes.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-935__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If an applicant does not permit the department to examine the relevant records,
the applicant waives all rights to the refund to which the application relates.
[2013 c.781 s13]
Note: See note under
319.883.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-940">
          <num>319.940</num>
          <heading>Violations</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-940__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A person may not intentionally make a false statement in a report or refund
application or when supplying other information required under ORS 319.920 or
319.930.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-940__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A person may not intentionally apply for, receive or attempt to receive a
refund under ORS 319.925 or 319.930 to which the person is not entitled.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-940__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A person may not intentionally aid or assist another person to violate any
provision of ORS 319.920, 319.925 or 319.930.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-940__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A person who violates any provision of this section commits a Class A
violation. [2013 c.781 s14]
Note: See note under
319.883.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-945">
          <num>319.945</num>
          <heading>Authority to issue emblems; display</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-945__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Department of Transportation may
issue an emblem to the registered owner of a subject vehicle to show that the
use of fuel in the subject vehicle is exempt from taxation under ORS 319.510 to
319.880.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-945__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An emblem issued under this section shall be displayed:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="319-945__subsec_2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In a conspicuous place on the subject vehicle; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="319-945__subsec_2__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Only upon the subject vehicle with respect to which it is issued. [2013 c.781 s15;
2015 c.716 s10]
Note: See note under
319.883.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-946">
          <num>319.946</num>
          <heading>General rulemaking authority for per-mile road usage charge program</heading>
          <content>
            <p>In accordance
with applicable provisions of ORS chapter 183, the Department of Transportation
may adopt any rules the department considers necessary or convenient for the
administration of ORS 319.883 to 319.946. [2019 c.428 s11]
Note: See note under
319.883.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-947">
          <num>319.947</num>
          <heading>Multijurisdictional agreements</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-947__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Conducting joint research relating to road usage charges and development
programs on a multistate basis;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-947__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Furthering the development and operation of single state or multistate road
usage charge pilot programs;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-947__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Sharing costs incurred in conducting the research described in subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-947__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section; and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-947__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Developing a program for stakeholder outreach and communications with respect
to road usage charges. [2013 c.781 s29]
Note: 319.947 was
enacted into law by the Legislative Assembly but was not added to or made a
part of ORS chapter 319 or any series therein by legislative action. See
Preface to Oregon Revised Statutes for further explanation.
LOCAL
FUEL TAXES</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-950">
          <num>319.950</num>
          <heading>Election required for local tax on motor vehicle fuel; agreement with Department of Transportation to collect tax</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-950__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The governing body of a city,
county or other local government may enact or amend any charter provision,
ordinance, resolution or other provision taxing fuel for motor vehicles after
submitting the proposed tax to the electors of the local government for their
approval.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-950__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The governing body of a local government that imposes a tax on fuel for motor
vehicles pursuant to this section may enter into an intergovernmental agreement
under ORS 190.010 with the Department of Transportation pursuant to which the
department shall collect and distribute the revenues from the tax. [2009 c.865 s27;
2021 c.630 s13]
Note: 319.950 was
enacted into law by the Legislative Assembly but was not added to or made a
part of ORS chapter 319 or any series therein by legislative action. See
Preface to Oregon Revised Statutes for further explanation.
PENALTIES</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_319-990">
          <num>319.990</num>
          <heading>Penalties</heading>
          <subsection eId="319-990__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any person who violates any of the provisions of ORS 319.010 to 319.430, or
any person who makes any false statement in any statement required by ORS
319.010 to 319.430 for the refund of any money or tax as provided in ORS
319.010 to 319.430, or who collects or causes to be repaid to the person or any
person any tax, without being entitled to it under the provisions of ORS
319.010 to 319.430, commits a Class B misdemeanor.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-990__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Violation of ORS 319.180</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-990__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>or 319.694</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-990__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>is theft of public money and, upon
conviction, is punishable as provided in ORS 164.043 to 164.057.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-990__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Violation of any provision of ORS 319.240</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-990__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-990__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>is a Class B misdemeanor.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="319-990__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Violation of any provision of ORS 319.510 to 319.880 is a Class A misdemeanor. [Amended
by 1959 c.188 s43; 1961 c.261 s3; 1971 c.743 s355; 1987 c.610 s19; 1987 c.907 s15;
1999 c.769 s15; 2011 c.597 s181]
_______________</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>