<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="ORS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-or/act/ors/chapter-318"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-or/act/ors/chapter-318"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#oregon-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-or"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="318"/>
          <FRBRname value="ORS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-or/act/ors/chapter-318/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-or/act/ors/chapter-318/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-or/act/ors/chapter-318/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-or/act/ors/chapter-318/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="oregon-legislature" href="https://www.oregonlegislature.gov" showAs="Oregon State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <chapter eId="chp_318">
        <num>318</num>
        <heading>Corporation Income Tax</heading>
        <section eId="sec_318-010">
          <num>318.010</num>
          <heading>Short title; Department of Revenue to administer chapter</heading>
          <content>
            <p>This chapter
shall be known and may be cited as the Corporation Income Tax Act of 1955, and
it shall be administered by the Department of Revenue.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_318-020">
          <num>318.020</num>
          <heading>Imposition of tax</heading>
          <subsection eId="318-020__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>There hereby is imposed upon every corporation for each taxable year a tax
at the rate provided in ORS 317.061 upon its Oregon taxable income derived from
sources within this state, other than income for which the corporation is
subject to the tax imposed by ORS chapter 317 according to or measured by its
Oregon taxable income.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="318-020__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Income from sources within this state includes income from tangible or
intangible property located or having a situs in this state and income from any
activities carried on in this state, regardless of whether carried on in
intrastate, interstate or foreign commerce.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="318-020__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Income that constitutes net long-term capital gain described in ORS 317.063
shall be taxed at the rate imposed under ORS 317.063.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_318-031">
          <num>318.031</num>
          <heading>Provisions in ORS chapters 305, 314, 315 and 317 incorporated into corporation income tax law</heading>
          <content>
            <p>It being the intention of the Legislative Assembly that this chapter and ORS
chapter 317 shall be administered as uniformly as possible (allowance being
made for the difference in imposition of the taxes), ORS 305.140 and 305.150,
ORS chapter 314 and the following sections are incorporated into and made a
part of this chapter: ORS 315.104, 315.124, 315.133, 315.141, 315.156, 315.176,
315.204, 315.208, 315.213, 315.283, 315.304, 315.326, 315.331, 315.336,
315.506, 315.507, 315.523, 315.533, 315.593 and 315.643 (all only to the extent
applicable to a corporation) and ORS chapter 317.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_318-040">
          <num>318.040</num>
          <heading>Exempt corporations</heading>
          <content>
            <p>In addition to the corporations exempt from the provisions of this chapter by
the incorporation in this chapter of ORS 317.080, there shall also be exempt
those foreign corporations whose activities in this state are confined to
purchases of personal property, and the storage thereof incident to shipment
outside the state, unless such foreign corporation is an affiliate of another
foreign or domestic corporation which is doing business in Oregon or is subject
to this chapter. Whether or not corporations are affiliated shall be determined
as provided in section 1504 of the Internal Revenue Code.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_318-060">
          <num>318.060</num>
          <heading>Rules and regulations; personnel</heading>
          <content>
            <p>The Department of Revenue is authorized
to employ such personnel, and prescribe and prepare such rules, regulations,
forms and tables as are necessary to place this chapter in operation.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_318-070">
          <num>318.070</num>
          <heading>Disposition of revenue</heading>
          <content>
            <p>The net revenue from the tax imposed by this chapter
shall be paid over to the State Treasurer and held in the General Fund as
miscellaneous receipts available generally to meet any expense or obligation of
the State of Oregon lawfully incurred. A working balance of unreceipted revenue
from the tax imposed by this chapter may be retained by the Department of
Revenue for the payment of refunds, but such working balance shall not at the
close of any fiscal year exceed the sum of $50,000.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_318-074">
          <num>318.074</num>
          <heading>Disposition of revenue from tax imposed at increased rate; estimate</heading>
          <subsection eId="318-074__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For tax years
beginning on or after January 1, 2013, and before January 1, 2017, any revenue
that is received as a result of a rate of tax above 7.5 percent imposed under
this chapter and that is in excess of the revenue that would be received under
this chapter at a rate of 7.5 percent shall be deposited into the Oregon Rainy
Day Fund established by ORS 293.144.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="318-074__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For tax years beginning on or after January 1, 2017, any revenue that is
received as a result of a rate of tax above 7.2 percent imposed under this
chapter and that is in excess of the revenue that would be received under this
chapter at a rate of 7.2 percent shall be deposited into the Oregon Rainy Day
Fund established by ORS 293.144.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="318-074__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Before the end of each biennium, beginning with the biennium ending on June 30,
2015, the Department of Revenue shall estimate the revenue described in
subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="318-074__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>or</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="318-074__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section that is received during the biennium. An
amount equal to that estimate shall be transferred into the Oregon Rainy Day
Fund established by ORS 293.144 on or before June 30 of each odd-numbered year.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_318-106">
          <num>318.106</num>
          <heading>ORS 317.151 as part of chapter</heading>
          <content>
            <p>ORS 317.151 is incorporated into and made
a part of this chapter.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_318-130">
          <num>318.130</num>
          <heading>ORS 317.329 as part of chapter</heading>
          <content>
            <p>ORS 317.329 is incorporated into and made
a part of this chapter by reference.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>