<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="ORS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-or/act/ors/chapter-417"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-or/act/ors/chapter-417"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#oregon-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-or"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="417"/>
          <FRBRname value="ORS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-or/act/ors/chapter-417/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-or/act/ors/chapter-417/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-or/act/ors/chapter-417/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-or/act/ors/chapter-417/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="oregon-legislature" href="https://www.oregonlegislature.gov" showAs="Oregon State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <chapter eId="chp_417">
        <num>417</num>
        <heading>Youth Development Council; Positive Youth Development</heading>
        <section eId="sec_417-010">
          <num>417.010</num>
          <heading>“Juvenile” defined for ORS 417.010 to 417.080</heading>
          <content>
            <p>As used in ORS
417.010 to 417.080, “juvenile” includes any person who is within the
jurisdiction of the juvenile court.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-020">
          <num>417.020</num>
          <heading>Declaration of public policy</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-020__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It hereby is found and declared that:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-020__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Juveniles who are not under proper supervision and control, or who have
absconded, escaped or run away, are likely to endanger their own health, morals
and welfare, and the health, morals and welfare of others; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-020__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The cooperation of this state with other states is necessary to provide for the
welfare and protection of juveniles and of the people of this state.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-020__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It is therefore the policy of this state, in adopting the Interstate Compact
for Juveniles, to cooperate fully with other states in returning juveniles to
such other states whenever their return is sought, to accept the return of
juveniles whenever a juvenile residing in this state is found or apprehended in
another state and to take all measures to initiate proceedings for the return
of such juveniles.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-030">
          <num>417.030</num>
          <heading>The Interstate Compact for Juveniles</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-030__subsec_1965">
            <num>(1965)</num>
            <content>
              <p>, has authorized and encouraged compacts for cooperative
efforts and mutual assistance in the prevention of crime.
It
is the purpose of this compact, through means of joint and cooperative action
among the compacting states to:
A.
Ensure that the adjudicated juveniles and status offenders subject to this
compact are provided adequate supervision and services in the receiving state
as ordered by the adjudicating judge or parole authority in the sending state;
B.
Ensure that the public safety interests of the citizens, including the victims
of juvenile offenders, in both the sending and receiving states are adequately
protected;
C.
Return juveniles who have run away, absconded or escaped from supervision or
control or have been accused of an offense to the state requesting their
return;
D.
Make contracts for the cooperative institutionalization in public facilities in
member states for delinquent youth needing special services;
E.
Provide for the effective tracking and supervision of juveniles;
F.
Equitably allocate the costs, benefits and obligations of the compacting
states;
G.
Establish procedures to manage the movement between states of juvenile
offenders released to the community under the jurisdiction of courts, juvenile
departments, or any other criminal or juvenile justice agency that has
jurisdiction over juvenile offenders;
H.
Ensure immediate notice to jurisdictions where defined offenders are authorized
to travel or to relocate across state lines;
I.
Establish procedures to resolve pending charges (detainers) against juvenile
offenders prior to transfer or release to the community under the terms of this
compact;
J.
Establish a system of uniform data collection on information pertaining to
juveniles subject to this compact that allows access by authorized juvenile
justice and criminal justice officials, and regular reporting of Compact
activities to heads of state executive, judicial and legislative branches and
juvenile and </p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-030__subsec_2000">
            <num>(2000)</num>
            <content>
              <p>, or such
other administrative procedures act, as the Interstate Commission deems
appropriate consistent with due process requirements under the United States
Constitution as now or hereafter interpreted by the United States Supreme
Court. All rules and amendments shall become binding as of the date specified,
as published with the final version of the rule as approved by the Commission.
C.
When promulgating a rule, the Interstate Commission shall, at a minimum:
1.
Publish the proposed rule’s entire text stating the reason</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-030__subsec_2000__subsec_s">
              <num>(s)</num>
              <content>
                <p>for that proposed
rule;
2.
Allow and invite any and all persons to submit written data, facts, opinions
and arguments, which information shall be added to the record, and be made
publicly available;
3.
Provide an opportunity for an informal hearing if petitioned by 10 or more
persons; and
4.
Promulgate a final rule and its effective date, if appropriate, based on input
from state or local officials, or interested parties.
D.
Allow, not later than 60 days after a rule is promulgated, any interested
person to file a petition in the United States District Court for the District
of Columbia or in the Federal District Court where the Interstate Commission’s
principal office is located for judicial review of such rule. If the court
finds that the Interstate Commission’s action is not supported by substantial
evidence in the rulemaking record, the court shall hold the rule unlawful and
set it aside. For purposes of this subsection, evidence is substantial if it
would be considered substantial evidence under the Model State Administrative
Procedures Act.
E.
If a majority of the legislatures of the compacting states rejects a rule,
those states may, by enactment of a statute or resolution in the same manner
used to adopt the compact, cause that such rule shall have no further force and
effect in any compacting state.
F.
The existing rules governing the operation of the Interstate Compact on
Juveniles superceded by this Act shall be null and void 12 months after the
first meeting of the Interstate Commission created hereunder.
G.
Upon determination by the Interstate Commission that a state of emergency
exists, it may promulgate an emergency rule that shall become effective
immediately upon adoption, provided that the usual rulemaking procedures
provided hereunder shall be retroactively applied to said rule as soon as
reasonably possible, but no later than 90 days after the effective date of the
emergency rule.
ARTICLE
VII
OVERSIGHT,
ENFORCEMENT</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-040">
          <num>417.040</num>
          <heading>Juvenile Compact Administrator and staff; rules</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-040__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The office of
Juvenile Compact Administrator hereby is created. The Director of the Oregon
Youth Authority shall be ex officio Juvenile Compact Administrator, with no additional
compensation. The administrator shall act jointly with like officers of other
party states in promulgating rules and regulations to carry out more
effectively the terms of the compact. The administrator shall cooperate with
all departments, agencies and officers of the government of this state and its
subdivisions in facilitating the proper administration of the compact or of any
supplementary agreement or agreements entered into by this state thereunder.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-040__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Juvenile Compact Administrator shall appoint a Deputy Juvenile Compact
Administrator to serve at the pleasure of the administrator. The deputy shall
be appointed on the basis of personal qualifications in accordance with
standards fixed by the Oregon Youth Authority. The youth authority shall fix
the salary of the deputy. Subject to the approval of the youth authority, and
at salaries fixed by it, the administrator may employ such other personnel as
may be necessary to accomplish the purposes of ORS 417.010 to 417.080. The
administrator shall prescribe the duties of the deputy and such other
personnel, and they shall be subject to the control and under the immediate
supervision of the administrator. Personnel other than the administrator and
the deputy shall be subject to any applicable provision of the State Personnel
Relations Law. Subject to the approval of the youth authority, the
administrator may also provide necessary offices, supplies and equipment.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-042">
          <num>417.042</num>
          <heading>Adjudicated delinquent’s obligation to report as sex offender</heading>
          <content>
            <p>Before granting
permission to a sending state to authorize an adjudicated delinquent on
probation or parole to reside in this state, the Juvenile Compact Administrator
described in ORS 417.040 shall determine whether the adjudicated delinquent is
required to report as a sex offender under ORS 163A.025. If the adjudicated
delinquent is required to report as a sex offender, the Juvenile Compact
Administrator shall, before granting permission for the adjudicated delinquent to
reside in this state, make a diligent effort to ensure that the sending state
notifies the adjudicated delinquent of the obligation to report described in
ORS 163A.025 and the procedures for obtaining relief from that obligation
described in ORS 163A.130 and 163A.135. [2009 c.713 s19; 2009 c.891 s3; 2011
c.271 s23]
Note: 417.042 was
enacted into law by the Legislative Assembly but was not added to or made a
part of ORS chapter 417 or any series therein by legislative action. See
Preface to Oregon Revised Statutes for further explanation.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-050">
          <num>417.050</num>
          <heading>Supplementary agreements</heading>
          <content>
            <p>The Juvenile Compact Administrator may enter into
supplementary agreements with appropriate officials of other states under the
compact. In the event that a supplementary agreement requires or contemplates
the use of any institution or facility of this state or requires or
contemplates the providing of any service by this state, the supplementary
agreement shall have no force or effect until approved by the head of the
department or agency under whose jurisdiction the institution or facility is
operated or whose department or agency will be charged with the providing of
the service.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-060">
          <num>417.060</num>
          <heading>Proceedings for recovery of expenses in enforcing compact and agreements</heading>
          <content>
            <p>The Juvenile
Compact Administrator may recover from parents or guardians any moneys expended
by this state or any of its subdivisions in returning a delinquent or
nondelinquent juvenile to this state, for care pending the return of the
juvenile to this state or for care provided pursuant to any supplementary
agreement. Proceedings to recover such moneys shall be brought before the
juvenile court, which shall, upon the parent, parents or guardian being duly
summoned or voluntarily appearing, enter such order or judgment as is equitable
in the premises. The order or judgment may be enforced by execution or in any
manner in which a court of equity may enforce its orders or judgments. No
property belonging to persons subject to the order or judgment shall be exempt
from levy and sale under execution.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-070">
          <num>417.070</num>
          <heading>Juvenile court jurisdiction</heading>
          <content>
            <p>The juvenile courts of this state have
jurisdiction of juveniles within the operation of ORS 417.010 to 417.080.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-080">
          <num>417.080</num>
          <heading>Enforcement of compact</heading>
          <content>
            <p>The courts, departments, agencies and officers of
this state and its subdivisions shall enforce this compact and shall do all
things appropriate to the effectuation of its purposes and intent which may be
within their respective jurisdictions. [1959 c.434 s6]
INTERSTATE
COMPACTS
FOR
ADOPTION ASSISTANCE</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-090">
          <num>417.090</num>
          <heading>Definitions for ORS 417.090 to 417.105</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-090__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Adoption assistance” means financial and medical assistance to an adoptive
family to assist the family with the costs associated with the needs of the
adoptive child.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-090__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Adoption assistance state” means the state that has signed an adoption
assistance agreement in a particular case.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-090__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Medical assistance” means programs for payment of medical and remedial care
provided to eligible individuals.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-090__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Residence state” means the state in which a child who is the subject of an
adoption assistance agreement is living.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-090__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“State” means a state of the United States, the District of Columbia, the
Commonwealth of Puerto Rico, the United States Virgin Islands, Guam, the
Commonwealth of the Northern Mariana Islands or a territory or possession of,
or administered by, the United States.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-095">
          <num>417.095</num>
          <heading>Authority to enter into interstate compacts</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-095__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Department of Human
Services may develop, participate in the development of, negotiate and enter
into one or more interstate compacts on behalf of this state with other states
to:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-095__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Provide adoption assistance and other necessary services for children who are
the subjects of adoption assistance agreements in one state and are residing in
another state; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-095__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Establish procedures for efficient interstate delivery of adoption assistance
and related services and benefits that will protect the interests of adopted
children who move from one state to another.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-095__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When the department enters into an interstate compact under this section, the
compact has the force and effect of law for as long as it remains in effect.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-100">
          <num>417.100</num>
          <heading>Requirements for interstate compacts</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-100__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A compact entered into under ORS
417.095 must contain all of the following:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-100__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A provision making the compact available for joinder by all states.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-100__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A provision for withdrawal from the compact upon written notice to the parties
with a period of one year between the date of the notice and the effective date
of the withdrawal.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-100__subsec_1__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A requirement that, notwithstanding a state’s withdrawal from the compact, the
state shall continue to provide the protections afforded by the compact for the
duration of any adoption assistance agreement to all children and their
adoptive parents who, on the effective date of the state’s withdrawal, are
receiving adoption assistance from a state other than the residence state.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-100__subsec_1__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A requirement that:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="417-100__subsec_1__subsec_d__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Each instance of adoption assistance to which the compact applies be covered by
an adoption assistance agreement;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-100__subsec_1__subsec_d__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>An adoption assistance agreement be in writing and signed by the adoptive parents
and the child welfare agency of the state that undertakes to provide the
adoption assistance; and</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-100__subsec_1__subsec_d__subsec_C">
                <num>(C)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>An adoption assistance agreement is intended expressly for the benefit of the
adopted child and is enforceable by the adoptive parents and the state agency
providing the adoption assistance.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-100__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A compact entered into under ORS 417.095 may contain:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-100__subsec_2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Provisions necessary to administer the compact.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-100__subsec_2__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Provisions establishing procedures for and entitlement to medical and necessary
social services for a child when the child and the adoptive parents are living
in a state other than the state responsible for or providing the services or
the funds to pay part or all of the costs of the services.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-105">
          <num>417.105</num>
          <heading>Medical assistance identification document; penalty for false, misleading or fraudulent statement; rules</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-105__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Department of Human Services
shall issue a medical assistance identification document to a child who is
living in this state if the child:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-105__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Is the subject of an adoption assistance agreement with another state;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-105__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Is eligible for medical assistance in the other state; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-105__subsec_1__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Files with the department a certified copy of the adoption assistance agreement
obtained from the adoption assistance state.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-105__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department shall consider the holder of a medical assistance identification
document issued under this section to be the same as a holder of any other
medical assistance identification document issued under other laws of this
state. The department shall process and make payment on claims on behalf of the
holder in the same manner and subject to the same conditions and procedures as
for other recipients of medical assistance.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-105__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department shall provide coverage and benefits for a child who is in
another state and is covered by an adoption assistance agreement made by the
department if the coverage or benefits are not provided by the residence state.
The adoptive parent may submit to the department evidence of payment for
services or benefit amounts that are not payable in the residence state. The
department shall reimburse the adoptive parent for services and benefit amounts
covered by this state’s medical assistance program. However, the department may
not reimburse the adoptive parent for services or benefit amounts covered under
any insurance or other third-party medical contract or arrangement held by the
child or the adoptive parent. The additional services and benefit amounts
provided under this subsection are for services for which there is no federal contribution
toward the cost of the services, or for services for which there is a federal
contribution toward the cost of the services but the services are not provided
by the residence state.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-105__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <paragraph eId="417-105__subsec_4__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For purposes of subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-105__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section, the department by rule may
require the adoptive parents to show, at least annually, that the adoption
assistance agreement is in force.</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-105__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall adopt rules implementing subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-105__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section.
The department shall include in the rules procedures for obtaining prior
approval for services in those instances when approval is required for the
assistance.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-105__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A person who submits a false, misleading or fraudulent claim for payment or
reimbursement for services or benefits under this section, or makes a false,
misleading or fraudulent statement in connection therewith, commits a Class C
felony if the person knows or should know that the claim or statement is false,
misleading or fraudulent. [1999 c.859 s4]
INTERSTATE
COMPACT ON PLACEMENT OF CHILDREN</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-200">
          <num>417.200</num>
          <heading>Interstate Compact on Placement of Children</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-200__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The name, date and place of birth of the child.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-200__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The identity and address or addresses of the parents or legal guardian.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-200__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The name and address of the person, agency or institution to or with which the
sending agency proposes to send, bring, or place the child.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-200__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A full statement of the reasons for such proposed action and evidence of the
authority pursuant to which the placement is proposed to be made.</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-200__subsec_4__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Any public officer or agency in a receiving state which is in receipt of a
notice pursuant to paragraph</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-200__subsec_4__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this article may request of the sending
agency, or any other appropriate officer or agency of or in the sending agency’s
state, and shall be entitled to receive therefrom, such supporting or
additional information as it may deem necessary under the circumstances to
carry out the purpose and policy of this compact.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-200__subsec_4__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The child shall not be sent, brought, or caused to be sent or brought into the
receiving state until the appropriate public authorities in the receiving state
shall notify the sending agency, in writing, to the effect that the proposed
placement does not appear to be contrary to the interests of the child.
ARTICLE
IV
PENALTY
FOR ILLEGAL PLACEMENT
The
sending, bringing, or causing to be sent or brought into any receiving state of
a child in violation of the terms of this compact shall constitute a violation
of the laws respecting the placement of children of both the state in which the
sending agency is located or from which it sends or brings the child and of the
receiving state. Such violation may be punished or subjected to penalty in either
jurisdiction in accordance with its laws. In addition to liability for any such
punishment or penalty, any such violation shall constitute full and sufficient
grounds for the suspension or revocation of any license, permit, or other legal
authorization held by the sending agency which empowers or allows it to place,
or care for children.
ARTICLE
V
RETENTION
OF JURISDICTION</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-200__subsec_4__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The sending agency shall retain jurisdiction over the child sufficient to
determine all matters in relation to the custody, supervision, care, treatment
and disposition of the child which it would have had if the child had remained
in the sending agency’s state, until the child is adopted, reaches majority,
becomes self-supporting or is discharged with the concurrence of the appropriate
authority in the receiving state. Such jurisdiction shall also include the
power to effect or cause the return of the child or its transfer to another
location and custody pursuant to law. The sending agency shall continue to have
financial responsibility for support and maintenance of the child during the
period of the placement. Nothing contained herein shall defeat a claim of
jurisdiction by a receiving state sufficient to deal with an act of delinquency
or crime committed therein.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-200__subsec_4__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When the sending agency is a public agency, it may enter into an agreement with
an authorized public or private agency in the receiving state providing for the
performance of one or more services in respect of such case by the latter as
agent for the sending agency.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-200__subsec_4__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Nothing in this compact shall be construed to prevent a private charitable
agency authorized to place children in the receiving state from performing
services or acting as agent in that state for a private charitable agency of
the sending state; nor to prevent the agency in the receiving state from
discharging financial responsibility for the support and maintenance of a child
who has been placed on behalf of the sending agency without relieving the
responsibility set forth in paragraph</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-200__subsec_4__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>hereof.
ARTICLE
VI
INSTITUTIONAL
CARE
OF
DELINQUENT CHILDREN
A
child adjudicated delinquent may be placed in an institution in another party
jurisdiction pursuant to this compact but no such placement shall be made
unless the child is given a court hearing on notice to the parent or guardian
with opportunity to be heard, prior to being sent to such other party
jurisdiction for institutional care and the court finds that:</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-200__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Equivalent facilities for the child are not available in the sending agency’s
jurisdiction; and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-200__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Institutional care in the other jurisdiction is in the best interest of the
child and will not produce undue hardship.
ARTICLE
VII
COMPACT
ADMINISTRATOR
The
executive head of each jurisdiction party to this compact shall designate an
officer who shall be general coordinator of activities under this compact in
the jurisdiction of the officer and who, acting jointly with like officers of
other party jurisdictions, shall have power to promulgate rules and regulations
to carry out more effectively the terms and provisions of this compact.
ARTICLE
VIII
LIMITATIONS
This
compact shall not apply to:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-200__subsec_2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The sending or bringing of a child into a receiving state by a parent,
step-parent, grandparent, adult brother or sister, adult uncle or aunt, or guardian
and leaving the child with any such relative or nonagency guardian in the
receiving state.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-200__subsec_2__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Any placement, sending or bringing of a child into a receiving state pursuant
to any other interstate compact to which both the state from which the child is
sent or brought and the receiving state are party, or to any other agreement
between said states which has the force of law.
ARTICLE
IX
ENACTMENT
AND WITHDRAWAL
This
compact shall be open to joinder by any state, territory or possession of the
United States, the District of Columbia, Commonwealth of Puerto Rico, and, with
the consent of Congress, the Government of Canada or any province thereof. It
shall become effective with respect to any such jurisdiction when such
jurisdiction has enacted the same into law. Withdrawal from this compact shall
be by the enactment of a statute repealing the same, but shall not take effect
until two years after the effective date of such statute and until written
notice of the withdrawal has been given by the withdrawing state to the
Governor of each other party jurisdiction. Withdrawal of a party state shall
not affect the rights, duties and obligations under this compact of any sending
agency therein with respect to a placement made prior to the effective date of
withdrawal.
ARTICLE
X
CONSTRUCTION
AND SEVERABILITY
The
provisions of this compact shall be liberally construed to effectuate the
purposes thereof. The provisions of this compact shall be severable and if any
phrase, clause, sentence or provision of this compact is declared to be
contrary to the constitution of any party state or of the United States or the
applicability thereof to any government, agency, person or circumstance is held
invalid, the validity of the remainder of this compact and the applicability thereof
to any government, agency, person or circumstance shall not be affected
thereby. If this compact shall be held contrary to the constitution of any
state party thereto, the compact shall remain in full force and effect as to
the remaining states and in full force and effect </p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-210">
          <num>417.210</num>
          <heading>Financial responsibility for placed children</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-210__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Financial responsibility for
any child placed pursuant to the provisions of the Interstate Compact on the
Placement of Children shall be determined in accordance with the provisions of
Article V thereof in the first instance. However, in the event of partial or
complete default of performance thereunder, the provisions of ORS chapter 110
and any other applicable laws also may be invoked.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-210__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The “appropriate public authorities” as used in Article III of the Interstate
Compact on the Placement of Children shall, with reference to this state, mean
the Department of Human Services and the department shall receive and act with
reference to notices required by Article III thereof.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-210__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>As used in paragraph</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-210__subsec_3__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of Article V of the Interstate Compact on the
Placement of Children, the phrase “appropriate authority in the receiving state”
with reference to this state shall mean the Department of Human Services.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-220">
          <num>417.220</num>
          <heading>Agreements with other states; effect of financial provisions</heading>
          <content>
            <p>The officers and
agencies of this state and its subdivisions having authority to place children
are authorized to enter into agreements with appropriate officers or agencies
of or in other party states pursuant to paragraph (b) of Article V of the
Interstate Compact on the Placement of Children. Any such agreement which
contains a financial commitment or imposes a financial obligation on this state
or subdivision or agency thereof shall not be binding unless it has the
approval in writing of the State Treasurer in the case of the state and of the
chief local fiscal officer in the case of a subdivision of the state.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-230">
          <num>417.230</num>
          <heading>Compliance with visitation, inspection or supervision requirements</heading>
          <content>
            <p>Any requirements
for visitation, inspection or supervision of children, homes, institutions or
other agencies in another party state which may apply under ORS 418.250,
418.255 and 418.260 shall be considered to be met if performed pursuant to an
agreement entered into by appropriate officers or agencies of this state or a
subdivision thereof as contemplated by paragraph (b) of Article V of the
Interstate Compact on the Placement of Children.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-240">
          <num>417.240</num>
          <heading>Placement of children in institutions in other states</heading>
          <content>
            <p>Any court having
jurisdiction pursuant to ORS 419B.100 or 419C.005 to place children may place a
child in an institution in another state pursuant to Article VI of the
Interstate Compact on the Placement of Children and shall retain jurisdiction
as provided in Article V thereof.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-250">
          <num>417.250</num>
          <heading>“Executive head” defined</heading>
          <content>
            <p>As used in Article VII of the Interstate Compact on
the Placement of Children, the term “executive head” means the Governor. The
Governor is authorized to appoint a compact administrator in accordance with
the terms of said Article VII.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-260">
          <num>417.260</num>
          <heading>ORS 418.290 inapplicable to children placed pursuant to compact</heading>
          <content>
            <p>The provisions of
ORS 418.290 do not apply to a child placed or proposed to be placed in Oregon
pursuant to the Interstate Compact on the Placement of Children. Application of
the requirement contained in paragraph (d) of Article III of the Interstate
Compact on the Placement of Children shall be in lieu of the requirements of ORS
418.290. [1975 c.482 s7]
INTERCOUNTRY
ADOPTIONS</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-262">
          <num>417.262</num>
          <heading>Intercountry adoptions of children in custody of Department of Human Services; rules</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-262__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>As used in this section:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-262__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>“Convention” means the Convention on Protection of Children and Co-operation in
Respect of Intercountry Adoption, concluded May 29, 1993, and entered into
force for the United States on April 1, 2008.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-262__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>“Convention adoption” means the adoption of a child resident in a Convention
country by a United States citizen, or the adoption of a child resident in the
United States by an individual residing in a Convention country when, in
connection with the adoption, the child has moved or will move between the
United States and the Convention country.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-262__subsec_1__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>“Convention country” means a country that is a party to the Convention and with
which the Convention is in force for the United States.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-262__subsec_1__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>“Intercountry Adoption Act of 2000” means the Intercountry Adoption Act of
2000, 42 U.S.C. 14901 et seq.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-262__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>To the extent consistent with the Convention and the Intercountry Adoption Act
of 2000, the Department of Human Services shall establish rules, policies and
procedures to implement the Convention, the Intercountry Adoption Act of 2000
and any applicable federal laws or regulations governing Convention adoptions
with respect to any child who is the subject of a Convention adoption, if the
child is in the department’s custody pursuant to a court order under ORS
418.015 or ORS chapter 419B or 419C or other law of this state.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-265">
          <num>417.265</num>
          <heading>Department of Human Services to implement Convention adoptions; minimum requirements; exchange of reports</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-265__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>As used in this section:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-265__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>“Central Authority” means the entity designated by any Convention country as
such under Article 6</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-265__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of the Convention or, in the case of the United States,
the United States Department of State.</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-265__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>“Central Authority function” means any duty required to be carried out by a
Central Authority under the Convention or by an entity authorized to perform
Central Authority functions under the Convention.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-265__subsec_1__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>“Convention” means the Convention on Protection of Children and Co-operation in
Respect of Intercountry Adoption, concluded May 29, 1993, and entered into
force for the United States on April 1, 2008.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-265__subsec_1__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>“Convention adoption” means the adoption of a child resident in a Convention
country by a United States citizen, or the adoption of a child resident in the
United States by an individual residing in a Convention country when, in
connection with the adoption, the child has moved or will move between the
United States and the Convention country.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-265__subsec_1__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>“Convention country” means a country that is a party to the Convention and with
which the Convention is in force for the United States.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-265__subsec_1__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>“Foreign authorized entity” means a foreign Central Authority or foreign entity
authorized to perform Central Authority functions, other than a United States
authorized entity, in a Convention adoption case.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-265__subsec_1__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>“Intercountry Adoption Act of 2000” means the Intercountry Adoption Act of
2000, 42 U.S.C. 14901 et seq.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-265__subsec_1__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>“Outgoing Convention adoption” means a Convention adoption of a child in the
custody of the Department of Human Services by an individual residing in a
Convention country when, in connection with the adoption, the child has moved
or will be moving from the United States to the Convention country.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-265__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Department of Human Services shall work with the United States Department
of State to implement the Convention requirements for Convention adoptions.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-265__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>To the extent consistent with the Convention and the Intercountry Adoption Act
of 2000, the rules, policies and procedures adopted by the Department of Human
Services under this section must provide that the Department of Human Services
shall, in cooperation with a foreign authorized entity of another Convention
country:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-265__subsec_3__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Develop minimum requirements for the placement and supervision of a child who
is the subject of an outgoing Convention adoption.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-265__subsec_3__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Require the exchange and provision of appropriate written reports, including
but not limited to background and home studies, between the Department of Human
Services and the foreign authorized entity as necessary to meet the
requirements developed under paragraph</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-265__subsec_3__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this subsection.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-265__subsec_3__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Establish minimum requirements regarding visits:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="417-265__subsec_3__subsec_c__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>To the prospective adoptive parent’s home;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-265__subsec_3__subsec_c__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>With the child;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-265__subsec_3__subsec_c__subsec_C">
                <num>(C)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>With the prospective adoptive parents;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-265__subsec_3__subsec_c__subsec_D">
                <num>(D)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>With other persons living in the prospective adoptive parents’ home; and</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-265__subsec_3__subsec_c__subsec_E">
                <num>(E)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>With other persons who may have information about the child’s adoptive
placement. [2009 c.528 s1]
POLICIES
ON PROVIDING
SERVICES
TO CHILDREN
AND
FAMILIES</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-270">
          <num>417.270</num>
          <heading>Policy on equal access; documentation of expenditure for males and females; identification of disparities; equal access plan</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-270__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The
Legislative Assembly hereby acknowledges that females under 18 years of age
often lack equal access, both individually and as a group, when compared with
males under 18 years of age, to the facilities, services and treatment
available through human services and juvenile corrections programs provided by
or funded by the State of Oregon.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-270__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Legislative Assembly therefore declares that, as a matter of statewide
concern, it is in the best interests of the people of this state that equal
access for both males and females under 18 years of age to appropriate
facilities, services and treatment be available through all state agencies
providing or funding human services and juvenile corrections programs for
children and adolescents.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-270__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Recognizing this concern, the Legislative Assembly further declares that:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-270__subsec_3__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Any state administrative agency that regularly provides services to minors
shall, when the agency submits its annual budget to the Legislative Assembly,
specify the percentages of moneys allocated to, and expended for, the two
separate groups, males under 18 years of age and females under 18 years of age;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-270__subsec_3__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>All state agencies providing human services and juvenile corrections programs
shall identify existing disparities in the allocations of moneys and services
to, and expended for, the two groups, males under 18 years of age and females
under 18 years of age, and shall document such disparities, if any, for the
purpose of reporting the information to the next odd-numbered year regular
session of the Legislative Assembly; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-270__subsec_3__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The state agencies described in subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-270__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section shall:
(A)
Develop a plan to implement equal access to appropriate services and treatment,
based on presenting behaviors, for both males under 18 years of age and females
under 18 years of age, by January 1, 1995; and
(B)
Monitor the implementation and results of newly enacted legislation intended to
improve services for females under 18 years of age.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-270__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>As used in subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-270__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <paragraph eId="417-270__subsec_3__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this section, disparities include, but are not
limited to, disparities in:</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-270__subsec_3__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The nature, extent and effectiveness of services offered for females under 18
years of age within the areas of teen pregnancy, physical and sexual abuse,
alcohol and drug abuse, services offered for runaway and homeless females under
18 years of age and services offered for females under 18 years of age who are
involved in gangs or other delinquent activity; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-270__subsec_3__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The equity of services offered to at-risk children and youth with respect to
gender within the areas of physical and sexual abuse, alcohol and drug abuse
and services offered to runaway and homeless children and youth.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-280">
          <num>417.280</num>
          <heading>Victim services providers; placement at child welfare offices; coordination of services</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-280__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>As used in this section, “victim services provider” means a nonprofit
agency or program receiving moneys administered by the Department of Human
Services or the Department of Justice that offers safety planning, counseling,
support or advocacy to victims of domestic violence.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-280__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Department of Human Services may contract with local victim services
providers to place staff members from victim services providers at child
welfare offices for the purposes of allowing the staff members to divide their
time between the child welfare office and the staff member’s office to foster a
closer working relationship between the child welfare system and victim
services providers.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-280__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the department contracts with local victim services providers, the staff
members described in subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-280__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section shall:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-280__subsec_2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Provide in-depth safety planning, education, advocacy and continuing support to
adult victims of domestic violence who have children in the child welfare
system;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-280__subsec_2__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Receive referrals on cases that are closed at assessment; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-280__subsec_2__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Participate in case reviews and provide consultation to workers at the child
welfare office.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-280__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In addition to the services provided under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-280__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section,
staff members from victim services providers shall work with addiction and
recovery teams to help address co-occurrence of domestic violence and substance
abuse.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-280__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the department contracts with local victim services providers, the
department shall consult with victim services providers in creating policies
and protocols to coordinate the provision of services under this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-300">
          <num>417.300</num>
          <heading>Purpose of ORS 417.305</heading>
          <content>
            <p>The purpose of ORS 417.305 is to establish a state
policy for serving Oregon’s children and families, in recognition that
addressing the needs, strengths and assets of children necessarily requires
addressing the needs, strengths and assets of families and communities, and to
direct state agencies to work in partnership with local communities to plan,
coordinate and provide programs accordingly.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-305">
          <num>417.305</num>
          <heading>Legislative findings relating to serving children and families</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-305__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The
Legislative Assembly finds and declares that:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-305__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Children are our future;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-305__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Healthy children and families are of fundamental importance to the vitality of
Oregon;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-305__subsec_1__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Children are entitled to safety and health;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-305__subsec_1__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>All children deserve love, respect and guidelines for responsible behavior;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-305__subsec_1__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Families should be supported and strengthened;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-305__subsec_1__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Communities provide the context for healthy children and families, and strong
families and healthy communities are interdependent; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-305__subsec_1__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Economic opportunity and social cohesion are essential for healthy communities.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-305__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Legislative Assembly recognizes that demands on families, created in part
by changes in family structures and relationships, intensify the need for
Oregon to support children and families toward the goals of family stability
and broader access for children, youth and families to:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-305__subsec_2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The best possible physical and mental health;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-305__subsec_2__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Adequate food and safe physical shelter;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-305__subsec_2__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A safe and healthy environment;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-305__subsec_2__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The highest quality child care;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-305__subsec_2__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The highest quality of educational opportunity;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-305__subsec_2__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Quality education;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-305__subsec_2__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Effective training, apprenticeship and productive employment;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-305__subsec_2__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A range of civic, cultural, educational, family support and positive youth
development programs and activities that promote self-esteem, involvement and a
sense of community;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-305__subsec_2__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Community services that are efficient, coordinated and readily available; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-305__subsec_2__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Genuine participation in decisions concerning the planning and managing of
their lives and respect for such decisions.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-305__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the interest of ensuring coordination of all children and family services
and education programs provided by or funded by the state and the effective use
of state resources, the state shall:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-305__subsec_3__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Develop a plan for appropriating adequate funds;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-305__subsec_3__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Develop a cooperative partnership among state agencies that serve children,
youth and families;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-305__subsec_3__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Establish state priorities; develop and implement service standards that
reflect a balanced and comprehensive range of services for all children, youth
and families; monitor and evaluate services and ensure accessibility of
services for all children, youth and families; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-305__subsec_3__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Actively seek the advice of local governmental jurisdictions, providers of
services, educators, the private business sector, citizens and youth in
effecting this subsection.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-305__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Legislative Assembly finds that, in order to fulfill the purposes of this
section, service delivery systems for children and families shall include:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-305__subsec_4__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Cooperative partnerships among state agencies that serve children, youth and
families;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-305__subsec_4__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Methods of accountability to measure effectiveness of state-funded programs;
and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-305__subsec_4__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Use of public resources for programs and services that move the state toward
meeting the goals described in subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-305__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-340">
          <num>417.340</num>
          <heading>Definitions for ORS 417.340 to 417.349</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-340__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Child’s home” means the home in which a child resides with the child’s
biological or adoptive parents or legal guardian. It does not include foster
care, proctor care, group home placement or other institutional placement.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-340__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Family” means the unit that consists of:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-340__subsec_2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A member with a disability or chronic illness; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-340__subsec_2__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>One or more related persons who reside in the same household.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-340__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Family member with a disability or chronic illness” means a person who has a
disability or chronic illness that:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-340__subsec_3__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Is likely to continue indefinitely;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-340__subsec_3__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Results in substantial functional limitations in one or more of the following
areas of major life activity:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="417-340__subsec_3__subsec_b__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Self-care;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-340__subsec_3__subsec_b__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Receptive and expressive language;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-340__subsec_3__subsec_b__subsec_C">
                <num>(C)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Learning;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-340__subsec_3__subsec_b__subsec_D">
                <num>(D)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Mobility;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-340__subsec_3__subsec_b__subsec_E">
                <num>(E)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Self-direction;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-340__subsec_3__subsec_b__subsec_F">
                <num>(F)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Capacity for independent living; or</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-340__subsec_3__subsec_b__subsec_G">
                <num>(G)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Economic self-sufficiency; and</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-340__subsec_3__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Reflects the person’s need for special, interdisciplinary or generic care,
treatment or other services that are of lifelong duration and must be
individually planned and coordinated.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-340__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Medically involved” means having a physical or developmental disability that
requires assistance with most activities of daily living and requires health
and personal care throughout the day and night.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-342">
          <num>417.342</num>
          <heading>Family support services; principles</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-342__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Family support services are based on
the belief that all people, regardless of disability, chronic illness or
special need, have the right to a permanent and stable familial relationship in
the community. Children have a developmental need to grow up in a family home
environment. However, nothing in ORS 417.340 to 417.348 or 417.349 is intended
to require any person with a disability or chronic illness to live in the
family home.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-342__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Family support services can provide the support necessary to enable the family
to meet the needs of caring for a family member with a disability or chronic
illness at home and, subject to available funds, shall be based on the
following principles:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-342__subsec_2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Family support services may use private and volunteer resources, publicly
funded services and other flexible dollars to provide a family with the
services needed to care for the family member with a disability or chronic
illness.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-342__subsec_2__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Family support services must be sensitive to the unique needs, strengths and
multicultural values of an individual and the family rather than fitting the
individual and family into existing services.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-342__subsec_2__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Family support services must be built on a relationship of respect and trust
that recognizes that families are better able to determine their own needs than
have their needs determined by the state or a public agency.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-342__subsec_2__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Family support services shall be provided in a manner that develops
comprehensive, responsive and flexible support to families in their role as
primary caregivers for family members with disabilities or chronic illnesses.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-342__subsec_2__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Family support services shall focus on the entire family and be responsive to
the needs of the individual and the family.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-342__subsec_2__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Family support services may be needed throughout the lifespan of the individual
family member living at home who has a disability or chronic illness.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-342__subsec_2__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Family support services shall be available to families before they are in
crisis.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-342__subsec_2__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Family support services may be a service option offered to families, but not
imposed on them.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-342__subsec_2__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Family support services shall encourage maximum use of existing social networks
and natural sources of support and should encourage community integration.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-342__subsec_2__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Family support services shall not be confined to a single program or set of
services but shall be a philosophy that permeates all programs and services.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-344">
          <num>417.344</num>
          <heading>Types of services included</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-344__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Family support consultation;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-344__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Information and referral;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-344__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Financial assistance;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-344__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Emergency and outreach services; and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-344__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Individual and family centered assistance, including but not limited to:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-344__subsec_5__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Purchase of special equipment;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-344__subsec_5__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Respite care;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-344__subsec_5__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Recreation;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-344__subsec_5__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Transportation;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-344__subsec_5__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Special dietary needs;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-344__subsec_5__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Dependent care;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-344__subsec_5__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Medical services;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-344__subsec_5__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Housing modification;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-344__subsec_5__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Counseling; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-344__subsec_5__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Support groups.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-345">
          <num>417.345</num>
          <heading>Medically Involved Home-Care Program; services; enrollment; effect of program on funding for certain programs; rules</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-345__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Medically Involved Home-Care
Program is created in the Department of Human Services. The department shall
provide all State Plan Medicaid and waivered services available under state and
federal law that are necessary to enable a medically involved child to be cared
for in the child’s home. The waivered services that must be available include
but are not limited to home nursing care, durable medical equipment and respite
care.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-345__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department shall adopt by rule criteria for determining the need for and
extent of assistance to be provided to a medically involved child enrolled in
the Medically Involved Home-Care Program created by subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-345__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this
section. The criteria shall include, but are not limited to, consideration of:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-345__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The medical needs of the child;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-345__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The needs of any other family member with a disability or chronic illness in
the child’s home;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-345__subsec_1__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Family and community support available to the child and family caregivers; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-345__subsec_1__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The assistance necessary for the family to care for the child in the child’s
home, disregarding parental or legal guardian income.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-345__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to limits on enrollment required by state or federal law, services
offered through the Medically Involved Home-Care Program shall be made
available to children meeting the criteria established by the department by
rule. Priority for enrollment shall be given to:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-345__subsec_3__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A child transferring to the child’s home from nursing home placement, foster
care placement or other out-of-home placement;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-345__subsec_3__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A child living at home who is at risk of nursing home placement, foster care
placement or other out-of-home placement;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-345__subsec_3__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A child who does not otherwise qualify for medical assistance under ORS chapter
414 and for whom the department pays family support payments pursuant to ORS
430.215 that exceed $10,000 per year; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-345__subsec_3__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A child who is at risk of losing eligibility for medical assistance under ORS
chapter 414 due to a caregiver’s employment or an increase in a caregiver’s
earnings.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-345__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department shall enroll no fewer than 125 medically involved children in
the Medically Involved Home-Care Program beginning January 1, 2008. The
department shall enroll an additional 25 medically involved children each
calendar year thereafter, to the maximum number allowed by federal law or under
the terms of the federal approval.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-345__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Moneys appropriated to the department for the Medically Involved Home-Care
Program may not be used to supplant moneys appropriated to the department for
the Children’s Intensive In-Home Services program.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-345__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>As used in this section, “child” means a person under 18 years of age.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-346">
          <num>417.346</num>
          <heading>Duties of Director of Human Services; rules</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-346__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Identify current programs and potential resources available to families
providing care for a family member with a disability or chronic illness.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-346__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Develop a biennial plan for adequate funding and recommend budgetary priorities
for family support services.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-346__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Develop a biennial cooperative plan for assuring a statewide interagency system
of family support services.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-346__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Adopt rules for family support services that are guided by the goals and
principles set forth in ORS 417.340 to 417.348. These rules shall contain a grievance
procedure.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-346__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Make a biennial report to the Legislative Assembly on the state of the family
support system, including strengths, deficiencies, cost savings and
recommendations. This report shall include a comprehensive statement of the
efforts of the Department of Human Services to carry out the policies and
principles set forth in this legislation. The report shall include but not be
limited to a list of family support services, a summary of costs and the number
of clients served.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-346__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Establish a Family Support Advisory Council whose purpose is to review and
comment on plans and services provided or contracted for family support by
state agencies and advise the director on the state plans for coordinated
family support services.</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-346__subsec_6__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The council shall meet a minimum of four times per year.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-346__subsec_6__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The membership of the council shall be 51 percent consumers of family support
services.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-346__subsec_6__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The remaining membership shall be composed of representatives of agencies
providing family support services and representatives of advocacy groups. One
member shall be a representative of the Department of Education.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-348">
          <num>417.348</num>
          <heading>Eligibility requirements</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-348__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The family has a family member requiring long term care due to disability or
chronic illness whom the family desires to keep at home or return to the home
from an institution or other out-of-home placement.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-348__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The family desires to care for the dependent family member at home if
financial, physical or other barriers are reduced or eliminated and adequate
community based support services are provided.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-348__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The family is caring for a family member who is waiting for residential or
vocational services.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-348__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Other requirements established by the Department of Human Services. The
requirements must be reviewed by the Family Support Advisory Council.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-349">
          <num>417.349</num>
          <heading>Department of Human Services to provide family support services</heading>
          <content>
            <p>In accordance
with ORS 417.342 and 417.344, the Department of Human Services shall provide
family support services throughout the department. Notwithstanding ORS 430.640
and 430.662, the department may contract directly with community organizations
for the provision of family support services.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-350">
          <num>417.350</num>
          <heading>Family support services as social benefits</heading>
          <content>
            <p>Funds, goods and services provided
to families under ORS 417.340 to 417.348 are social benefits for the promotion
of general welfare. The benefits may not be used to replace or reduce other
state or federal benefits provided the families under Oregon law.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-351">
          <num>417.351</num>
          <heading>Regional family support networks</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-351__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In addition to the family support
services and goods provided under ORS 417.340 to 417.348 and 417.349, the
Department of Human Services shall establish and maintain regional family support
networks to provide peer-delivered supports for families of individuals with
intellectual or developmental disabilities.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-351__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department shall make the services provided through regional family support
networks under this section available to families of individuals who are
currently receiving or at risk of requiring developmental disability services,
as defined in ORS 427.101.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-351__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding ORS 430.662, the department may contract directly with
community organizations for the provision of regional family support network
services.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-352">
          <num>417.352</num>
          <heading>Department to compile lists of providers; assistance to parents in obtaining services</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-352__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Department of Human Services, directly or through its contracting
agencies, shall compile and maintain lists of providers who are qualified to
provide home and community-based services to children in each community. The
department, or its contracting agencies, shall make the list of local providers
available to residents in each community.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-352__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department or its contracting agencies shall assist a parent in obtaining
home and community-based services for the parent’s child if:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-352__subsec_2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The parent resides in Oregon;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-352__subsec_2__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The parent has a child who does not reside in Oregon but who visits the parent
in Oregon for at least six weeks each year; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-352__subsec_2__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The child qualifies for home and community-based services under 42 U.S.C.
1396n</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-352__subsec_2__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-352__subsec_2__subsec_k">
              <num>(k)</num>
              <content>
                <p>in the child’s state of residence.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-352__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The assistance provided under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-352__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section includes:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-352__subsec_2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Providing the parent with the list of local providers;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-352__subsec_2__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Contacting the state Medicaid agency in the child’s state of residence to
facilitate payment for the home and community-based services; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-352__subsec_2__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Assisting the parent in providing any documentation required by the child’s
state of residence.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-355">
          <num>417.355</num>
          <heading>Principles of family law system</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-355__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The welfare of children shall be paramount in the resolution of family
conflicts.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-355__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Children must learn to develop healthy relationships and to resolve conflicts
in peaceful ways.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-355__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Whenever possible and appropriate, children shall continue to have both parents
in their lives and parents shall be encouraged to work out agreements between
themselves regarding their children.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-355__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The safety and economic well-being of family members shall be given priority.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-355__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Family members in conflict must have appropriate forums in which to grieve and
accept change.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-355__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All families deserve respect and the support of social policy. [1995 c.800 s1]
FAMILY-
OR CLIENT-CENTERED SERVICE SYSTEM</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-360">
          <num>417.360</num>
          <heading>Findings and policy</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-360__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Legislative Assembly finds that:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-360__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The current delivery system for human services is fragmented and uncoordinated,
producing service duplication and inappropriate or inadequate responses to
individuals and to families;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-360__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Clients with multiple needs must interact with a variety of agencies and
frequently feel powerless to negotiate the complicated array of services;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-360__subsec_1__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The system is too often perceived as victimizing the persons it is intended to
serve;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-360__subsec_1__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Dedicated direct service workers become the target of disillusionment by
clients even though the workers are equally frustrated by their lack of control
over bureaucratic requirements; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-360__subsec_1__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The state needs to rethink and restructure traditional methods of delivering
human services. Organizations that have traditionally not viewed themselves as
partners, such as social services and education, must be strongly encouraged to
integrate their programs.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-360__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall be the policy of this state to foster a family-or client-centered service
delivery system at the community level with the goal of providing more
efficient and responsive services, driven by the needs of the individuals and
families served and not by funding tied to traditional, categorical programs.
Family services available through community level delivery systems should
include, but need not be limited to, education, information and referral
services.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-362">
          <num>417.362</num>
          <heading>System requirements</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-362__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Insures active participation of clients in service planning, decision making
and service delivery;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-362__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Empowers direct service workers to gain access to a broad continuum of services
and flexible funding to meet the needs of individuals and families served;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-362__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Pools funds of multiple service delivery agencies;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-362__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Generates policies for program planning and implementation at the community
level rather than mandating policies at the state level; and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-362__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Supports and enhances family harmony with the goal of preserving the health and
integrity of all family units.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-365">
          <num>417.365</num>
          <heading>“Family decision-making meeting” defined for ORS 417.365 to 417.375</heading>
          <content>
            <p>As used in ORS
417.365 to 417.375, “family decision-making meeting” means a family-focused
intervention facilitated by professional staff that is designed to build and
strengthen the natural caregiving system for the child. Family decision-making
meetings may include family group conferences, family unity meetings, family
mediation or other professionally recognized interventions that include
extended family and rely upon the family to make decisions about planning for
its children. The purpose of the family decision-making meeting is to establish
a plan that provides for the safety, attachment and permanency needs of the
child.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-368">
          <num>417.368</num>
          <heading>Consideration of meeting required for certain cases</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-368__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The
Department of Human Services shall consider the use of a family decision-making
meeting in each case in which a child is placed in substitute care for more
than 30 days.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-368__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When the department determines that the use of a family decision-making meeting
is appropriate, the meeting shall be held, whenever possible, before the child
has been in substitute care for 60 days.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-368__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the department elects not to conduct a family decision-making meeting, the
reasons for that decision shall be clearly documented in the written service
plan of the child developed by the department.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-371">
          <num>417.371</num>
          <heading>Notice to family members of meeting</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-371__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the Department of Human Services
determines that the use of a family decision-making meeting is appropriate, the
department shall conduct and document reasonable inquiries to promptly locate
and notify the parents, grandparents and any other family member who has had
significant, direct contact with the child in the year prior to the substitute
care placement.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-371__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All family members notified by the department may attend the meeting unless the
department determines that the safety of any attendee will be compromised by
the attendance of any family member.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-371__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any family member the department deems a safety risk may provide written
statements that address the subject of any family decision-making meeting,
including the determination of placement of the child or components of a
service plan for the child and family members.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-371__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>As used in this section:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-371__subsec_4__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>“Family member” means any person related to the child by blood, marriage or
adoption, including but not limited to parents, grandparents, stepparents,
aunts, uncles, sisters, brothers, cousins or great-grandparents. “Family member”
also includes a child 12 years of age or older, or a child younger than 12
years of age when appropriate.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-371__subsec_4__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>“Reasonable inquiries” means efforts that involve reviewing the case file for
relevant information, contacting the parents or guardians and contacting
additional sources of information that may lead to ascertaining the whereabouts
of family members, if necessary.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-375">
          <num>417.375</num>
          <heading>Development of family plan; contents</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-375__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the Department of Human Services
conducts a family decision-making meeting under ORS 417.365 to 417.375, the
meeting shall result in the development of a written family plan that may
include a primary permanent plan, concurrent permanent plan, placement
recommendations and service recommendations. The family plan or service
agreement shall also include:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-375__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The expectations of the parents of the child and other family members;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-375__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Services the department will provide;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-375__subsec_1__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Timelines for implementation of the plan;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-375__subsec_1__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The benefits of compliance with the plan;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-375__subsec_1__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The consequences of noncompliance with the plan; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-375__subsec_1__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A schedule of subsequent meetings, if appropriate.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-375__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any family member participating in a family decision-making meeting shall sign
a written acknowledgment of the content of the family plan developed at the
family decision-making meeting and their attendance at the meeting.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-375__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department shall incorporate the family plan developed at the family
decision-making meeting into the department’s service plan for the child to the
extent that the family plan protects the child, builds on family strengths and
is focused on achieving permanency for the child within a reasonable time.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-375__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the family plan is not incorporated in the department’s service plan for the
child, the department shall document the reasons in the service plan.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-375__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department shall send a copy of the family plan to the family participants,
including those family members who participated in writing pursuant to ORS
417.371</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-375__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>, no later than 21 days after the conclusion of the family
decision-making meeting.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-705">
          <num>417.705</num>
          <heading>Definitions for ORS 417.705 to 417.800</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-705__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Early Learning Hub” means an entity designated under ORS 417.827.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-705__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Outcome” means the measure of a desired result.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-705__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Services for children and families” does not include services provided by the
Department of Education or school districts that are related to curriculum or
instructional programs.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-705__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Target” means a specific level of achievement desired for a specific time,
expressed numerically.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-707">
          <num>417.707</num>
          <heading>Duty of state agencies providing services for children and families</heading>
          <content>
            <p>The purpose of
ORS 417.705 to 417.800, as described in ORS 417.708 to 417.725, shall be
implemented by all state agencies providing services for children and families
to guide the providing of those services. [Formerly 417.755; 2012 c.97 s20]</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-708">
          <num>417.708</num>
          <heading>Legislative findings relating to young children</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-708__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The first three years of life are a crucial period in a child’s life, and
during this period a child is sensitive to the protective mechanisms of
parental and family support.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-708__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Brain development that takes place during the first year of life is rapid and
extensive and has implications for lifelong physical, social-emotional and
cognitive well-being.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-710">
          <num>417.710</num>
          <heading>Statement of purpose</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-710__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Authorize the Early Learning Council to set statewide guidelines for the
planning, coordination and delivery of services for children and families in
conjunction with other state agencies and other planning bodies;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-710__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Vest in Early Learning Hubs the authority to distribute state and federal
funds, to coordinate services and to purchase services for children and families
in the local area;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-710__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Provide a process for providing local services that are consistent with
statewide guidelines;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-710__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Retain in the state the responsibility for funding of services for children and
families through a combination of local, state and federal funding, including
the leveraging of public and private funds available under ORS 417.705 to
417.800; and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-710__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Retain state supervision of child protection and other services that should be
uniform throughout the state and that are necessarily the state’s
responsibility.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-715">
          <num>417.715</num>
          <heading>Policy; service system values and goals</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-715__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It is the intent of the Legislative
Assembly to enable families and communities to protect, nurture and realize the
full physical, social, emotional, cognitive and cultural developmental
potential of children in Oregon. Toward this end, the Legislative Assembly
shall develop and implement a statewide system of services that is preventive,
integrated in local communities and accessible to children and families and
that focuses on promoting the wellness of Oregon’s children.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-715__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The service system shall be based on promoting the wellness of Oregon’s
children and families. The following values shall guide the design and
implementation of this system:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-715__subsec_2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A commitment to children that ranks them as Oregon’s first priority;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-715__subsec_2__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A commitment to reducing the number of Oregon’s children and families living in
poverty;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-715__subsec_2__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A commitment to equitable treatment of gender in both services and funding;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-715__subsec_2__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A view that strengthening families is of paramount concern, but that child
safety must come first if a conflict between the well-being of a child and the
well-being of a family arises;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-715__subsec_2__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A recognition of the central role of families as the best place for children to
develop;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-715__subsec_2__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A realization that good parenting skills are fundamental to a healthy society;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-715__subsec_2__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A sensitivity to diversity that requires culturally competent services
respectful of genders, cultures, orientations and disabilities;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-715__subsec_2__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An offering of opportunities for children to develop self-worth and concern for
others, and to reach their full potential;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-715__subsec_2__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A fundamental assumption that children should be provided the means to attain
safety and good health; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-715__subsec_2__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A commitment to early detection and treatment of families at risk for child
abuse and neglect.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-715__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The service system shall emphasize:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-715__subsec_3__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Services designed to identify risks and nurture potential at the earliest time
in a child’s life;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-715__subsec_3__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Services designed to respond to and reduce risks at the earliest possible point
of detection;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-715__subsec_3__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A comprehensive continuum of services such as prevention, early intervention
and treatment for children in all age groups;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-715__subsec_3__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The realization that funding one age group or gender of children at the expense
of another is destructive of the wellness of children; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-715__subsec_3__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>That maintenance and enhancement of treatment services and augmentation of
preventive services are paramount to the effective delivery of services to
children and families.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-715__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The service system must begin at the local level, through cooperation and
integration of all local and state providers, treat the whole person and be
built on the strengths and natural supports of neighborhoods and communities.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-720">
          <num>417.720</num>
          <heading>Characteristics of service system</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-720__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Is nonstigmatizing;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-720__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Is available and accessible when needed and is based on the perspective of
children and families and, whenever possible, allows families to design their
own service programs, based on assessment of their needs and their solutions
and resources for change;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-720__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Is outcome-oriented;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-720__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Is integrated;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-720__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Recognizes the contributions of the system’s workers;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-720__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Promotes in the community a sense of responsibility for self and others and is
committed to the well-being of children as well as support for families;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-720__subsec_7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Emphasizes local planning for children and families and integrates local needs
with statewide goals;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-720__subsec_8">
            <num>(8)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Provides services locally in a process that encourages partnerships, alliances
and efficient use of resources; and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-720__subsec_9">
            <num>(9)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Provides local service delivery systems that build on the unique strengths of
the county or community.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-721">
          <num>417.721</num>
          <heading>Collaboration with coordinated care organizations</heading>
          <content>
            <p>The Oregon Health
Authority, the Health Plan Quality Metrics Committee and the Early Learning
Council shall work collaboratively with coordinated care organizations to
develop performance metrics for prenatal care, delivery and infant care that
align with early learning outcomes. [2013 c.728 s8; 2015 c.389 s12]
Note: 417.721 and
417.723 were enacted into law by the Legislative Assembly but were not added to
or made a part of ORS chapter 417 or any series therein by legislative action.
See Preface to Oregon Revised Statutes for further explanation.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-723">
          <num>417.723</num>
          <heading>Grant program to support alignment of systems</heading>
          <content>
            <p>The Oregon Health
Authority and the Early Learning Council shall establish a grant program to
provide funding to support effective and scalable strategies that align
statewide early learning systems and health systems for the purpose of
improving the developmental outcomes for children from zero through three years
of age. [2013 c.728 s9; 2021 c.631 s2]
Note: See note under
417.721.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-725">
          <num>417.725</num>
          <heading>Key elements of system; family resource and community learning centers</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-725__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Key elements
of the service system developed and implemented under ORS 417.705 to 417.800
are:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-725__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A two-to-seven-year incremental implementation process with measurable
outcomes;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-725__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An implementation process resulting in a voluntary system based on nurturing
human development; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-725__subsec_1__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A service continuum based on promoting wellness for the children of Oregon
whose parents have given their express written consent. Family resource centers
and community learning centers as defined in ORS 329.007 are a viable, but not
the exclusive, structure for delivering a service continuum.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-725__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If a system of family resource centers and community learning centers is
selected by an Early Learning Hub to deliver services, the centers:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-725__subsec_2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>May serve as the prevention arm of the voluntary delivery system and may link
and integrate neighborhood-based services with the intent that services be
available to all families who have given their express written consent to
promote their children’s wellness;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-725__subsec_2__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Shall involve parents in the care and education of their children;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-725__subsec_2__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Shall involve the local community in developing and overseeing family resource
center programs and community learning center programs; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-725__subsec_2__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Shall incorporate the requirements specified for community learning centers
under ORS 329.156.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-727">
          <num>417.727</num>
          <heading>Oregon Early Learning System</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-727__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Prevent child abuse and neglect;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-727__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Improve the health and development of young children;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-727__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Promote bonding and attachment in the early years of a child’s life;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-727__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Support parents in providing the optimum environment for their young children;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-727__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Link and integrate services and supports in the statewide early learning system
pursuant to ORS 417.728;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-727__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Ensure that children are entering school ready to learn; and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-727__subsec_7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Ensure that parents have access to affordable, quality child care.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-728">
          <num>417.728</num>
          <heading>Statewide early learning system; components; rules</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-728__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Early
Learning Council is responsible for leading cross-sector strategic planning
that establishes the goals, objectives and strategies necessary for a statewide
early learning system.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-728__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The purpose of the statewide early learning system is to make progress toward
ensuring that:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-728__subsec_2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Children enter school ready to learn;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-728__subsec_2__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Children are raised in families that are healthy, stable and attached; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-728__subsec_2__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Early learning is available and provided in a manner that is aligned,
coordinated and family centered.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-728__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The statewide early learning system shall include the following components:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-728__subsec_3__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A process to identify as early as possible children and families who would
benefit from early learning services, including the required use of
standardized screening and referral procedures used throughout the statewide
early learning system;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-728__subsec_3__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A plan to support the identified needs of the child and family that coordinates
case management personnel and the delivery of services to the child and family;
and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-728__subsec_3__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Services to support children who are zero through six years of age and their
families who give their express written consent, including:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="417-728__subsec_3__subsec_c__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Screening, assessment and home visiting services pursuant to ORS 417.795;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-728__subsec_3__subsec_c__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Specialized or targeted home visiting services;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-728__subsec_3__subsec_c__subsec_C">
                <num>(C)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Community-based services such as relief nurseries, family support programs and
parent education programs;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-728__subsec_3__subsec_c__subsec_D">
                <num>(D)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Affordable, quality child care, as defined by the Early Learning Council;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-728__subsec_3__subsec_c__subsec_E">
                <num>(E)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Preschool and other early education services;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-728__subsec_3__subsec_c__subsec_F">
                <num>(F)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Health services for children and pregnant women;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-728__subsec_3__subsec_c__subsec_G">
                <num>(G)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Mental health services;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-728__subsec_3__subsec_c__subsec_H">
                <num>(H)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Alcohol and drug treatment programs that meet the standards promulgated by the
Oregon Health Authority pursuant to ORS 430.357;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-728__subsec_3__subsec_c__subsec_I">
                <num>(I)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Developmental disability services; and</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-728__subsec_3__subsec_c__subsec_J">
                <num>(J)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Other state and local services.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-728__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In establishing the definition of affordable, quality child care under
subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-728__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <paragraph eId="417-728__subsec_3__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <subparagraph eId="417-728__subsec_3__subsec_c__subsec_D">
                <num>(D)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>of this section, the Early Learning Council shall consult
with child care providers and early childhood educators. The definition
established by the council shall support parental choice of child care provider
and shall consider differences in settings and services, including but not
limited to child care for school-aged children, part-time care, odd-hour and
respite care and factors of cultural appropriateness and competence.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-728__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Early Learning Council shall:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-728__subsec_5__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Consolidate administrative functions relating to the statewide early learning
system, to the extent practicable, including but not limited to training and
technical assistance, planning and budgeting.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-728__subsec_5__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Adopt policies to establish training and technical assistance programs to
ensure that personnel have skills in appropriate areas, including screening,
family assessment, competency-based home visiting skills, cultural and gender
differences and other areas as needed.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-728__subsec_5__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Identify research-based age-appropriate and culturally and gender appropriate
screening and assessment tools that would be used as appropriate in programs
and services of the statewide early learning system.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-728__subsec_5__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Develop a plan for the implementation of a common data system for voluntary
early childhood programs.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-728__subsec_5__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Coordinate existing and new early childhood programs to provide a range of
community-based supports.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-728__subsec_5__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Establish a common set of quality assurance standards to guide local
implementation of all elements of the statewide early learning system,
including voluntary universal screening and assessment, home visiting,
staffing, evaluation and community-based services.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-728__subsec_5__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Ensure that all plans for voluntary early childhood services are coordinated
and consistent with federal and state law, including but not limited to plans
for the Oregon Prenatal to Kindergarten Program, federal Head Start programs,
early childhood special education services, early intervention services and
public health services.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-728__subsec_5__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Identify how the statewide early learning system for children who are zero
through six years of age will link with systems of support for older children
and their families.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-728__subsec_5__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>During January of each odd-numbered year, report to the Governor and the
Legislative Assembly on the statewide early learning system.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-728__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Board of Education, the Employment Department, the Department of
Human Services and the Oregon Health Authority when adopting rules to
administer voluntary early childhood programs under their individual authority
shall adopt rules:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-728__subsec_6__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>That are consistent with the requirements of the statewide early learning
system created under this section; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-728__subsec_6__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>With the direction of the Early Learning Council.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-728__subsec_7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Information gathered in conjunction with the voluntary comprehensive screening
and assessment of children and their families may be used only for the
following purposes:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-728__subsec_7__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Providing services to children and families who give their express written
consent;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-728__subsec_7__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Providing statistical data that are not personally identifiable;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-728__subsec_7__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Accomplishing other purposes for which the family has given express written
consent; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-728__subsec_7__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Meeting the requirements of mandatory state and federal disclosure laws. [Formerly
417.748; 2003 c.293 s2; 2005 c.271 s2; 2009 c.595 s359; 2012 c.37 ss44b,91;
2013 c.728 ss3,4; 2015 c.698 s3; 2021 c.631 s1; 2023 c.547 s27]</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-781">
          <num>417.781</num>
          <heading>Early Childhood Equity Fund</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-781__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Early Childhood Equity Fund is
established in the State Treasury, separate and distinct from the General Fund.
Moneys in the Early Childhood Equity Fund are continuously appropriated to the
Department of Early Learning and Care to make grants under ORS 417.782 to
culturally specific early learning, early childhood and parent support programs
and to promote the capacity of culturally specific organizations to deliver
these programs.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-781__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The fund shall consist of:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-781__subsec_2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Moneys appropriated or otherwise transferred to the fund from the Legislative
Assembly;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-781__subsec_2__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Earnings received on moneys in the fund; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-781__subsec_2__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Other amounts deposited into the fund from any source. [2019 c.122 s53; 2021
c.631 s48]
Note: 417.781 and
417.782 were enacted into law by the Legislative Assembly but were not added to
or made a part of ORS chapter 417 or any series therein by legislative action.
See Preface to Oregon Revised Statutes for further explanation.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-782">
          <num>417.782</num>
          <heading>Early childhood support grant program; rules</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-782__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Department of Early
Learning and Care may make grants from the Early Childhood Equity Fund established
under ORS 417.781 to culturally specific early learning, early childhood and
parent support programs in this state that build capacity in communities,
ensure children start kindergarten ready to succeed and support families to be
stable, healthy and attached. For purposes of this subsection, a program is in
this state if the program serves communities within the geographic boundaries
of this state, including communities within Indian country of a federally
recognized Oregon Indian tribe that is within the geographic boundaries of this
state.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-782__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>To receive a grant under this section, a program must:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-782__subsec_2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Provide outreach, support and resources to children and families who are at
risk because of any combination of two or more factors, including their race,
ethnicity, English language proficiency, socioeconomic status and geographic
location; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-782__subsec_2__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Demonstrate a proven ability to provide outreach, support and resources to
children and families described in paragraph</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-782__subsec_2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this subsection.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-782__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department shall monitor capacity needs and provide technical assistance to
grantees.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-782__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department shall conduct a biennial evaluation of programs that receive
grants under this section. The evaluation shall include measurement of outcomes
that align with:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-782__subsec_4__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Current research regarding positive child and family indicators, including
family stability and early childhood school readiness; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-782__subsec_4__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Culturally specific approaches.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-782__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Early Learning Council, in consultation with the department, shall adopt
rules necessary to carry out the provisions of this section. The rules shall
include requirements for grant eligibility under this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-782__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>On or before September 15 of each odd-numbered year, the department shall
submit to the interim committees of the Legislative Assembly related to early
childhood and child welfare a report on the status and impact of grants made to
programs under this section. The report shall include changes in the capacity
of culturally specific organizations and the results of any biennial
evaluations conducted in accordance with subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-782__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section. [2019
c.122 s54; 2021 c.631 s49]
Note: See note under
417.781.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-784">
          <num>417.784</num>
          <heading>Infant and toddler care program</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-784__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>As used in this section:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-784__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>“Local entity” includes:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="417-784__subsec_1__subsec_a__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>An Early Learning Hub designated under ORS 417.827;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-784__subsec_1__subsec_a__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>A resource and referral entity;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-784__subsec_1__subsec_a__subsec_C">
                <num>(C)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>An education service district;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-784__subsec_1__subsec_a__subsec_D">
                <num>(D)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>A federal Head Start program;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-784__subsec_1__subsec_a__subsec_E">
                <num>(E)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>A community-based organization; or</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-784__subsec_1__subsec_a__subsec_F">
                <num>(F)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Any entity identified by the Department of Early Learning and Care.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-784__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>“Provider” means a provider of infant and toddler care.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-784__subsec_1__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>“Resource and referral entity” means a resource and referral entity established
under ORS 329A.100 to 329A.135.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-784__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Department of Early Learning and Care shall administer an infant and
toddler care program to improve access to high quality infant and toddler care
for families whose incomes, at the time of enrollment, are at or below 200
percent of the federal poverty guidelines.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-784__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <paragraph eId="417-784__subsec_3__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Each biennium, each Early Learning Hub, in consultation with resource and
referral entities, shall complete a community plan. The plan must include the
following for the region served by the Early Learning Hub:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="417-784__subsec_3__subsec_a__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Identification of priority populations of children and families to enroll in
the program;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-784__subsec_3__subsec_a__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Assessment of the availability of high-quality infant and toddler care;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-784__subsec_3__subsec_a__subsec_C">
                <num>(C)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Identification of existing providers and opportunities to increase the number
and enrollment capacity of providers;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-784__subsec_3__subsec_a__subsec_D">
                <num>(D)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Prioritization of local entities to serve as providers based on community need
and enrollment capacity;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-784__subsec_3__subsec_a__subsec_E">
                <num>(E)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Identification of methods for increasing the enrollment capacity of providers
and for providing professional development to providers; and</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-784__subsec_3__subsec_a__subsec_F">
                <num>(F)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Identification of other services related to infant and toddler care.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-784__subsec_3__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>After completing a community plan described in paragraph</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-784__subsec_3__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this
subsection, an Early Learning Hub shall submit the plan to the department for
approval based on rules adopted by the Early Learning Council.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-784__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <paragraph eId="417-784__subsec_4__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall contract with resource and referral entities to recruit
eligible providers to participate in the infant and toddler care program
established under this section.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-784__subsec_4__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To be eligible to participate in the program, a provider must demonstrate a
commitment and ability to:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="417-784__subsec_4__subsec_b__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Address the needs identified in the community plan approved by the department
under subsection</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-784__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section;
(B)
Provide care to infants and toddlers;
(C)
Serve families whose incomes, at the time of enrollment, are at or below 200
percent of the federal poverty guidelines; and
(D)
Serve families who otherwise meet criteria established by the Early Learning
Council by rule.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-784__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <paragraph eId="417-784__subsec_5__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall identify a local entity within each Early Learning Hub
region that shall be responsible for awarding grants and contracts to providers
who meet the eligibility criteria established under subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-784__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this
section.</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-784__subsec_4__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Before a provider may be awarded a grant or contract under this section, the
provider must agree to participate in any quality improvement and professional
development activities necessary to meet the standards established by the
department.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-784__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Resource and referral entities shall:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-784__subsec_6__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In consultation with each provider awarded a grant or contract under this
section, develop a quality improvement and professional development plan for
the provider; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-784__subsec_6__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Provide coaching and other professional development services necessary to
execute the plan developed under this subsection. [2019 c.573 s1; 2021 c.93 s3;
2021 c.631 s50]
Note: 417.784 was
enacted into law by the Legislative Assembly but was not added to or made a
part of ORS chapter 417 or any series therein by legislative action. See
Preface to Oregon Revised Statutes for further explanation.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-786">
          <num>417.786</num>
          <heading>Definitions for ORS 417.788</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-786__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“At risk” means likely to enter foster care due to multiple risk factors,
including but not limited to:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-786__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Living in a household that is at or near poverty, as determined under federal
poverty guidelines;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-786__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Living in inadequate or unsafe housing;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-786__subsec_1__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Having inadequate nutrition;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-786__subsec_1__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Living in a household where there is significant or documented domestic
conflict, disruption or violence;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-786__subsec_1__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Having a parent who suffers from mental illness, who engages in substance abuse
or who experiences a developmental disability or an intellectual disability;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-786__subsec_1__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Living in circumstances under which there is neglectful or abusive caregiving;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-786__subsec_1__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Having unmet health care and medical treatment needs; or</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-786__subsec_1__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Having a racial or ethnic minority status that is historically consistent with
disproportionate overrepresentation in academic achievement gaps or in the
system of child welfare, foster care or juvenile or adult corrections.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-786__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Relief Nursery program” means a program that:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-786__subsec_2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Provides services to families with at-risk children who are zero through five
years of age, where the participation and progress of each child and family are
tracked and reported through a database that is created and maintained by the
Oregon Association of Relief Nurseries;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-786__subsec_2__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Is community based and implemented by a nongovernmental entity;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-786__subsec_2__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Is exempt from income tax under section 501</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-786__subsec_2__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-786__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of the Internal Revenue Code;
and</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-786__subsec_3__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Maintains or exceeds the minimum therapeutic program services necessary for
certification by the Oregon Association of Relief Nurseries, including but not
limited to therapeutic early childhood programs, home visiting and parent
education, support and outreach. [2017 c.645 s1]
Note: 417.786 was
enacted into law by the Legislative Assembly but was not added to or made a
part of ORS chapter 417 or any series therein by legislative action. See
Preface to Oregon Revised Statutes for further explanation.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-788">
          <num>417.788</num>
          <heading>Relief Nursery programs; rules</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-788__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Department of Early Learning and
Care shall support Relief Nursery programs statewide as funding becomes
available. Funding to support Relief Nursery programs may include, but is not
limited to:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-788__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Administrative costs;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-788__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Costs for direct service personnel, equipment, supplies and operating expenses;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-788__subsec_1__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Start-up costs;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-788__subsec_1__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Classroom furniture and materials;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-788__subsec_1__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Playground equipment;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-788__subsec_1__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Computers; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-788__subsec_1__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Transportation vehicles.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-788__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department may encourage communities to establish Relief Nursery programs
for young children who are at risk and their families. Communities may choose
to establish regional Relief Nursery programs. The Relief Nursery programs
shall be consistent with the statewide early learning system coordinated by the
Early Learning Council.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-788__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Relief Nursery programs shall participate in a statewide independent evaluation
conducted by the Oregon Association of Relief Nurseries to document improved
child safety, reduction in foster care placements, progress in healthy child
development and improvement in family functioning and support.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-788__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Each Relief Nursery program that receives state funding shall have financial
support from the community that, excluding any amounts distributed to the
Relief Nursery program pursuant to ORS 131A.360</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-788__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <paragraph eId="417-788__subsec_4__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>and 131A.365</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-788__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <paragraph eId="417-788__subsec_3__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>, is
at least equal to 25 percent of any state allocation.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-788__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department shall adopt rules necessary for the administration of this
section, including rules requiring that any public funds received by Relief
Nursery programs be used to achieve the outcomes identified in subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-788__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-790">
          <num>417.790</num>
          <heading>Grants for services, initiatives and other programs</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-790__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Make grants to fund research-based services and initiatives to improve outcomes
for children, youth or families.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-790__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Make Great Start grants to fund community-based programs for children zero
through six years of age. A recipient shall use Great Start grant funds to
provide research-based early childhood programs in community settings and to
provide services that have proven to be successful and that meet the needs of
the community. These services shall be provided in accordance with ORS 417.728.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-790__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Make grants under ORS 417.782 to fund culturally specific early learning, early
childhood and parent support programs that build capacity in communities to
provide culturally appropriate services to ensure children start kindergarten
ready to succeed and to support family stability.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-793">
          <num>417.793</num>
          <heading>Parents-as-teachers programs</heading>
          <content>
            <p>The Department of Early Learning and Care
shall support parents-as-teachers programs statewide as funding becomes
available. If a program is offered, the program shall be part of a
comprehensive, research-based approach to parent education and support. The
program shall be consistent with the statewide early learning system plan
coordinated by the Early Learning Council.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-795">
          <num>417.795</num>
          <heading>Healthy Families Oregon programs; standards; coordination</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-795__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The
Department of Early Learning and Care shall establish Healthy Families Oregon
programs in all counties of this state as funding becomes available.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-795__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>These programs shall be nonstigmatizing, voluntary and designed to achieve the
appropriate early childhood benchmarks and shall:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-795__subsec_2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Ensure that express written consent is obtained from the family prior to any
release of information that is protected by federal or state law and before the
family receives any services;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-795__subsec_2__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Ensure that services are voluntary and that, if a family chooses not to accept
services or ends services, there are no adverse consequences for those
decisions;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-795__subsec_2__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Offer a voluntary comprehensive risk assessment of all children, from zero
through three years of age, and their families in coordination with statewide
early learning system screening and referral efforts;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-795__subsec_2__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Ensure that the disclosure of information gathered in conjunction with the
voluntary comprehensive risk assessment of children and their families is
limited pursuant to ORS 417.728</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-795__subsec_7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>to the following purposes:
(A)
Providing services under the programs to children and families who give their
express written consent;
(B)
Providing statistical data that are not personally identifiable;
(C)
Accomplishing other purposes for which the family has given express written
consent; and
(D)
Meeting the requirements of mandatory state and federal disclosure laws;</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-795__subsec_7__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Ensure that risk factors used in the risk screen are limited to those risk factors
that have been shown by research to be associated with poor outcomes for
children and families;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-795__subsec_7__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Identify, as early as possible, families that would benefit most from the
programs;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-795__subsec_7__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Provide parenting education and support services, including but not limited to
community-based home visiting services;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-795__subsec_7__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Provide other supports, including but not limited to referral to and linking of
community and public services for children and families such as mental health
services, alcohol and drug treatment programs that meet the standards
promulgated by the Oregon Health Authority under ORS 430.357, child care, food,
housing and transportation;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-795__subsec_7__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Coordinate services for children consistent with other services provided
through the Oregon Early Learning System;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-795__subsec_7__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Integrate data with any common data system for early childhood programs;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-795__subsec_7__subsec_k">
              <num>(k)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Be included in a statewide independent evaluation to document:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="417-795__subsec_7__subsec_k__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Level of screening and assessment;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-795__subsec_7__subsec_k__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Incidence of child abuse and neglect;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-795__subsec_7__subsec_k__subsec_C">
                <num>(C)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Change in parenting skills; and</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-795__subsec_7__subsec_k__subsec_D">
                <num>(D)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Rate of child development;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-795__subsec_7__subsec_k__subsec_L">
                <num>(L)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Be included in a statewide training program in the dynamics of the skills
needed to provide early childhood services, such as assessment and home
visiting; and</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-795__subsec_7__subsec_m">
              <num>(m)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Meet statewide quality assurance and quality improvement standards.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-795__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Healthy Families Oregon programs, in coordination with statewide home
visiting partners, shall:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-795__subsec_3__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Identify existing services and describe and prioritize additional services
necessary for a voluntary home visit system;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-795__subsec_3__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Build on existing programs;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-795__subsec_3__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Maximize the use of volunteers and other community resources that support all
families;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-795__subsec_3__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Target, at a minimum, all prenatal families and families with children less
than three months of age and provide services through at least the child’s
third birthday; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-795__subsec_3__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Ensure that home visiting services provided by local home visiting partners for
children and pregnant women support and are coordinated with local Healthy
Families Oregon programs.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-795__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Through a Healthy Families Oregon program, a trained home visitor shall be
assigned to each family assessed as at risk that consents to receive services
through the trained home visitor. The trained home visitor shall conduct home
visits and assist the family in gaining access to needed services.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-795__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The services required by this section shall be provided by hospitals, public or
private entities or organizations, or any combination thereof, capable of
providing all or part of the family risk assessment and the follow-up services.
In granting a contract, collaborative contracting or requests for proposals may
be used and must include the most effective and consistent service delivery
system.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-795__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The family risk assessment and follow-up services for families at risk shall be
provided by trained home visitors organized in teams supervised by a manager.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-795__subsec_7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Each Healthy Families Oregon program shall adopt disciplinary procedures for
trained home visitors and other employees of the program. The procedures shall
provide appropriate disciplinary actions for trained home visitors and other
employees who violate federal or state law or the policies of the program.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-796">
          <num>417.796</num>
          <heading>Early childhood education and development programs and services; public hearings and comment; annual statewide strategic report</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-796__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The
Department of Early Learning and Care shall:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-796__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Conduct a periodic statewide needs assessment concerning the quality and
availability of early childhood education and development programs and services
for children from birth to school age, including an assessment of the
availability of high-quality prekindergarten services for low-income children
in this state.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-796__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Identify opportunities for, and barriers to, collaboration and coordination
among federally funded and state-funded child care and early childhood
education and development programs and services, including collaboration and
coordination among state agencies responsible for administering those programs
and services.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-796__subsec_1__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Develop recommendations for increasing the overall participation of children in
existing federal, state and local early childhood education and development
programs and services, including outreach to underrepresented and special
populations.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-796__subsec_1__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Develop recommendations for establishing a unified data collection system for
public early childhood education and development programs and services
throughout this state.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-796__subsec_1__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Develop recommendations regarding statewide professional development and career
advancement plans for providers of early childhood education and development
programs and services in this state.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-796__subsec_1__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Assess the capacity and effectiveness of two-year and four-year public and
private institutions of higher education in this state in supporting the
development of early childhood educators, including the extent to which the
institutions have articulation agreements, professional development and career
advancement plans, and internships or other training opportunities that allow
students to spend time with children enrolled in the federal Head Start program
or another prekindergarten program. The assessment conducted under this
paragraph must be conducted in coordination with appropriate higher education
governance bodies.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-796__subsec_1__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Make recommendations for improvements in state early learning standards and
undertake efforts to develop high-quality comprehensive early learning
standards when appropriate.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-796__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department shall hold public hearings and provide an opportunity for public
comment in relation to the actions described in subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-796__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-796__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <paragraph eId="417-796__subsec_3__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall submit an annual statewide strategic report addressing the
activities described in subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-796__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section to the State Director of
Head Start Collaboration, the Legislative Assembly and the Governor.</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-796__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Following submission of a statewide strategic report described in paragraph</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-796__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this subsection, the department may meet periodically to review the
implementation of the recommendations in the report and to review any changes
in state or local needs. [2012 c.37 ss7,8; 2015 c.774 ss32,62; 2019 c.395 ss8,9;
2021 c.631 s55]
Note: 417.796 and
417.798 were enacted into law by the Legislative Assembly but were not added to
or made a part of ORS chapter 417 or any series therein by legislative action.
See Preface to Oregon Revised Statutes for further explanation.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-798">
          <num>417.798</num>
          <heading>State Director of Head Start Collaboration</heading>
          <content>
            <p>For purposes of the statutory laws
of this state and all state operations of the federal Head Start program, the
director of state operations of the federal Head Start program may be
referenced as the State Director of Head Start Collaboration. [2012 c.37 s139]
Note: See note under
417.796.
(Runaway
and Homeless Youth)</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-799">
          <num>417.799</num>
          <heading>Runaway and homeless youth; delivery of services; policies; advisory committee on statewide planning; annual report</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-799__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Department of Human Services is
responsible for coordinating statewide planning for delivery of services to
runaway and homeless youth and their families.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-799__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department shall recommend policies that integrate a system of services and
support for runaway and homeless youth into the state’s continuum of care for
children who are 0 through 17 years of age. The department shall recommend
policies for a system of services and support for youth who are 18 through 20
years of age and who continue to be or who become homeless.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-799__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department may work with the Youth Development Division, the Employment
Department, the Housing and Community Services Department, the Office of
Community Colleges and Workforce Development, the Department of Education and
the Oregon Youth Authority to develop a comprehensive and coordinated approach
for services and support for runaway and homeless youth and their families,
including youth who are 18 through 20 years of age and who continue to be or
who become homeless.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-799__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In addition to the entities listed in subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-799__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section, the
department shall include representatives of youth, nonprofit organizations and
statewide coalitions related to runaway and homeless youth services and
supports, including services and supports for youth who are 18 through 20 years
of age and who continue to be or who become homeless, in the joint process
described in subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-799__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-799__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department may enter into and renew contracts with providers for the
provision of services to runaway and homeless youth and their families,
including services to youth who are 18 through 20 years of age and who continue
to be or who become homeless.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-799__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department shall appoint an advisory committee to advise the department
with respect to policies and procedures to coordinate statewide planning for
delivery of services to runaway and homeless youth and their families. The
advisory committee shall meet with and advise the department on a regular
basis, provide the department with information regarding the status of existing
services and make recommendations for improvements and additional services. The
department shall include as members of the advisory committee stakeholders with
expertise in housing, mental health and addictions, sex trafficking, child
welfare and law enforcement.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-799__subsec_7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department shall report annually on or before September 15 of each year to
the interim legislative committees on child welfare regarding the status of the
system of services and support for runaway and homeless youth developed by the
department, and the advice and information provided by the advisory committee
appointed by the department, pursuant to this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-800">
          <num>417.800</num>
          <heading>Department to coordinate efforts and make recommendations</heading>
          <content>
            <p>The Department of
Human Services shall coordinate the collection of data, provision of technical
assistance to communities for assessing the needs of runaway and homeless
youth, and identification and promotion of the best practices for service
delivery, and shall recommend long term goals to identify and address the
underlying causes of homelessness of youth.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-802">
          <num>417.802</num>
          <heading>Enhancement grant program for youth experiencing homelessness; rules</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-802__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>As used in
this section, “youth experiencing homelessness” means a person who is at least
14 years of age but not more than 24 years of age, who is not in the physical
custody of a parent or legal guardian and who is homeless.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-802__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In addition to any other scholarships or grants, the Department of Human
Services may award two-year grants to organizations that provide services to
youth experiencing homelessness.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-802__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department may award a grant under this section to an organization that:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-802__subsec_3__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Has an existing grant from the department to provide services to youth
experiencing homelessness; or</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-802__subsec_3__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Proposes to provide evidence-based services, as described by the department by
rule, for youth experiencing homelessness in an underserved area or an area in
which those services are not provided.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-802__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Grants awarded under this section may be used for any of the following:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-802__subsec_4__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To increase the accessibility of any of the following programs and services to
youth experiencing homelessness:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="417-802__subsec_4__subsec_a__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Shelter facilities;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-802__subsec_4__subsec_a__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Outreach;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-802__subsec_4__subsec_a__subsec_C">
                <num>(C)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Culturally specific services; and</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-802__subsec_4__subsec_a__subsec_D">
                <num>(D)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Mental health or substance abuse services; and</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-802__subsec_4__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To create or strengthen partnerships with host home programs and other
transitional housing options.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-802__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An applicant for a grant under this section must describe how the applicant
intends to ensure that other funding, including from federal or local
governments or charitable donations, will be used to supplement the total cost
of the proposed program.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-802__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department may adopt rules to administer the grant program described in
this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-803">
          <num>417.803</num>
          <heading>Host home project grants for youth experiencing homelessness; rules</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-803__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>As used in
this section:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-803__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>“Host home project” means a project that facilitates an arrangement under which
a youth experiencing homelessness resides in the home of a private individual,
pursuant to the terms of a contract between the private individual and the
youth, for free or at below-market rent.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-803__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>“Long-term host home project” means a host home project run by an organization
that has a memorandum of understanding or a letter of agreement with one or
more school districts and in which participating youth experiencing
homelessness, on average during the most recent two years, resided in host
homes for a minimum of 180 days, as reported by the relevant school district.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-803__subsec_1__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>“Short-term host home project” means a host home project in which participating
youth experiencing homelessness, on average during the most recent two years,
resided in host homes for a maximum of 180 days, as reported by the relevant
school district.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-803__subsec_1__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>“Youth experiencing homelessness” means a person who is:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="417-803__subsec_1__subsec_d__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>At least 16 years of age but not more than 21 years of age;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-803__subsec_1__subsec_d__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Not in the physical custody of a parent or legal guardian;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-803__subsec_1__subsec_d__subsec_C">
                <num>(C)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Not in the custody of the Department of Human Services;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-803__subsec_1__subsec_d__subsec_D">
                <num>(D)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Not a ward of the state; and</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-803__subsec_1__subsec_d__subsec_E">
                <num>(E)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Homeless.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-803__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In addition to and not in lieu of any other scholarships or grants, the
department may award two-year grants to organizations that operate host home
projects for youth experiencing homelessness.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-803__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An organization is eligible to apply for a grant under this section if the
organization can demonstrate the ability to:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-803__subsec_3__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Continue the operation of existing host home projects;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-803__subsec_3__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Expand host home projects in communities in which the organization provides
services;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-803__subsec_3__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Establish new long-term host home projects in communities that do not have
long-term host home projects; or</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-803__subsec_3__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Establish new short-term host home projects.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-803__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Recipients of grants awarded under this section shall work to achieve the
following outcomes for youth experiencing homelessness:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-803__subsec_4__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Improved school attendance.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-803__subsec_4__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Participation in formal or informal mentoring.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-803__subsec_4__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Increased access to nutrition, health care, mental trauma-informed support and
transportation services.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-803__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A recipient of a grant awarded under this section shall ensure all individuals
of 18 years of age or older residing in the host home who are not the youth
experiencing homelessness have an approved background check under ORS 181A.200
and 409.027.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-803__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A host home is not a child-caring agency as defined in ORS 418.205.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-803__subsec_7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department may adopt rules to administer the grant program described in
this section. [2021 c.531 s2; 2023 c.13 s44]
(Office
of Children’s Advocate)</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-805">
          <num>417.805</num>
          <heading>Toll-free child abuse hotline</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-805__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Access information and be referred to the appropriate services in matters of
child abuse.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-805__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Voice concerns regarding the actions and conduct of the Department of Human
Services relating to child abuse.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-805__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Have a single place to file complaints concerning the actions and conduct of
the Department of Human Services relating to child abuse.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-810">
          <num>417.810</num>
          <heading>Office of Children’s Advocate established; appointment; staff</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-810__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Office of
Children’s Advocate is established in the Department of Human Services. The
office is under the supervision and control of the Children’s Advocate, who is
responsible for the performance of the duties, functions and powers of the
office. With the concurrence of the Governor, the Director of Human Services shall
appoint the Children’s Advocate and may terminate the Children’s Advocate.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-810__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to available funds and the applicable provisions of ORS chapter 240,
the Children’s Advocate may hire staff to carry out the duties, functions and
powers of the office and shall prescribe their duties and fix their
compensation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-810__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Children’s Advocate shall be a person who has background and experience in:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-810__subsec_3__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Law enforcement with particular emphasis on crimes involving child victims; or</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-810__subsec_3__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Social work with particular emphasis on child abuse.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-815">
          <num>417.815</num>
          <heading>Duties of office; confidentiality; protection for person filing complaint</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-815__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Office of
Children’s Advocate shall be accessible to the public through the state
toll-free telephone line maintained pursuant to ORS 417.805 and through other
electronic and written forms of communication. The office shall:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-815__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Disseminate information and educate the public about the detection and
prevention of child abuse and about the prosecution of persons accused of child
abuse;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-815__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Cooperate with other units within the Department of Human Services and law
enforcement officials in performing duties under ORS 418.747 and 418.748 and
419B.005 to 419B.050 when the investigation involves alleged child abuse;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-815__subsec_1__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Provide technical assistance in the development and implementation of state and
local programs that relate to child abuse;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-815__subsec_1__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In cooperation with the department, objectively review the department’s systems
for handling child abuse cases; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-815__subsec_1__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Analyze data collected by the office to discern general patterns and trends,
chronic problems and other systemic difficulties in the detection, reporting,
investigation, prosecution and resolution of cases of child abuse.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-815__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In addition to the duties required under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-815__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section, the
office shall:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-815__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Review any complaint regarding the department’s involvement in a specific child
abuse case, unless the office determines there is an adequate remedy for the
complaint;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-815__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Make any appropriate referrals of the complaint or complainant at the time the
office receives the complaint or during the office’s review process;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-815__subsec_1__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Inform the complainant of the referral of the complaint or any other action
taken by the office on the complaint;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-815__subsec_1__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Inform the department of the office’s intention to review the department’s
action, unless the office determines that advance notice will unduly hinder the
review; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-815__subsec_1__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Conduct a review of the department’s action when appropriate, and inform the
department of the results of the review, including any recommendation the
Children’s Advocate believes would resolve any case or any systemic issues
identified in the review.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-815__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the office has knowledge of confidential information relating to a child
involved or allegedly involved in child abuse, the office shall keep the
information confidential from public disclosure. However, the office is subject
to legal mandates in ORS 418.747 and 418.748 and 419B.005 to 419B.050.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-815__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A person who files a complaint under this section or ORS 417.805 or
participates in any investigation under this section may not be, because of
that action:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-815__subsec_4__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Subject to any penalties, sanctions or restrictions imposed by the department;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-815__subsec_4__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Subject to any penalties, sanctions or restrictions connected with the person’s
employment; or</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-815__subsec_4__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Denied any right, privilege or benefit.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-815__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If deemed necessary by the Children’s Advocate for the purposes of carrying out
the duties of the office, the office may conduct criminal records checks
pursuant to ORS 181A.200 on a person through the Law Enforcement Data System
maintained by the Department of State Police.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-825">
          <num>417.825</num>
          <heading>Portions of certain filing fees dedicated to office</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-825__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In addition
to any other fees provided by law, the appropriate agency:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-825__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When records of live birth are registered with the state, shall pay a $1 fee on
each record of live birth registered with the agency.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-825__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>That issues certified copies of records of live birth for the state or a
county, shall collect a $1 fee on each certified copy of a record of live birth
issued by the agency.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-825__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The agencies paying or collecting the fees described in subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-825__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this
section shall transfer moneys from the fees imposed by this section to the
State Treasurer for deposit in the Department of Human Services Account
established under ORS 409.060. The moneys deposited under this section are
appropriated continuously to the Department of Human Services for use by the
Office of Children’s Advocate for the administration of ORS 417.805, 417.810
and 417.815. [1993 c.678 s11; 2003 c.591 s6; 2011 c.595 s111; 2013 c.366 s74]
EARLY
LEARNING HUBS</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-827">
          <num>417.827</num>
          <heading>Early Learning Hubs; system requirements; requests for proposals; proposal requirements; rules; metrics for funding; match requirements; delivery of services to community without hub</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-827__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>As used in this section and ORS
417.829:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-827__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>“Early Learning Hub” means any entity designated by regional partners to
coordinate early learning services, as determined by rules adopted by the Early
Learning Council.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-827__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>“Regional partners” includes counties, cities, school districts, education
service districts, community colleges, public universities, private educational
institutions, faith-based organizations, nonprofit service providers and
tribes.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-827__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The council shall implement and coordinate a system that coordinates the
delivery of early learning services to the communities of this state through
the direction of Early Learning Hubs. The system may not include more than 16
Early Learning Hubs.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-827__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The system implemented and coordinated by the council must ensure that:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-827__subsec_3__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Providers of early learning services are accountable for outcomes;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-827__subsec_3__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Services are provided in a cost-efficient manner; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-827__subsec_3__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The services provided, and the means by which those services are provided, are
focused on the outcomes of the services.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-827__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The council shall develop and implement a process for requesting proposals from
entities to become Early Learning Hubs. Proposals submitted under this
subsection must comply with criteria and requirements adopted by the council by
rule, including:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-827__subsec_4__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The entity will be able to coordinate the provision of early learning services
to the community that will be served by the entity. An entity may meet the
requirement of this paragraph by submitting evidence that local stakeholders,
including but not limited to service providers, parents, community members,
county governments, local governments and school districts, have participated
in the development of the proposal and will maintain a meaningful role in the
Early Learning Hub.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-827__subsec_4__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The services coordinated by the entity will be in alignment with the services
provided by the public schools of the community that will be served by the
entity.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-827__subsec_4__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The entity will be in alignment with, and make advantageous use of, the system
of public health care and services available through local health departments
and other publicly supported programs delivered through, or in partnership
with, counties and coordinated care organizations.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-827__subsec_4__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The entity will be able to integrate efforts among education providers,
providers of health care, providers of human services and providers of other
programs and services in the community.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-827__subsec_4__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The entity will use coordinated and transparent budgeting.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-827__subsec_4__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The entity will operate in a fiscally sound manner.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-827__subsec_4__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The entity must have a governing body or community advisory body that:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="417-827__subsec_4__subsec_g__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Has the authority to initiate audits, recommend the terms of a contract and
provide reports to the public and to the council on the outcomes of the
provision of early learning services to the community served by the entity.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-827__subsec_4__subsec_g__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Has members selected through a transparent process and includes both public and
private entities, locally based parents and service recipients, human social
service providers, child care providers, health care providers and
representatives of local governments from the service area.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-827__subsec_4__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The entity will collaborate on documentation related to coordinated services
with public and private entities that are identified by the council as
providers of services that advance the early learning of children.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-827__subsec_4__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The entity will serve a community that is based on the population and service
needs of the community and will demonstrate the ability to improve results for
at-risk children, including the ability to identify, evaluate and implement
coordinated strategies to ensure that a child is ready to succeed in school.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-827__subsec_4__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The entity will be able to raise and leverage significant funds from public and
private sources and to secure in-kind support to support early learning
services coordinated by the entity and operate in a fiscally sound manner.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-827__subsec_4__subsec_k">
              <num>(k)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The entity meets any other qualifications established by the council.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-827__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The council may adopt by rule requirements that are in addition to the
requirements described in subsections</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-827__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-827__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section that an
entity must meet to qualify as an Early Learning Hub. When developing the
additional requirements, the council must use a statewide public process of
community engagement that is consistent with the requirements of the federal
Head Start Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-827__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When determining whether to designate an entity as an Early Learning Hub, the
council shall balance the following factors:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-827__subsec_6__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The entity’s ability to engage the community and be involved in the community.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-827__subsec_6__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The entity’s ability to produce outcomes that benefit children.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-827__subsec_6__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The entity’s resourcefulness.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-827__subsec_6__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The entity’s use, or proposed use, of evidence-based practices.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-827__subsec_7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The council shall develop metrics for the purpose of providing funding to Early
Learning Hubs designated under this section. The metrics must:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-827__subsec_7__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Focus on community readiness, high capacity development and progress toward
tracking child outcomes;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-827__subsec_7__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Establish a baseline of information for the area to be served by the Early
Learning Hub, including information about the inclusion of community partners
in the governance structure of the Early Learning Hub, the availability of data
on local programs and outcomes and the success in leveraging private, nonprofit
and other governmental resources for early learning; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-827__subsec_7__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Include child performance metrics.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-827__subsec_8">
            <num>(8)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The council may require that, as a condition of receiving funding as a
designated Early Learning Hub under this section, the Early Learning Hub
provide matching funding. The percentage of matching funding shall be
determined by the council and may vary for each fiscal year. Any moneys
received by an Early Learning Hub are subject to the restrictions of this
section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-827__subsec_9">
            <num>(9)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For any community in this state that is not served by an Early Learning Hub,
the council shall coordinate and administer the delivery of early learning
services for that community and, to the extent practicable, shall regionalize
service administration.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-827__subsec_10">
            <num>(10)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The council may alter the lines of the territory served by an Early Learning
Hub only to ensure that all children of this state are served by an Early
Learning Hub and receive adequate early learning services for a community.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-827__subsec_11">
            <num>(11)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An entity designated as part of an Early Learning Hub may not use more than 15
percent of the moneys received by the entity from the Department of Early
Learning and Care to pay administrative costs of the entity.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-827__subsec_12">
            <num>(12)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Department of Human Services or the Oregon Health Authority may not
transfer any authority for determining eligibility for a state or federal
program to an Early Learning Hub.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-829">
          <num>417.829</num>
          <heading>Evaluation; report</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-829__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Each biennium, the Department of Early Learning and Care shall conduct an
evaluation of Early Learning Hubs that assesses the efficacy of the Early
Learning Hubs with respect to:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-829__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Creating an aligned, coordinated and family-centered system of early learning
services;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-829__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Increasing coordination and collaboration among entities involved in, and
providers of services related to, early learning services, education and health
and human services;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-829__subsec_1__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Increasing focus on outcomes; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-829__subsec_1__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Improving outcomes, including but not limited to outcomes associated with
school readiness, for populations defined by statute or rule as being at-risk.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-829__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An evaluation performed under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-829__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section must also assess,
with respect to Early Learning Hubs:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-829__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Governance structure;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-829__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Funding mechanisms and metrics for providing funding; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-829__subsec_1__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Compilation and use of data.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-829__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department may contract with a third party to perform an evaluation
required by this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-829__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No later than March 15 of each odd-numbered year, the department shall submit a
report to the interim legislative committees on education and early learning
regarding the findings and recommendations made as a result of an evaluation
performed under this section. The report shall include any recommendations for
legislative changes based upon the findings and recommendations made as a
result of the evaluation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-831">
          <num>417.831</num>
          <heading>Tribal Early Learning Hub; tribal advisory committee; rules</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-831__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>As used in
this section:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-831__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>“Tribal advisory committee” means the committee established by the Department
of Early Learning and Care for the purpose of advising the Early Learning
Council on the Tribal Early Learning Hub.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-831__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>“Tribal Early Learning Hub” means the entity designated by the Early Learning
Council, in consultation with the tribal advisory committee, to coordinate
early learning services provided to the tribal communities of this state, as
determined by rules adopted by the Early Learning Council in consultation with
the tribal advisory committee.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-831__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Early Learning Council shall implement and coordinate a system that
coordinates the delivery of early learning services to the tribal communities
of this state through the direction of the Tribal Early Learning Hub. The
Tribal Early Learning Hub shall be separate and distinct from the Early
Learning Hubs designated under ORS 417.827.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-831__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Department of Early Learning and Care shall establish a tribal advisory
committee. The tribal advisory committee shall consist of 21 members appointed
by the Department of Early Learning and Care in consultation with the nine
federally recognized Indian tribes of this state as follows:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-831__subsec_3__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Two representatives from each of the nine federally recognized Indian tribes of
this state;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-831__subsec_3__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>One representative from the Commission on Indian Services, who shall be a
nonvoting member;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-831__subsec_3__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>One representative of the Early Learning Council, who shall be a nonvoting
member; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-831__subsec_3__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>One representative of the Department of Early Learning and Care, who shall be a
nonvoting member.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-831__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The tribal advisory committee shall advise the Early Learning Council on the
delivery of early care and education services to the tribal communities of this
state in a culturally specific manner. The Early Learning Council shall adopt
rules related to the Tribal Early Learning Hub in consultation with the tribal
advisory committee, including rules that prescribe the requirements for
accountability and services provided.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-847">
          <num>417.847</num>
          <heading>Youth Development Council; purpose; members; duties and authority; rules</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-847__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Youth
Development Council is established.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-847__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The council is established for the purpose of coordinating a unified and
aligned system that provides services to school-age children through youth 24
years of age in a manner that supports educational and workforce success,
promotes protective factors, prevents justice system involvement, reduces high
risk behaviors and is measurable and accountable. The council shall develop
policy for and provide guidance to the Youth Development Division.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-847__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The council consists of no fewer than 15 members who are appointed by the
Governor. The Governor shall ensure that membership of the council satisfies
any federal requirements for membership of a state advisory group on juvenile
justice, and shall include tribal representation in the membership of the
council.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-847__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The council shall:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-847__subsec_4__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Approve funding processes to support community-based youth development
programs, services and initiatives with demonstrated outcomes and strategic
objectives established by the council by rule.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-847__subsec_4__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Prioritize funding for services related to:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="417-847__subsec_4__subsec_b__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The prevention of and intervention in the risk factors that lead to justice
system involvement and the promotion of protective factors that improve the
health and well-being of children and youth, as supported by evidence-based
program models, culturally specific and traditional practices and other
emerging models;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-847__subsec_4__subsec_b__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The prevention of and intervention in community violence and gang activity,
with an emphasis on a public health approach and community-based programs; and</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-847__subsec_4__subsec_b__subsec_C">
                <num>(C)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The provision of workforce development, reengagement and other types of
programming designed to support educational success, increase youth career
readiness and post-secondary success or otherwise deliver training and remove
barriers in order to promote positive youth development.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-847__subsec_4__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Coordinate the statewide youth reengagement system described in ORS 417.859, in
collaboration with the division.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-847__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The council may:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-847__subsec_5__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Enter into intergovernmental agreements with county and municipal governments,
tribal governments, educational institutions and other governmental entities
identified by rule of the council for the provision of youth development
programs, services and initiatives.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-847__subsec_5__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Enter into grant agreements and contracts with community-based organizations,
educational institutions, regional entities and other entities identified by
rule of the council for the provision of youth development programs, services
and initiatives.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-847__subsec_5__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Determine the means by which services to children and youth may be provided
effectively and efficiently across multiple programs to improve the academic
and social outcomes of children and youth, including directing the distribution
of funding by the division through processes approved by the council.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-847__subsec_5__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Assess state programs and services related to youth development and training,
and identify methods by which programs and services may be coordinated or
consolidated.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-847__subsec_5__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Establish common academic and social indicators to support attainment of goals
established by the council.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-847__subsec_5__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Establish common program outcome measurements and coordinate data collection
across multiple programs and services.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-847__subsec_5__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Ensure implementation of best practices that:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="417-847__subsec_5__subsec_g__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Are informed by developmental science, evidence, and effective or promising
community practices;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-847__subsec_5__subsec_g__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Are culturally, gender and age appropriate;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-847__subsec_5__subsec_g__subsec_C">
                <num>(C)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Address individual protective and risk factors;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-847__subsec_5__subsec_g__subsec_D">
                <num>(D)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Build upon factors that improve the health and well-being of children and
youth; and</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-847__subsec_5__subsec_g__subsec_E">
                <num>(E)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Include tribal best practices.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-847__subsec_5__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Delegate responsibilities to the division.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-847__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Governor may designate one member of the council to serve as the
chairperson or, if the Governor chooses not to designate a chairperson, the
council may elect one of its members to serve as chairperson.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-847__subsec_7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In accordance with applicable provisions of ORS chapter 183, the council may
adopt rules necessary for the administration of the laws that the council is
charged with administering.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-850">
          <num>417.850</num>
          <heading>Additional duties of council; rules</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-850__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Review the budget and allocation formula for appropriations for the purpose of
juvenile crime prevention.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-850__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Review the components of local high-risk juvenile crime prevention plans
developed under ORS 417.855 and make recommendations to the Governor about the
local plans.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-850__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Ensure that high-risk juvenile crime prevention planning criteria are met by
state and local public and private entities.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-850__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Recommend high-risk juvenile justice and juvenile crime prevention policies to
the Governor and the Legislative Assembly.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-850__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Ensure initiation of contracts based on approved local high-risk juvenile crime
prevention plans and oversee contract changes.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-850__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Review data and outcome information.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-850__subsec_7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Establish and publish review and assessment criteria for the local high-risk
juvenile crime prevention plans. The criteria shall include, but not be limited
to, measuring changes in juvenile crime and juvenile recidivism.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-850__subsec_8">
            <num>(8)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Review local high-risk juvenile crime prevention plans and ensure alignment of
the plans with diversion plans and basic services grants of county juvenile
departments. The council shall consult or communicate with county juvenile
departments, federally recognized Indian tribes and the Oregon Youth Authority
to adopt rules to carry out the provisions of this subsection.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-850__subsec_9">
            <num>(9)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Work to ensure broad-based citizen involvement in the planning and execution of
high-risk juvenile crime prevention plans at both the state and local levels.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-850__subsec_10">
            <num>(10)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Develop a funding policy that provides incentives for flexible programming and
promotes strategies that build protective factors and contribute to the
well-being of youth and families.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-850__subsec_11">
            <num>(11)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Periodically report to the Governor and the Legislative Assembly on the
progress of the council.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-850__subsec_12">
            <num>(12)</num>
            <content>
              <p>As required by the federal Juvenile Justice and Delinquency Prevention Act of
1974, 34 U.S.C. 11133 et seq., approve funding and policy recommendations of
the state advisory group and adopt rules for overseeing approved funding and
policy recommendations.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-850__subsec_13">
            <num>(13)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Work with tribal governments to develop tribal high-risk juvenile crime
prevention plans.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-851">
          <num>417.851</num>
          <heading>Juvenile detention data; rules</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-851__subsec_12">
            <num>(12)</num>
            <content>
              <p>, the Youth Development Division may collect data and inspect any
facility, as identified by the Youth Development Council by rule, in which
juveniles are detained.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-852">
          <num>417.852</num>
          <heading>Youth Development Division; purpose; administrative officer</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-852__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Youth
Development Division is established in the Department of Education. The purpose
of the division is to ensure that services are provided to school-age children
through youth 24 years of age in a manner that supports education and career
success, disrupts youth crime and violence and affirms youth strengths and
safety.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-852__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The division shall function under and be coordinated by the Youth Development
Council with the Youth Development Director serving as the administrative
officer.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-852__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The division shall:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-852__subsec_3__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Distribute funding as directed by the council or the Legislative Assembly and
administer grant funding processes and programs;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-852__subsec_3__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Carry out compliance monitoring and other required activities as directed by
the council, under the federal Juvenile Justice and Delinquency Prevention Act
of 1974, 34 U.S.C. 11133 et seq.;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-852__subsec_3__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Collaborate with the council to develop youth development policies and programs
that support youth, family, practitioners and community needs;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-852__subsec_3__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Collaborate with other state agencies serving youth in order to align services,
programs and activities and to share expertise;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-852__subsec_3__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Engage in administrative functions to ensure the effective operation of the
division and council and work with the Department of Education when services
are shared;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-852__subsec_3__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Seek to increase opportunities for youth to participate in leadership roles and
have direct influence on youth development programs, in collaboration with the
council and through the programs administered by the division; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-852__subsec_3__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Ensure that youth development services administered by the division are
delivered to youth in an equitable, accountable and effective manner, through
the collection of data from administered programs, communication with entities
delivering services and recipients of program services, and coordination with
other state agencies.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-853">
          <num>417.853</num>
          <heading>Youth Development Director; appointment; responsibilities</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-853__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Governor
shall appoint the Youth Development Director, who is responsible for the
performance of the duties, functions and powers of the Youth Development Division.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-853__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The director shall serve at the pleasure of the Governor.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-853__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The director shall be directly responsible to the Superintendent of Public
Instruction.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-854">
          <num>417.854</num>
          <heading>Youth Development Division Fund; sources; uses</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-854__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Youth
Development Division Fund is established in the State Treasury, separate and
distinct from the General Fund. Interest earned by the Youth Development
Division Fund shall be credited to the fund.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-854__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Moneys in the Youth Development Division Fund consist of:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-854__subsec_2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Amounts donated to the fund;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-854__subsec_2__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Moneys transferred to the fund from the federal government, state agencies and
local governments;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-854__subsec_2__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Amounts appropriated or otherwise transferred to the fund by the Legislative
Assembly;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-854__subsec_2__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Investment earnings received on moneys in the fund; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-854__subsec_2__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Other amounts deposited in the fund from any source.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-854__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Moneys in the fund are continuously appropriated to the Department of Education
for the purpose of fulfilling the duties, functions and powers of the Youth
Development Division.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-854__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department may establish accounts and subaccounts within the fund when the
department determines that accounts or subaccounts are necessary or desirable
and may credit any interest or income derived from moneys in the fund to any
account or subaccount in the fund.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-855">
          <num>417.855</num>
          <heading>Local high-risk juvenile crime prevention plan</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-855__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <paragraph eId="417-855__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The
governing body of a county shall designate an agency or organization to serve
as the lead planning organization to facilitate the creation of a partnership
among state and local public and private entities in each county. The
partnership shall include, but is not limited to, education representatives,
public health representatives, local alcohol and drug planning committees,
representatives of the court system, local mental health planning committees,
city or municipal representatives and local public safety coordinating
councils.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-855__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The partnership described in paragraph</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-855__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this subsection shall develop a
local high-risk juvenile crime prevention plan. The partnership shall submit
the plan to the Youth Development Council, on a timeline established by the
council, for review and approval in order for the county to receive an
allocation described in subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-855__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section.</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-855__subsec_3__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The governing body of a county may decline to submit a local high-risk juvenile
crime prevention plan in writing to the Youth Development Council. A governing
body that declines to submit a plan to the Youth Development Council may choose
to convene the partnership described in paragraph</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-855__subsec_3__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this subsection and
develop and submit a local high-risk juvenile crime prevention plan in a
subsequent biennium.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-855__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The local high-risk juvenile crime prevention plans shall use services and
activities to meet the needs of a targeted population of youths who:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-855__subsec_2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Have more than one of the following risk factors:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="417-855__subsec_2__subsec_a__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Antisocial behavior;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-855__subsec_2__subsec_a__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Poor family functioning or poor family support;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-855__subsec_2__subsec_a__subsec_C">
                <num>(C)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Failure in school;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-855__subsec_2__subsec_a__subsec_D">
                <num>(D)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Substance abuse problems; or</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-855__subsec_2__subsec_a__subsec_E">
                <num>(E)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Negative peer association; and</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-855__subsec_2__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Are clearly demonstrating at-risk behaviors that have come to the attention of
government or community agencies, schools or law enforcement and will lead to
imminent or increased involvement in the juvenile justice system.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-855__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <paragraph eId="417-855__subsec_3__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Youth Development Council shall allocate funds available to support the
local high-risk juvenile crime prevention plans to counties based, in part, on
the youth population age 18 or younger in those counties.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-855__subsec_3__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Youth Development Council shall award a minimum grant to small counties.
The minimum grant level shall be determined by the council through a public
process and reviewed by the council biennially.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-855__subsec_3__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Youth Development Council shall allocate funds to federally recognized
Indian tribes to support tribal high-risk juvenile crime prevention plans. The
amount of the allocation shall be determined by the council through a public
process and reviewed by the council biennially.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-859">
          <num>417.859</num>
          <heading>Statewide youth reengagement system; rules</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-859__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>As used in this section, “eligible
youth” means a person 14 through 24 years of age who:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-859__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Is not currently enrolled in school for the school year and who:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="417-859__subsec_1__subsec_a__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Is not a high school graduate; or</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-859__subsec_1__subsec_a__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Has not received a certificate for passing an approved high school equivalency
test such as the General Educational Development (GED) test;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-859__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Is recommended to participate in a youth reengagement program by the Department
of Human Services, the Housing and Community Services Department, a juvenile
court, the Oregon Youth Authority, a county juvenile department, a federally
recognized Indian tribe, a school district, an education service district or
any other entity identified by the Youth Development Council by rule; or</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-859__subsec_1__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Is not on track to graduate on time, as determined based on rules adopted by
the council.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-859__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Youth Development Division shall develop and administer a statewide youth
reengagement system to provide appropriate educational opportunities and access
to services for eligible youths.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-859__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Under the statewide youth reengagement system, a school district or other
entity identified by the Youth Development Council by rule may choose to
provide a youth reengagement program. A youth reengagement program must:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-859__subsec_3__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Be offered in collaboration with the Youth Development Division; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-859__subsec_3__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Include a partnership with an education service district, a community college
district, a federally recognized Indian tribe, a community-based organization
or any other entity identified by the Youth Development Council by rule.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-859__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A youth reengagement program must offer, at a minimum, the following:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-859__subsec_4__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Academic instruction that enables an eligible youth to receive credit that can
be:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="417-859__subsec_4__subsec_a__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Applied toward a high school diploma, a modified diploma or an extended diploma;
or</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-859__subsec_4__subsec_a__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Used to improve college or career readiness, including courses that assist the
eligible youth in preparing for an approved high school equivalency test such
as the General Educational Development (GED) test; or</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-859__subsec_4__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Services for monitoring and supporting eligible youths, including:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="417-859__subsec_4__subsec_b__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Academic counseling, career coaching and workforce readiness services; or</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-859__subsec_4__subsec_b__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Assistance with accessing services and resources that support at-risk youth and
reduce barriers to educational success.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-859__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If a school district or other entity chooses to provide a youth reengagement
program, the school district or other entity may enter into an agreement to
provide academic instruction or services as described in subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-859__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this
section. The agreement:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-859__subsec_4__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>May be entered into with:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="417-859__subsec_4__subsec_a__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>An education service district, a community college district or another public
entity;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-859__subsec_4__subsec_a__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>A federally recognized Indian tribe or a school or other provider of
educational services associated with the tribe; or</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-859__subsec_4__subsec_a__subsec_C">
                <num>(C)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>A community-based organization; and</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-859__subsec_4__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Must comply with any other requirements prescribed by the State Board of
Education or the Youth Development Council by rule.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-859__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <paragraph eId="417-859__subsec_6__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The State Board of Education, in collaboration with the Youth Development
Council, shall establish by rule criteria for a school district or other entity
to receive funding for eligible youths participating in a youth reengagement
program. Funding may be in the form of grants.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-859__subsec_6__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The criteria to receive funding may prescribe:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="417-859__subsec_6__subsec_b__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Enrollment and attendance standards for eligible youths.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-859__subsec_6__subsec_b__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Performance measures that establish targets that must be met for purposes of
accountability. The performance measure targets shall be based on standards
adopted by the Youth Development Council and may take into account the specific
purpose of the program offered by the school district or other entity, the
population served by the program and any other factors identified by the
council.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-859__subsec_6__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The criteria to receive funding must require a school district or other entity
to provide to the Youth Development Division information that, at a minimum,
describes:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="417-859__subsec_6__subsec_c__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>How the school district or other entity will identify, refer and enroll
eligible youths;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-859__subsec_6__subsec_c__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>How academic instruction and services will be provided through the youth
reengagement program and what academic instruction and services will be
provided;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-859__subsec_6__subsec_c__subsec_C">
                <num>(C)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>How student records will be maintained and how data will be collected and
reported;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-859__subsec_6__subsec_c__subsec_D">
                <num>(D)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>How any applicable assessments under ORS 329.485 or 329.488 will be
administered;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-859__subsec_6__subsec_c__subsec_E">
                <num>(E)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>How the school district or other entity will provide special education and
related services for eligible youths with disabilities who have an
individualized education program or will provide necessary accommodations and
plans for eligible youths who qualify under section 504 of the Rehabilitation
Act of 1973 (29 U.S.C. 794);</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-859__subsec_6__subsec_c__subsec_F">
                <num>(F)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>How the school district or other entity will ensure that eligible youths
receive appropriate in-person guidance or support; and</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-859__subsec_6__subsec_c__subsec_G">
                <num>(G)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>How the school district or other entity will record and report performance
measures for purposes of accountability, including longitudinal monitoring of
student progress and post-secondary education and employment readiness.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-859__subsec_7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Department of Education and Youth Development Division shall provide
technical assistance to school districts and other eligible entities choosing
to provide youth reengagement programs.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-859__subsec_8">
            <num>(8)</num>
            <paragraph eId="417-859__subsec_8__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Youth Development Council shall coordinate with the State Board of
Education to adopt rules under this section.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-859__subsec_8__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When adopting rules under this section, the board and the council shall consult
or communicate with:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="417-859__subsec_8__subsec_b__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Post-secondary institutions of education, school districts and community-based
organizations that have previously offered youth reengagement programs;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-859__subsec_8__subsec_b__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Providers of online courses and programs;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-859__subsec_8__subsec_b__subsec_C">
                <num>(C)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Federally recognized Indian tribes; and</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-859__subsec_8__subsec_b__subsec_D">
                <num>(D)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Education service districts.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-859__subsec_9">
            <num>(9)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Nothing in this section affects the authority of a school district or other
entity to directly offer youth reengagement programs or other educational
services for eligible youths. [2019 c.122 s33; 2021 c.87 s1; 2021 c.97 s42]
MISCELLANEOUS</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-875">
          <num>417.875</num>
          <heading>Required training regarding concussions; restrictions on participation in athletic event or training; guidelines; liability</heading>
          <subsection eId="417-875__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>As used in
this section:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-875__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>“Coach” means a person who volunteers for, or is paid to instruct or train
members of, a nonschool athletic team.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-875__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>“League governing body” means a governing body that:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="417-875__subsec_1__subsec_b__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Oversees an association of nonschool athletic teams that provide instruction or
training for team members and that may compete with each other; and</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-875__subsec_1__subsec_b__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Is affiliated with, or otherwise sponsored or organized by, a nonprofit
corporation established as provided by ORS chapter 65.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-875__subsec_1__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>“Nonschool athletic team” means an athletic team that includes members who are
under 18 years of age and that is not affiliated with a public school in this
state.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-875__subsec_1__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>“Qualified health care professional” means:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="417-875__subsec_1__subsec_d__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>A physician licensed pursuant to ORS 677.100 to 677.228; or</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-875__subsec_1__subsec_d__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>A health care professional who meets the requirements described in ORS 336.490
to provide a medical release for a member of a nonschool athletic team who is
suspected of having a concussion.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-875__subsec_1__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>“Referee” means a person who volunteers or is paid to act as a referee, as an
umpire or in a similar supervisory position for events involving nonschool
athletic teams.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-875__subsec_1__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>“Referee governing body” means a governing body that:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="417-875__subsec_1__subsec_f__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Trains and certifies individuals to serve as referees for nonschool athletic
team events; and</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-875__subsec_1__subsec_f__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Is affiliated with, or otherwise sponsored or organized by, a nonprofit
corporation established as provided by ORS chapter 65.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-875__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <paragraph eId="417-875__subsec_2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Each league governing body and each referee governing body shall ensure that
the coaches and the referees, respectively, receive annual training to learn
how to recognize the symptoms of a concussion and how to seek proper medical
treatment for a person who is suspected of having a concussion.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-875__subsec_2__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Each league governing body and each referee governing body shall adopt a policy
that establishes:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="417-875__subsec_2__subsec_b__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The requirements of the training described in paragraph</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-875__subsec_2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this subsection;
and</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="417-875__subsec_2__subsec_a__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Procedures that ensure that every coach and referee receives the training
described in paragraph</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-875__subsec_2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this subsection.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-875__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Except as provided in subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-875__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-875__subsec_4__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A coach may not allow a member of a nonschool athletic team to participate in
any athletic event or training on the same day that the member:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="417-875__subsec_4__subsec_a__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Exhibits signs, symptoms or behaviors consistent with a concussion following an
observed or suspected blow to the head or body; or</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-875__subsec_4__subsec_a__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Has been diagnosed with a concussion.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-875__subsec_4__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A coach may allow a member of a nonschool athletic team who is prohibited from
participating in an athletic event or training, as described in paragraph</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-875__subsec_4__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this subsection, to participate in an athletic event or training no sooner
than the day after the member experienced a blow to the head or body and only
after the member:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="417-875__subsec_4__subsec_a__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>No longer exhibits signs, symptoms or behaviors consistent with a concussion;
and</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="417-875__subsec_4__subsec_a__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Receives a medical release from a qualified health care professional.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-875__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A coach may allow a member of a nonschool athletic team to participate in any athletic
event or training at any time after an athletic trainer licensed by the Board
of Athletic Trainers, or a physician licensed pursuant to ORS 677.100 to
677.228, determines that the member of a nonschool athletic team has not
suffered a concussion. The athletic trainer or physician may, but is not
required to, consult with a qualified health care professional in making the
determination that the member of a nonschool athletic team has not suffered a
concussion.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-875__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The league governing body shall develop or use existing guidelines and other
relevant materials, and shall make available those guidelines and materials, to
inform and educate persons under 18 years of age desiring to be a member of a
nonschool athletic team, the parents and legal guardians of the persons and the
coaches about the symptoms and warning signs of a concussion.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-875__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For each year of participation, and prior to a person under 18 years of age
participating as a member of a nonschool athletic team, at least one parent or
legal guardian of the person must acknowledge the receipt of the guidelines and
materials described in subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-875__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section and the review of those
guidelines and materials by:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="417-875__subsec_5__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The parent or legal guardian of the person; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-875__subsec_5__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the person is 12 years of age or older, the person.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-875__subsec_7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A league governing body may hold an informational meeting prior to the start of
any season for each nonschool athletic team regarding the symptoms and warning
signs of a concussion.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="417-875__subsec_8">
            <num>(8)</num>
            <paragraph eId="417-875__subsec_8__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Any person who regularly serves as a coach or as a referee and who complies
with the provisions of this section is immune from civil or criminal liability
related to a head injury unless the person acted or failed to act because of
gross negligence or willful or wanton misconduct.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="417-875__subsec_8__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Nothing in this section shall be construed to affect the civil or criminal
liability related to a head injury of a person who does not regularly serve as
a coach or a referee.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_417-990">
          <num>417.990</num>
          <heading>Penalty for placement of children in violation of compact</heading>
          <content>
            <p>The sending,
bringing, or causing to be sent or brought into any receiving state of a child
in violation of the terms of the Interstate Compact on the Placement of
Children is a Class A misdemeanor. [1975 c.482 s8]
_______________</p>
          </content>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>