<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="ORS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-or/act/ors/chapter-310"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-or/act/ors/chapter-310"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#oregon-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-or"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="310"/>
          <FRBRname value="ORS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-or/act/ors/chapter-310/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-or/act/ors/chapter-310/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-or/act/ors/chapter-310/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-or/act/ors/chapter-310/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="oregon-legislature" href="https://www.oregonlegislature.gov" showAs="Oregon State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <chapter eId="chp_310">
        <num>310</num>
        <heading>Property Tax Limitations; Local Government Taxes</heading>
        <section eId="sec_310-010">
          <num>310.010</num>
          <heading>Determination of amount of money for county and other purposes</heading>
          <content>
            <p>The county court
or board of county commissioners of each county shall, in July of each year,
estimate and determine the amount of money to be raised for county purposes for
the current fiscal year, and also the several amounts to be raised in the county
for other purposes, as required or authorized by law. The determination shall
be entered in its records.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_310-020">
          <num>310.020</num>
          <heading>Levy of tax to defray county expenses</heading>
          <content>
            <p>The county court or board of county
commissioners for each county in the state shall, in July of each year, levy a
tax upon all taxable property in the county sufficient in amount to defray the
expenses of the county for the current fiscal year.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_310-030">
          <num>310.030</num>
          <heading>Levy of taxes required or permitted by law</heading>
          <content>
            <p>The county court or board of
county commissioners shall, in July of each year, levy all taxes which by law
it is required to levy, and any other taxes which it may determine to levy and
by law it is permitted to levy.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_310-040">
          <num>310.040</num>
          <heading>Reducing levy where necessity for budget item eliminated</heading>
          <content>
            <p>If after a tax
levy has been made by any county court or board of county commissioners and
before the extension of the levy upon the tax rolls, the necessity for any item
contained in the budget upon which the levy is based is eliminated by act of
the Legislative Assembly, the county court or board of county commissioners
shall by appropriate order reduce the amount of the levy by the amount of such
item. Thereupon the levy shall be extended upon the rolls as so reduced.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_310-055">
          <num>310.055</num>
          <heading>Operating taxes</heading>
          <subsection eId="310-055__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>As used in the property tax laws of this state, “operating taxes” means ad
valorem property taxes that are subject to a permanent rate limit under section
11, Article XI of the Oregon Constitution, or statutory rate limit under ORS
310.236</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-055__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>or 310.237, if applicable.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-055__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For the tax year beginning July 1, 1997, operating taxes consist of the sum of
the following (or such lesser amount as is certified to the assessor under ORS
310.206</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-055__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <paragraph eId="310-055__subsec_4__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>:</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-055__subsec_4__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The total amount of ad valorem property taxes as provided in ORS 310.200 to
310.242, except that the amount under this paragraph does not include:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="310-055__subsec_4__subsec_a__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Local option taxes;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="310-055__subsec_4__subsec_a__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Ad valorem property taxes used to repay taxing district bond or pension and
disability plan obligations described in section 11</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-055__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>, Article XI of the
Oregon Constitution;
(C)
Ad valorem property taxes that would otherwise be subject to this paragraph,
except that the taxes are of a taxing district other than a city, county or
school district, and are used to support a hospital facility;
(D)
Ad valorem property taxes that would otherwise be subject to this paragraph,
except that the levy of the taxes was approved by voters prior to December 5,
1996, that met the voter participation requirements in section 11</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-055__subsec_8">
            <num>(8)</num>
            <content>
              <p>, Article
XI of the Oregon Constitution, and that are first imposed in the tax year
beginning July 1, 1996, or July 1, 1997;
(E)
Serial or one-year levies described in ORS 280.040 to 280.140 (1995 Edition)
that replace levies that were imposed in the tax year beginning July 1, 1996,
that were approved by voters in an election held after December 4, 1996, and
that are first imposed for the tax year beginning July 1, 1997, if the rate or
the amount of the levy is not greater than the rate or the amount of the
replaced levy;
(F)
Taxes imposed to pay principal and interest on exempt bonded indebtedness; and
(G)
Urban renewal increment taxes; and</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="310-055__subsec_8__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The total amount of the following ad valorem property taxes, without reduction
under ORS 310.200 to 310.242:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="310-055__subsec_8__subsec_b__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Ad valorem property taxes of a taxing district other than a city, county or
school district that are used to support a hospital facility;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="310-055__subsec_8__subsec_b__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Ad valorem property taxes approved by voters prior to December 5, 1996, that
met the voter participation requirements in section 11</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-055__subsec_8">
            <num>(8)</num>
            <content>
              <p>, Article XI of the
Oregon Constitution, and that are first imposed in the tax year beginning July
1, 1996, or July 1, 1997; and
(C)
Serial or one-year levies described in ORS 280.040 to 280.140 (1995 Edition)
that replace levies that were imposed in the tax year beginning July 1, 1996,
that were approved by voters after December 4, 1996, and that are first imposed
for the tax year beginning July 1, 1997, if the rate or the amount of the levy
is not greater than the rate or the amount of the replaced levy.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-055__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For tax years beginning on or after July 1, 1998, each taxing district is
authorized to levy the full amount of the operating taxes of the district on
all taxable property within the boundaries of the district. Operating taxes
consist of:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="310-055__subsec_3__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Ad valorem property taxes imposed at the rate established as the permanent rate
limit or statutory rate limit, if applicable, for the taxing district or such
lesser rate or amount as the taxing district certifies to the assessor under
ORS 310.060; or</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-055__subsec_3__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the district is imposing operating property taxes for the first time, ad
valorem property taxes imposed at the rate established in the manner provided
for by law as the permanent rate limit for the district or such lesser rate or
amount as the taxing district may determine.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_310-060">
          <num>310.060</num>
          <heading>Notice certifying taxes; contents; extension of time to give notice or correct erroneous certification</heading>
          <subsection eId="310-060__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Not later than July 15 of each year, a city,
school district or other public corporation authorized to levy or impose a tax
on property shall file a written notice certifying the ad valorem property tax
rate or the estimated amount of ad valorem property taxes to be imposed by the
taxing district and any other taxes on property imposed by the taxing district
on property subject to ad valorem property taxation that are required or
authorized to be placed on the assessment and tax roll for the current fiscal
year. The notice must be accompanied by two copies of a lawfully adopted
ordinance or resolution that categorizes the tax, fee, charge, assessment or
toll as subject to or not subject to the limits of section 11b, Article XI of
the Oregon Constitution, identified by the categories set forth in ORS 310.150.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-060__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For ad valorem property taxes levied by a taxing district, the notice required
under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-060__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section must state as separate items:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="310-060__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The taxing district’s rate or amount of ad valorem property taxation that is
within the permanent rate limitation imposed by section 11</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-060__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>, Article XI of
the Oregon Constitution, or within the statutory rate limit determined in ORS
310.236</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-060__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <paragraph eId="310-060__subsec_4__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or 310.237, if applicable;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-060__subsec_4__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The total rate or amount of the taxing district’s local option taxes imposed
pursuant to ORS 280.040 to 280.145 that have a term of five years or less and
that are not for capital projects;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-060__subsec_4__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The total rate or amount of the taxing district’s local option taxes that are
for capital projects;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-060__subsec_4__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The total amount levied for the payment of bonded indebtedness or interest on
bonded indebtedness that is not subject to limitation under section 11</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-060__subsec_11">
            <num>(11)</num>
            <content>
              <p>or
section 11b, Article XI of the Oregon Constitution; and</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="310-060__subsec_11__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The total amount levied that is subject to section 11b, Article XI of the Oregon
Constitution, but that is not subject to the permanent ad valorem property tax
rate limit described in section 11</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-060__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>, Article XI of the Oregon Constitution,
because the amount levied is to be used to repay:
(A)
Principal and interest for a bond issued before December 5, 1996, and secured
by a pledge or explicit commitment of ad valorem property taxes or a covenant
to levy or collect ad valorem property taxes;
(B)
Principal and interest for any other formal, written borrowing of moneys
executed before December 5, 1996, for which ad valorem property tax revenues
have been pledged or explicitly committed, or that are secured by a covenant to
levy or collect ad valorem property taxes;
(C)
Principal and interest for a bond issued to refund an obligation described in
subparagraph (A) or (B) of this paragraph; or
(D)
Local government pension and disability plan obligations that commit ad valorem
property taxes.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-060__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <paragraph eId="310-060__subsec_3__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The notice required under subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-060__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section must list each rate or
amount subject to the limits of section 11b, Article XI of the Oregon
Constitution, identified by the categories set forth in ORS 310.150.</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="310-060__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If an item described in subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-060__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section is allocable to more
than one category described in ORS 310.150, the notice must list separately the
portion of each item allocable to each category.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-060__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For other taxes on property imposed by the taxing district, the notice must
state:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="310-060__subsec_4__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The total amount of money to be raised by each other tax, in the aggregate or on
a property by property basis, as appropriate.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-060__subsec_4__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Each amount that is subject to the limits of section 11b, Article XI of the
Oregon Constitution, identified by the categories set forth in ORS 310.150.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-060__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For a district authorized by law to place other fees, charges, assessments or
tolls on the assessment and tax roll, the notice must state the total amount of
money to be raised on a property by property basis.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-060__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In addition to the notice required under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-060__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section, a
taxing district that is subject to the Local Budget Law shall also provide the
documents required under ORS 294.458</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-060__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-060__subsec_7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Not later than July 15 of each year, the taxing district shall give the notice
and documents described in this section to the assessor of the county in which
the principal office of the taxing district is located and, if the taxing
district is located in more than one county, to the assessor of each county in
which any part of the taxing district is located.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-060__subsec_8">
            <num>(8)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Department of Revenue shall prescribe the form of notice required under
this section. All amounts contained in the notice must be stated in dollars and
cents or ad valorem property tax rates in dollars and cents per thousand
dollars of assessed value, as required by law. If the notice is given to the
assessor, clerk or tax supervising and conservation commission of more than one
county, a copy of each other such notice given must accompany every notice
given.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-060__subsec_9">
            <num>(9)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For good and sufficient reason, a county assessor may extend the time for the
giving of the notice required under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-060__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section or
correcting an erroneous certification for the current year up to but not later
than October 1 as the county assessor considers reasonable. [Amended by 1955
c.259 s1; 1967 c.293 s4; 1973 c.333 s2; 1979 c.241 s28a; 1981 c.790 s12; 1985
c.784 s2; 1991 c.459 s218; 1993 c.270 s44; 1995 c.293 s1; 1997 c.154 s5; 1997
c.541 s244; 1999 c.186 s5; 1999 c.632 s23; 2001 c.135 s31; 2001 c.695 s32; 2001
c.753 s7; 2005 c.750 s1; 2007 c.894 s2; 2011 c.473 s26; 2013 c.420 s8]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_310-061">
          <num>310.061</num>
          <heading>Assessor to determine and report maximum school district operating tax when district certifies lesser rate; determination modified if district divided into zones</heading>
          <subsection eId="310-061__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If a school district certifies a rate pursuant to ORS 310.060 that is less
than the maximum rate of operating taxes allowed by law, the county assessor
for each county within which the school district is located shall determine the
amount of operating taxes that would have been imposed by the school district
if the school district had certified the maximum rate of operating taxes
allowed by law.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-061__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If a school district has established tax zones pursuant to ORS 328.570 to
328.579, solely for purposes of subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-061__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="310-061__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The maximum rate of operating tax allowed by law shall be determined for each
tax zone of the district; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-061__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The maximum rate of operating tax for a tax zone in which the district does not
provide all of kindergarten through grade 12 education shall equal the maximum
rate of operating tax for the district multiplied by the percentage established
for the zone in the resolution adopted under ORS 328.576.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-061__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Each county assessor who is required to calculate an amount under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-061__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section shall report that amount to the Department of Education. [1999
c.186 s12; 2001 c.246 s7]
Note: 310.061 was
enacted into law by the Legislative Assembly but was not added to or made a
part of ORS chapter 310 or any series therein by legislative action. See
Preface to Oregon Revised Statutes for further explanation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_310-065">
          <num>310.065</num>
          <heading>Procedure where notice not given</heading>
          <content>
            <p>If the written notice of a taxing
district’s ad valorem property tax or other tax is not given to the county
assessor at the time specified, or as extended, under ORS 310.060, the assessor
shall not include the tax in the computation of the total district tax rate
under ORS 310.090. [Formerly part of 310.050; 1993 c.270 s45; 1997 c.541 s246]</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_310-070">
          <num>310.070</num>
          <heading>Procedure when taxes exceed limitations or are incorrectly categorized</heading>
          <subsection eId="310-070__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the ad
valorem property taxes reported to the clerk, assessor or tax supervising and
conservation commission under ORS 310.060 are in excess of the constitutional
or statutory limitations, or both, the assessor, upon the advice of the
Department of Revenue, shall extend upon the tax roll of the county only such
part of the taxes as will comply with the constitutional and statutory
limitations and requirements governing the taxes.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-070__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any part of the taxes on property certified under ORS 310.060 is incorrectly
categorized as subject to or not subject to the limits of section 11b, Article
XI of the Oregon Constitution, the Department of Revenue shall notify the
taxing unit governing body and the county assessor and the county assessor
shall extend the taxes on the roll in a manner that complies with the Oregon
Constitution. For purposes of this section, taxes are incorrectly categorized
only if:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="310-070__subsec_2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The sole authority of the taxing unit to impose taxes on property is provided
by statute and the statute does not authorize the imposition of taxes on
property categorized as reported under ORS 310.060; or</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-070__subsec_2__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Oregon Tax Court or the Oregon Supreme Court has finally determined the
correct manner in which a tax on property of the taxing unit should be
categorized and that determination is different from the category reported
under ORS 310.060. For purposes of this paragraph, “finally determined” means
that the Oregon Tax Court has entered a decision which has become final as described
under ORS 305.440 or that, upon appeal from the Oregon Tax Court, the Supreme
Court has entered a decision.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-070__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any item certifying ad valorem property taxes under ORS 310.060 incorrectly
characterizes the item attributes under section 11, Article XI of the Oregon
Constitution, the Department of Revenue shall notify the taxing district
governing body and the county assessor, and the county assessor shall extend
the taxes on the roll in a manner that complies with the Oregon Constitution. [Amended
by 1967 c.293 s5; 1971 c.646 s3; 1981 c.790 s13; 1983 s.s. c.5 s19; 1985 c.319 s2;
1993 c.270 s46; 1997 c.541 s247; 2005 c.750 s2]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_310-090">
          <num>310.090</num>
          <heading>Computation of rate for each item of tax; category rates; total rates</heading>
          <subsection eId="310-090__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to
ORS 310.070, the county assessor shall compute the rate for each item of ad
valorem property taxes, the category rate of ad valorem property taxes for each
category described in ORS 310.150 and the total rate of ad valorem property
taxes for each taxing district as provided in this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-090__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the item of tax that is reported on the notice filed under ORS 310.060 is an
amount, the rate of tax for that item shall be computed by dividing the amount
by the assessed value used to compute the tax rate. The assessed value used to
compute the tax rate is the tax levying district’s assessed value adjusted as
otherwise provided by law.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-090__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The computed tax rates under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-090__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section or as reported on
the notice filed under ORS 310.060 shall be carried to the number of decimal
places specified by rule of the Department of Revenue and truncated. The
truncated rate shall be expressed as a rate per thousand dollars of assessed
value.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-090__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All of the taxing district’s taxes that are reported on the notice filed under
ORS 310.060 as rates and that are within the same category under ORS 310.150
shall be added together and added to the rates computed under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-090__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of
this section that are within the same category to obtain the category rates for
the taxing district.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-090__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The total tax rate of the district shall be the total of the truncated tax
rates calculated for the taxing district for the year. [Amended by 1967 c.293 s11;
1991 c.459 s221; 1997 c.541 s248]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_310-100">
          <num>310.100</num>
          <heading>Taxes to apply to property shown by assessment roll; furnishing certificate showing aggregate valuation of taxable property</heading>
          <content>
            <p>Each ad valorem
property tax of a taxing district shall apply to all the taxable property of
the district, or to all the taxable property in a tax zone of a district that
has established two or more tax zones within the district, as shown by the
assessment roll last compiled by the assessor. The assessor, upon the
application of the governing body or of the duly accredited officer of any such
taxing district, shall furnish a certificate, properly verified, showing the
aggregate valuation of the taxable property therein. [Amended by 1991 c.459 s222;
1997 c.541 s250; 2001 c.246 s8; 2001 c.553 s6]</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_310-105">
          <num>310.105</num>
          <heading>Rate adjustments to reflect nontimber offsets; no effect on permanent or statutory rate limits</heading>
          <subsection eId="310-105__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If a taxing district lying in two or more
counties is entitled to offsets which have been provided by statute, the rates
determined under ORS 310.090 shall be further adjusted to reflect the offsets.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-105__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Adjustments under this section shall be made to ensure that the rate of
taxation is uniform throughout the taxing district.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-105__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Adjustments made under this section shall not affect the permanent rate limit
determined for purposes of section 11</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-105__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>, Article XI of the Oregon
Constitution, or the statutory rate limit determined in ORS 310.236</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-105__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <paragraph eId="310-105__subsec_4__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or
310.237, if applicable.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_310-110">
          <num>310.110</num>
          <heading>Apportionment of taxes where taxing district lies in two or more counties; estimates</heading>
          <subsection eId="310-110__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If a taxing district lies in two or more counties, and the district
certifies an item of ad valorem property tax as an amount in the notice
required under ORS 310.060, the amount certified by the district shall be
apportioned on the basis of the assessed value used to compute the tax rate for
the current tax year, in the proportion that the assessed value of the part of
the district lying in each county bears to the assessed value of the whole
district. However, if a boundary change affecting the district becomes
effective as to the levy being apportioned, an adjustment of the assessed value
shall be made so as to reflect the boundary change.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-110__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any assessor who is unable to certify the current assessed value for any joint
district lying partially in the county by September 25 shall, with the cooperation
of the Department of Revenue, estimate as closely as practicable the assessed
value of that district for the purpose of apportioning the ad valorem property
taxes of the joint district in the current year as equitably as is possible.
The estimate shall be completed and certified to the assessor or assessors of
the other counties on the fifth business day after September 25 and shall be
used as the basis for the apportionment required by this section. [Amended by
1953 c.194 s2; 1963 c.274 s1; 1967 c.199 s1; 1971 c.482 s1; 1977 c.892 s38;
1979 c.438 s5; 1981 c.804 s86; 1985 c.613 s5; 1991 c.459 s223; 1997 c.541 s254;
1999 c.1078 s69; 2003 c.621 s94]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_310-140">
          <num>310.140</num>
          <heading>Legislative findings; definitions</heading>
          <subsection eId="310-140__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Legislative Assembly finds that
Article XI, section 11b, of the Oregon Constitution, was drafted by citizens
and placed before the voters of the State of Oregon by initiative petition. Article
XI, section 11b, of the Oregon Constitution, uses terms that do not have
established legal meanings and require definition by the Legislative Assembly.
Article XI, section 11b, of the Oregon Constitution, was amended by Article XI,
section 11</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-140__subsec_11">
            <num>(11)</num>
            <content>
              <p>, of the Oregon Constitution. This section is intended to
interpret the terms of Article XI, section 11b, of the Oregon Constitution, as
originally adopted and as amended by Article XI, section 11</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-140__subsec_11">
            <num>(11)</num>
            <content>
              <p>, of the Oregon
Constitution, consistent with the intent of the people in adopting these
provisions, so that the provisions of Article XI, section 11b, of the Oregon
Constitution, may be given effect uniformly throughout the State of Oregon,
with minimal confusion and misunderstanding by citizens and affected units of
government. As used in the revenue and tax laws of this state, and for purposes
of Article XI, section 11b, of the Oregon Constitution:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="310-140__subsec_11__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <subparagraph eId="310-140__subsec_11__subsec_a__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>“Actual cost” means all direct or indirect costs incurred by a government unit
in order to deliver goods or services or to undertake a capital construction
project. The “actual cost” of providing goods or services to a property or
property owner includes the average cost or an allocated portion of the total
amount of the actual cost of making a good or service available to the property
or property owner, whether stated as a minimum, fixed or variable amount.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="310-140__subsec_11__subsec_a__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>“Actual cost” includes, but is not limited to, the costs of labor, materials,
supplies, equipment rental, property acquisition, permits, engineering, financing,
reasonable program delinquencies, return on investment, required fees,
insurance, administration, accounting, depreciation, amortization, operation,
maintenance, repair or replacement and debt service, including debt service
payments or payments into reserve accounts for debt service and payment of
amounts necessary to meet debt service coverage requirements.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-140__subsec_11__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>“Assessment for local improvement” means any tax, fee, charge or assessment
that does not exceed the actual cost incurred by a unit of government for
design, construction and financing of a local improvement.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-140__subsec_11__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>“Bonded indebtedness” means any formally executed written agreement representing
a promise by a unit of government to pay to another a specified sum of money,
at a specified date or dates at least one year in the future.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-140__subsec_11__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <subparagraph eId="310-140__subsec_11__subsec_d__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>“Capital construction” means, for bonded indebtedness issued prior to December
5, 1996, and for the proceeds of any bonded indebtedness approved by electors
prior to December 5, 1996, that were spent or contractually obligated to be
spent prior to June 20, 1997, the construction, modification, replacement,
repair, remodeling or renovation of a structure, or addition to a structure,
that is expected to have a useful life of more than one year, and includes, but
is not limited to:</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-140__subsec_11__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Acquisition of land, or a legal interest in land, in conjunction with the
capital construction of a structure.
(ii)
Acquisition, installation of machinery or equipment, furnishings or materials
that will become an integral part of a structure.
(iii)
Activities related to the capital construction, including planning, design,
authorizing, issuing, carrying or repaying interim or permanent financing,
research, land use and environmental impact studies, acquisition of permits or
licenses or other services connected with the construction.
(iv)
Acquisition of existing structures, or legal interests in structures, in
conjunction with the capital construction.</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="310-140__subsec_11__subsec_i__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>“Capital construction,” for bonded indebtedness issued on or after December 5,
1996, except for the proceeds of any bonded indebtedness approved by electors
prior to December 5, 1996, that were spent or contractually obligated to be
spent before June 20, 1997, has the meaning given that term in subparagraph</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="310-140__subsec_11__subsec_i__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>of this paragraph except as provided in subparagraphs</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="310-140__subsec_11__subsec_i__subsec_C">
                <num>(C)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>and</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="310-140__subsec_11__subsec_i__subsec_D">
                <num>(D)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>of this
paragraph.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="310-140__subsec_11__subsec_i__subsec_C">
                <num>(C)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>“Capital construction” includes public safety and law enforcement vehicles with
a projected useful life of five years or more.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="310-140__subsec_11__subsec_i__subsec_D">
                <num>(D)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>“Capital construction” does not include:</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-140__subsec_11__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Maintenance and repairs, the need for which could be reasonably anticipated;
(ii)
Supplies and equipment that are not intrinsic to the structure; or
(iii)
Furnishings, unless the furnishings are acquired in connection with the
acquisition, construction, remodeling or renovation of a structure, or the
repair of a structure that is required because of damage or destruction of the
structure.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-140__subsec_11__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <subparagraph eId="310-140__subsec_11__subsec_e__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>“Capital costs” means costs of land and of other assets having a useful life of
more than one year, including costs associated with acquisition, construction,
improvement, remodeling, furnishing, equipping, maintenance or repair.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="310-140__subsec_11__subsec_e__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>“Capital costs” does not include costs of routine maintenance or supplies.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-140__subsec_11__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <subparagraph eId="310-140__subsec_11__subsec_f__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>“Capital improvements” means, for bonded indebtedness issued prior to December
5, 1996, and for the proceeds of any bonded indebtedness approved by electors
before December 5, 1996, that were spent or contractually obligated to be spent
before June 20, 1997, land, structures, facilities, personal property that is
functionally related and subordinate to real property, machinery, equipment or
furnishings having a useful life longer than one year.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="310-140__subsec_11__subsec_f__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>“Capital improvements,” for bonded indebtedness issued on or after December 5,
1996, except for the proceeds of any bonded indebtedness approved by electors
prior to December 5, 1996, that were spent or contractually obligated to be
spent before June 20, 1997, has the meaning given that term in subparagraph</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="310-140__subsec_11__subsec_f__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>of this paragraph except as provided in subparagraphs</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="310-140__subsec_11__subsec_f__subsec_C">
                <num>(C)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>and</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="310-140__subsec_11__subsec_f__subsec_D">
                <num>(D)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>of this
paragraph.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="310-140__subsec_11__subsec_f__subsec_C">
                <num>(C)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>“Capital improvements” includes public safety and law enforcement vehicles with
a projected useful life of five years or more.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="310-140__subsec_11__subsec_f__subsec_D">
                <num>(D)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>“Capital improvements” does not include:</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-140__subsec_11__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Maintenance and repairs, the need for which could be reasonably anticipated;
(ii)
Supplies and equipment that are not intrinsic to the structure; or
(iii)
Furnishings, unless the furnishings are acquired in connection with the
acquisition, construction, remodeling or renovation of a structure, or the
repair of a structure that is required because of damage or destruction of the
structure.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-140__subsec_11__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>“Direct consequence of ownership” means that the obligation of the owner of
property to pay a tax arises solely because that person is the owner of the
property, and the obligation to pay the tax arises as an immediate and
necessary result of that ownership without respect to any other intervening
transaction, condition or event.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-140__subsec_11__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <subparagraph eId="310-140__subsec_11__subsec_h__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>“Exempt bonded indebtedness” means:</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-140__subsec_11__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Bonded indebtedness authorized by a specific provision of the Oregon
Constitution;
(ii)
Bonded indebtedness incurred or to be incurred for capital construction or
capital improvements that was issued as a general obligation of the issuing
governmental unit on or before November 6, 1990;
(iii)
Bonded indebtedness incurred or to be incurred for capital construction or
capital improvements that was issued as a general obligation of the issuing
governmental unit after November 6, 1990, with the approval of the electors of
the issuing governmental unit prior to December 5, 1996;
(iv)
Bonded indebtedness incurred or to be incurred for capital construction or
capital improvements if the issuance of the bonds is approved by voters on or
after December 5, 1996, in an election that is in compliance with the voter
participation requirements of Article XI, section 11</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-140__subsec_8">
            <num>(8)</num>
            <content>
              <p>, of the Oregon
Constitution, or if the issuance of the bonds is approved by voters on or after
December 4, 2008, in an election that is in compliance with the voter
participation requirements of Article XI, section 11</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-140__subsec_8">
            <num>(8)</num>
            <content>
              <p>, of the Oregon
Constitution, as limited by Article XI, section 11k, of the Oregon Constitution;
or</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="310-140__subsec_8__subsec_v">
              <num>(v)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Bonded indebtedness incurred or to be incurred for capital costs on or after
January 1, 2011, if the issuance of the bonds is approved by voters in an
election that is in compliance with the voter participation requirements of
Article XI, section 11</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-140__subsec_8">
            <num>(8)</num>
            <content>
              <p>, of the Oregon Constitution, as limited by Article
XI, section 11k, of the Oregon Constitution.
(B)
“Exempt bonded indebtedness” includes bonded indebtedness issued to refund or
refinance any bonded indebtedness described in subparagraph (A) of this
paragraph.</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="310-140__subsec_8__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>“Incurred charge” means a charge imposed by a unit of government on property or
upon a property owner that does not exceed the actual cost of providing goods
or services and that can be controlled or avoided by the property owner
because:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="310-140__subsec_8__subsec_i__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The charge is based on the quantity of the goods or services used, and the
owner has direct control over the quantity;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="310-140__subsec_8__subsec_i__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The goods or services are provided only on the specific request of the property
owner; or</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="310-140__subsec_8__subsec_i__subsec_C">
                <num>(C)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The goods or services are provided by the government unit only after the
individual property owner has failed to meet routine obligations of ownership
of the affected property, and such action is deemed necessary by an appropriate
government unit to enforce regulations pertaining to health or safety.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-140__subsec_8__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>“Local improvement” means a capital construction project, or part thereof,
undertaken by a local government, pursuant to ORS 223.387 to 223.399, or
pursuant to a local ordinance or resolution prescribing the procedure to be
followed in making local assessments for benefits from a local improvement upon
the lots that have been benefited by all or a part of the improvement:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="310-140__subsec_8__subsec_j__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>That provides a special benefit only to specific properties or rectifies a
problem caused by specific properties;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="310-140__subsec_8__subsec_j__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The costs of which are assessed against those properties in a single assessment
upon the completion of the project; and</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="310-140__subsec_8__subsec_j__subsec_C">
                <num>(C)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>For which the property owner may elect to make payment of the assessment plus
appropriate interest over a period of at least 10 years.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-140__subsec_8__subsec_k">
              <num>(k)</num>
              <subparagraph eId="310-140__subsec_8__subsec_k__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>“Maintenance and repairs, the need for which could be reasonably anticipated”
means activities, the type of which may be deducted as an expense under the
provisions of the federal Internal Revenue Code, as defined in ORS 305.842,
that keep the property in ordinarily efficient operating condition and that do
not add materially to the value of the property nor appreciably prolong the
life of the property.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="310-140__subsec_8__subsec_k__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>“Maintenance and repairs, the need for which could be reasonably anticipated”
does not include:</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-140__subsec_8__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Maintenance and repair of property that is required by damage, destruction or
defect in design, or that was otherwise not reasonably expected at the time the
property was constructed or acquired, or the addition of material that is in the
nature of the replacement of property and that arrests the deterioration or
appreciably prolongs the useful life of the property; and
(ii)
Street and highway construction, overlay and reconstruction.</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="310-140__subsec_8__subsec_i__subsec_L">
                <num>(L)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>“Projected useful life” means the useful life, as reasonably estimated by the
unit of government undertaking the capital construction or capital improvement
project, beginning with the date the property was acquired, constructed or
reconstructed and based on the property’s condition at the time the property
was acquired, constructed or reconstructed.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-140__subsec_8__subsec_m">
              <num>(m)</num>
              <content>
                <p>“Routine obligations of ownership” means a standard of operation, maintenance,
use or care of property established by law, or if established by custom or
common law, a standard that is reasonable for the type of property affected.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-140__subsec_8__subsec_n">
              <num>(n)</num>
              <content>
                <p>“Single assessment” means the complete assessment process, including
preassessment, assessment or reassessment, for any local improvement authorized
by ORS 223.387 to 223.399, or a local ordinance or resolution that provides the
procedure to be followed in making local assessments for benefits from a local
improvement upon lots that have been benefited by all or part of the
improvement.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-140__subsec_8__subsec_o">
              <num>(o)</num>
              <content>
                <p>“Special benefit only to specific properties” shall have the same meaning as “special
and peculiar benefit” as that term is used in ORS 223.389.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-140__subsec_8__subsec_p">
              <num>(p)</num>
              <content>
                <p>“Specific request” means:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="310-140__subsec_8__subsec_p__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>An affirmative act by a property owner to seek or obtain delivery of goods or
services;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="310-140__subsec_8__subsec_p__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>An affirmative act by a property owner, the legal consequence of which is to
cause the delivery of goods or services to the property owner; or</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="310-140__subsec_8__subsec_p__subsec_C">
                <num>(C)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Failure of an owner of property to change a request for goods or services made
by a prior owner of the property.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-140__subsec_8__subsec_q">
              <num>(q)</num>
              <content>
                <p>“Structure” means any temporary or permanent building or improvement to real
property of any kind that is constructed on or attached to real property,
whether above, on or beneath the surface.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-140__subsec_8__subsec_r">
              <num>(r)</num>
              <content>
                <p>“Supplies and equipment intrinsic to a structure” means the supplies and
equipment that are necessary to permit a structure to perform the functions for
which the structure was constructed, or that will, upon installation,
constitute fixtures considered to be part of the real property that is
composed, in whole or part, of the structure and land supporting the structure.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-140__subsec_8__subsec_s">
              <num>(s)</num>
              <content>
                <p>“Tax on property” means any tax, fee, charge or assessment imposed by any
government unit upon property or upon a property owner as a direct consequence
of ownership of that property, but does not include incurred charges or
assessments for local improvements. As used in this paragraph, “property” means
real or tangible personal property, and intangible property that is part of a
unit of real or tangible personal property to the extent that such intangible property
is subject to a tax on property.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-140__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For purposes of subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-140__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <paragraph eId="310-140__subsec_1__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this section, an owner of property may
control or avoid an incurred charge if the owner is capable of taking action to
affect the amount of a charge that is or will be imposed or to avoid imposition
of a charge even if the owner must incur expense in so doing.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-140__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For purposes of subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-140__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <paragraph eId="310-140__subsec_1__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <subparagraph eId="310-140__subsec_1__subsec_i__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>of this section, an owner of property has
direct control over the quantity of goods or services if the owner of property
has the ability, whether or not that ability is exercised, to determine the
quantity of goods or services provided or to be provided.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-140__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For purposes of subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-140__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <paragraph eId="310-140__subsec_1__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this section, the status of a capital
construction project as a local improvement is not affected by the accrual of a
general benefit to property other than the property receiving the special
benefit.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_310-143">
          <num>310.143</num>
          <heading>Certification of taxes on taxable property subject to 1990 Measure 5 limits; refunds of taxes on property not certified, erroneously certified or certified by nongovernmental entity</heading>
          <subsection eId="310-143__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any tax on property that is imposed on property
that is subject to ad valorem taxation by any unit of local government shall be
certified to the assessor each year, as provided under ORS 310.060. Except as
otherwise specifically provided by law, any tax, fee, charge or assessment that
is not a tax on property or is not imposed on property subject to ad valorem
taxation shall not be certified to the assessor. Each tax certified shall be
certified in whichever of the following forms is applicable:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="310-143__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In dollars and cents in either the total amount to be raised from all property
in the unit;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-143__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In dollars and cents per property; or</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-143__subsec_1__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>As a rate per $1,000 of assessed value.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-143__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any unit of local government imposes on property that is subject to ad
valorem taxation a tax on property, as defined in ORS 310.140, that is not
certified to the assessor under ORS 310.060 for imposition and collection, and
a court of competent jurisdiction determines that the tax is subject to the
limits of section 11b, Article XI of the Oregon Constitution, the unit of local
government shall pay any refunds ordered by the court. No refunds shall be paid
from the unsegregated tax collections account, and the assessor shall not be
required to redetermine the amount of other taxes imposed on any property that
also is subject to the challenged tax.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-143__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding ORS 311.806, when any unit of local government certifies a tax
on property to be collected by the tax collector, and the amount of the tax on
individual properties is calculated by the unit of local government, any claim
for refund of such taxes due to an error in calculation of the amount of the
tax shall be made to the unit of local government within the same time and in
the same manner as claims for refund are to be made under ORS 311.806. The unit
of local government shall pay any refunds it determines to be due to errors in
calculation of the amount of the tax out of the funds available to the unit of
local government. Such refunds shall not be paid from the unsegregated tax
collections account, and the assessor shall not be required to redetermine the
amount of other taxes imposed on the property for which the refund is made.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-143__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding ORS 311.806, when any entity that is not a unit of local
government certifies an amount specifically authorized by law to be included on
the roll to be collected by the tax collector, and the amount on individual
properties is calculated by the entity, any claim for refund of the amount due
to an error in calculation of the amount shall be made to the entity within the
same time and in the same manner as claims for refunds are to be made under ORS
311.806</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-143__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>. The entity shall pay any refunds it determines to be due to errors
in calculation of the amount out of the funds available to the entity. The
refunds shall not be paid from the unsegregated tax collections account, and
the assessor shall not be required to redetermine the amount of other taxes
imposed on the property for which the refund is made.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_310-145">
          <num>310.145</num>
          <heading>Ordinance or resolution classifying and categorizing taxes subject to 1990 Measure 5 limits</heading>
          <subsection eId="310-145__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Each unit of local government that imposes a tax, fee, charge or assessment
may adopt an ordinance or resolution classifying all or any of the taxes, fees,
charges and assessments it imposes as being in one or more of the following
categories:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="310-145__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Taxes on property subject to the limits of section 11b, Article XI of the
Oregon Constitution, and within this category, those taxes that are dedicated
to funding the public school system, and those that are imposed to support
other government operations.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-145__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Incurred charges.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-145__subsec_1__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Assessments for local improvements.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-145__subsec_1__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Taxes to pay principal and interest on exempt bonded indebtedness.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-145__subsec_1__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>All other taxes, fees, charges and assessments that are not subject to the
limits of section 11b, Article XI of the Oregon Constitution.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-145__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An ordinance or resolution adopted under this section shall serve as notice of
the classification of taxes, fees, charges and assessments for purposes of ORS
305.580 to 305.591.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_310-147">
          <num>310.147</num>
          <heading>Code area system; tentative consolidated tax rates per category; total consolidated code area rates after adjustment; recordation on assessment roll</heading>
          <subsection eId="310-147__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Each year,
the county assessor shall establish a system of code areas, identified by code
numbers, which shall represent all of the various combinations of taxing
districts, or tax zones of taxing districts in which district taxes differ, as
of July 1 of that year in which a piece of property was located in the county
on January 1 of that year.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-147__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The assessor shall compute a tentative consolidated ad valorem property tax
rate for each code area. The tentative consolidated ad valorem property tax
rate for the code area shall be determined for each category under ORS 310.150.
The tentative consolidated ad valorem property tax rate for each category for
the code area shall be the sum of the category rates determined under ORS
310.090 for each taxing district in the code area.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-147__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <paragraph eId="310-147__subsec_3__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The assessor shall compute the consolidated category rate for each category
under ORS 310.150 using the ad valorem property taxes to be imposed on each
property after adjustment under ORS 310.150. In the case of the exempt bonded
indebtedness category, the tentative consolidated category rate for the code
area shall be the consolidated category rate for the code area.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-147__subsec_3__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The total consolidated rate for the code area shall equal the sum of the
consolidated rates for each category determined under paragraph</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-147__subsec_3__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this
subsection after adjustment under ORS 310.150.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-147__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The assessor shall indicate on the assessment roll the code area number for
each item of property assessed. In addition, the assessor shall compile in
duplicate a list of all code areas and their numbers and identify for each area
the names of each taxing district in the area, the rate, after adjustment under
ORS 310.150, for each item of the taxing district reported on the notice filed
under ORS 310.060, the total rate for each taxing district and by category as
described in ORS 310.150 and the total consolidated rate for the code area. The
list shall constitute a part of the certificate prepared under ORS 311.105, to
be delivered to the county clerk and to the tax collector. [Formerly 308.221;
2001 c.246 s9; 2001 c.553 s7; 2003 c.621 s104]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_310-150">
          <num>310.150</num>
          <heading>Segregation into categories; category limits; determination whether amount of taxes on property is within limits; method of reducing taxes to meet limits</heading>
          <subsection eId="310-150__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The three
categories within which ad valorem property tax items are to be categorized in
the notice to be filed under ORS 310.060 and for which category rates of ad
valorem property taxes are to be computed under ORS 310.090 and tentative
consolidated category rates are to be computed for each code area under ORS
310.147 are as follows:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="310-150__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Taxes levied or imposed for the purpose of funding exempt bonded indebtedness.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-150__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Taxes levied or imposed for the purpose of funding the public school system and
that are not described in paragraph</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-150__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this subsection.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-150__subsec_1__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Taxes levied or imposed for the purpose of funding government operations other
than public school system operations and that are not described in paragraph</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-150__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this subsection.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-150__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>After computation of the tentative ad valorem property tax consolidated rate
for each category under ORS 310.147, and after calculation of the amount of ad
valorem property taxes to be imposed on properties in the county, but before
extending any taxes on the assessment and tax roll, the assessor shall
determine whether the total amount of taxes on property to be imposed on each
property in the code area in each category is within the limits described in
subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-150__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-150__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <paragraph eId="310-150__subsec_3__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The assessor shall determine whether the ad valorem property taxes to be
imposed on any property exceed the limits described in this subsection in order
to ensure, as guaranteed in section 11</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-150__subsec_11">
            <num>(11)</num>
            <content>
              <p>and 11b, Article XI of the Oregon
Constitution, that taxes imposed in each geographic area taxed by the same
local taxing districts do not exceed $5 (public school system) and $10 (other
government) per $1,000 of real market value.</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="310-150__subsec_11__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For the category of taxes imposed for the purpose of funding the public school
system that are not for the purpose of paying principal and interest on exempt bonded
indebtedness, if the tentative consolidated ad valorem property tax rate
determined under subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-150__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section exceeds $5 per $1,000 of real
market value, the consolidated rate shall be adjusted as provided in this
section so that the consolidated rate for the public school system category
equals $5 per $1,000 of real market value.</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="310-150__subsec_2__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For the category of taxes imposed for the purpose of funding government
operations other than the public school system and that are not for the purpose
of paying principal and interest on exempt bonded indebtedness, if the
tentative consolidated ad valorem property tax rate exceeds $10 per $1,000 of
real market value, the consolidated rate shall be adjusted as provided in this
section so that the consolidated rate for the other government category equals
$10 per $1,000 of real market value.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-150__subsec_2__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For the category of taxes imposed for the purpose of paying principal and
interest on exempt bonded indebtedness, the tentative consolidated rate
determined under subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-150__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section shall be the consolidated rate
for the exempt bonded indebtedness category.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-150__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the taxes on property in either category to be imposed on any property in
the code area exceed the limit established for that category in subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-150__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section, the assessor shall reduce the taxes by applying a reduction
ratio.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-150__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <paragraph eId="310-150__subsec_5__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If local option taxes described under ORS 280.040 to 280.145 have been adopted
by one or more taxing districts in the code area, the reduction ratio shall be
calculated under this subsection and applied only to the local option taxes
imposed on the property for which the taxes are being determined.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-150__subsec_5__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Local option taxes subject to compression under this subsection include urban
renewal division of tax revenue that is derived from the division of local
option tax authority.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-150__subsec_5__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The numerator of the reduction ratio shall be the amount obtained (but not less
than zero) by subtracting the tentative consolidated category rate of ad
valorem property taxes that are not local option taxes from the maximum rate of
ad valorem property taxes for the category described in subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-150__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this
section.</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="310-150__subsec_3__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The denominator for the ratio shall be the total rate of all local option taxes
for the category.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-150__subsec_3__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The assessor shall multiply the reduction ratio determined under this
subsection by each local option tax amount to which the property is subject in
the category.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-150__subsec_3__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>So reduced, the assessor shall again determine if the total taxes for the
category to be imposed on the property exceed the limits described in
subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-150__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section. If the reduced taxes for the category do not
exceed the category limit, such taxes shall be the taxes used to compute the
consolidated rate for the code area in which the property is located. If the
reduced taxes for the category still exceed the category limit after all local
option taxes have been eliminated, the taxes in the category shall be subject
to further reduction under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-150__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-150__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <paragraph eId="310-150__subsec_6__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the property is not subject to local option taxes or if all local option
taxes have been eliminated as a result of the application of the reduction
ratio calculated under subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-150__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section, and the tentative
consolidated rate determined under ORS 310.147 for the category exceeds the
maximum rate of ad valorem property taxes for the category described in
subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-150__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section, the reduction ratio shall be determined under
this subsection.</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="310-150__subsec_3__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The numerator of the reduction ratio shall be the maximum rate permitted for
the category described in subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-150__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section.</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="310-150__subsec_3__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The denominator of the reduction ratio shall be the tentative consolidated
category rate under ORS 310.147 (or the category rate applicable to the
property after the reduction under subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-150__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section, if
applicable).</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="310-150__subsec_5__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The assessor shall multiply the reduction ratio determined under this
subsection by the amount of each taxing district item of ad valorem property
tax that is a component of the tentative consolidated category rate for the
code area in which the property is located.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-150__subsec_7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In determining whether the taxes described in subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-150__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <paragraph eId="310-150__subsec_1__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this section
exceed the limitation under subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-150__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <paragraph eId="310-150__subsec_3__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this section, all moneys
raised through the urban renewal special levy described in ORS 457.435 and all
moneys raised through the urban renewal division of tax, including amounts
derived from exempt bonded indebtedness authority and local option tax
authority, must be categorized as subject to the limitation described in
subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-150__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <paragraph eId="310-150__subsec_3__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_310-153">
          <num>310.153</num>
          <heading>Total amount to be raised for each taxing district and item; basis for assessor’s certificate</heading>
          <subsection eId="310-153__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The assessor shall determine the total amount to be raised for each taxing
district in the code area and, for the total amount for each taxing district,
the amount for each item that is listed in the taxing district’s notice filed
under ORS 310.060.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-153__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The amounts determined under this section shall serve as the basis for the
assessor’s certificate prepared under ORS 311.105. [1997 c.541 s263]
Note: 310.153 was
enacted into law by the Legislative Assembly but was not added to or made a
part of ORS chapter 310 or any series therein by legislative action. See
Preface to Oregon Revised Statutes for further explanation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_310-155">
          <num>310.155</num>
          <heading>Public school system limit; definitions</heading>
          <subsection eId="310-155__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For purposes of ORS 310.150, taxes
are levied or imposed to fund the public school system if the taxes will be
used exclusively for educational services, including support services, provided
by any unit of government, at any level from prekindergarten through
post-graduate training.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-155__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>As used in this section:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="310-155__subsec_2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <subparagraph eId="310-155__subsec_2__subsec_a__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>“Educational services” includes:</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-155__subsec_2__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Establishment and maintenance of preschools, kindergartens, elementary schools,
high schools, community colleges and the public universities listed in ORS
352.002.
(ii)
Establishment and maintenance of career schools, adult education programs,
evening school programs and schools or facilities for persons with physical,
mental or emotional disabilities.</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="310-155__subsec_2__subsec_i__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>“Educational services” does not include community recreation programs, civic
activities, public libraries, programs for custody or care of children or
community welfare activities if those programs or activities are provided to
the general public and not for the benefit of students or other participants in
the programs and activities described in subparagraph</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="310-155__subsec_2__subsec_i__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>of this paragraph.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-155__subsec_2__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>“Support services” includes clerical, administrative, professional and
managerial services, property maintenance, transportation, counseling, training
and other services customarily performed in connection with the delivery of
educational services.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_310-156">
          <num>310.156</num>
          <heading>Certain community college library limits</heading>
          <subsection eId="310-156__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding ORS 310.155
and for purposes of ORS 310.150, taxes levied or imposed by a community college
district to provide a public library system established prior to September 9,
1995, shall be considered to be levied or imposed for the purpose of funding
government operations other than the public school system.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-156__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>As used in this section, “public library system” has the meaning given the term
in ORS 357.400 (1993 Edition).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_310-160">
          <num>310.160</num>
          <heading>Unit of property; description for purposes of determining if amount of taxes exceeds 1990 Measure 5 limits</heading>
          <subsection eId="310-160__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For purposes of determining whether
the taxes on property to be imposed on any property exceed the limits imposed
by section 11b, Article XI of the Oregon Constitution, the unit of property to
be considered shall consist of all contiguous property within a single code
area in the county under common ownership that is used and appraised for a
single integrated purpose, whether or not that property is taxed as a single
account or multiple accounts.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-160__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the case of real property that is specially assessed under ORS 308A.107,
308A.256, 308A.315, 321.257 to 321.390 or 358.480 to 358.545 or any other law,
or partially exempt from tax under ORS 307.250 or 307.370 or any other law, the
unit of property shall consist of all components of land and improvements in a
single operating unit.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-160__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the case of timeshare properties, the unit of property shall consist of all
real property components associated with all timeshare property within a
timeshare plan as described in ORS 94.808.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-160__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the case of personal property that is not part of an operating unit
consisting of both real and personal property, the unit of property shall
consist of all items of personal property identified in a single property tax
account.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-160__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the case of land upon which an improvement is located, and the land and the
improvement are owned by different persons, if the land and improvements are a
single operating unit, the unit of property shall consist of the entire
improved parcel.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_310-165">
          <num>310.165</num>
          <heading>Partially exempt or specially assessed property; treatment of additional taxes imposed upon disqualification from special assessment or exemption</heading>
          <subsection eId="310-165__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For any unit
of property partially exempt from tax under ORS 307.250, 307.370 or 308.459 or
any other law, the assessor shall determine the maximum amount of taxes on
property to be imposed on such unit of property under ORS 310.150, by using the
lesser of the real market value or the taxable value of the unit of property
after the exemption has been applied.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-165__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For any unit of property that is specially assessed for ad valorem tax purposes
under ORS 308A.050 to 308A.128, 308A.250 to 308A.259, 308A.315, 321.257 to
321.390, 321.700 to 321.754, 321.805 to 321.855 or 358.480 to 358.545, the
assessor shall determine the maximum amount of taxes on property to be imposed
on such property under ORS 310.150 by using the lesser of the real market value
or the specially assessed value of the property.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-165__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the case of any unit of property of which a part of the unit is exempt from
taxation, and that part may be identified both as to value and physical
description, the real market value of the unit shall not include the value of
the exempt part of the unit.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-165__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This subsection applies to any unit of property described in subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-165__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>or</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-165__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section for which the maximum amount of taxes imposed has been
determined under this section. If the unit of property is subject to imposition
of additional taxes due to disqualification from special assessment or partial
exemption, the determination of the maximum amount of additional taxes that may
be imposed due to disqualification shall be made on the basis of the real
market value of the property for the year to which the additional taxes relate.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_310-170">
          <num>310.170</num>
          <heading>Allocation by districts of distributions from unsegregated tax collections account among taxes subject to 1990 Measure 5 limits</heading>
          <content>
            <p>If any taxing
district certifies for levy or imposition under ORS 310.060 more than one tax
subject to the limits of section 11b, Article XI of the Oregon Constitution,
and receives distributions from the unsegregated tax collections account in an
amount that is less than the total amount of taxes so certified, the taxing
district may allocate the funds distributed to it among the taxes so certified.
No taxing district may allocate funds to any one tax in an amount greater than
the amount the district certified for levy or imposition under ORS 310.060
during the period for which the tax is imposed.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_310-190">
          <num>310.190</num>
          <heading>Effect of election challenge on tax; resolution of challenge</heading>
          <subsection eId="310-190__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If a
challenge has been filed under ORS 258.016</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-190__subsec_7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>, any tax that was authorized by
the election shall not be extended on the assessment and tax roll until the
challenge has been resolved.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-190__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If a challenge is resolved so that the contested election is determined to be
valid and all appeals of the resolution also resolved, or rights to appeal
expired, the tax that was authorized by the election shall be extended on the
roll for the first tax year following the date of resolution.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-190__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The tax shall be extended for the same number of years as the tax would have
been imposed had the challenge not occurred.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_310-193">
          <num>310.193</num>
          <heading>Taxing district duty to notify assessor of challenge</heading>
          <content>
            <p>A taxing district
that has received notice of a challenge to one of the district’s elections
under ORS 258.016 shall notify the assessor of the filing of the challenge and
of the resolution of the challenge. [1997 c.541 s319]
(Calculation
of 1997 Measure 50 Permanent and Supplemental Statutory Rate Limits on
Operating Taxes and 1997-1998 Tax Reductions)</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_310-200">
          <num>310.200</num>
          <heading>Purpose</heading>
          <content>
            <p>The purpose of ORS 310.200 to 310.242 is to set forth the procedure by which
tax reductions caused by implementation of section 11, Article XI of the Oregon
Constitution, and caused by additional statutory reductions, for the tax year
beginning July 1, 1997, are to be distributed to the property taxpayers and
taxing districts of this state and to derive each district’s permanent rate
limit for operating taxes and statutory rate limit for operating taxes for tax
years beginning on or after July 1, 1997.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_310-202">
          <num>310.202</num>
          <heading>Definitions for ORS 310.200 to 310.242</heading>
          <subsection eId="310-202__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Local option taxes” means taxes described under section 11</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-202__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>or</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-202__subsec_7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <paragraph eId="310-202__subsec_7__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>,
Article XI of the Oregon Constitution, and does not include serial levies or
continuing levies first imposed in the tax year beginning July 1, 1997, that
merely replace serial or one-year levies imposed in the tax year beginning July
1, 1996.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-202__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Measure 5 assessed value rate” means the rate determined under ORS 310.238.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-202__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Measure 5 imposed tax estimate” means the amount determined under ORS 310.210
solely for purposes of tax reduction distribution and is not the amount of tax
actually to be imposed on property for the tax year.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-202__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Measure 5 value” means the real market value of taxable property that is not
subject to special assessment or the specially assessed value of property
subject to special assessment.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-202__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Measure 47 comparison taxes” means taxes calculated under ORS 310.212. The
Legislative Assembly is expressly not adopting by reference any provision of
repealed Ballot Measure 47</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-202__subsec_1996">
            <num>(1996)</num>
            <content>
              <p>under ORS 310.200 to 310.242.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-202__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Operating taxes” has the meaning given that term in ORS 310.055.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-202__subsec_7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Permanent rate limit on operating taxes” means a taxing district’s maximum
rate of operating taxes allowed under section 11</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-202__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>, Article XI of the Oregon
Constitution.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-202__subsec_8">
            <num>(8)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Pre-reduction Measure 50 taxes” means the amount determined by subtracting
those taxes not subject to reduction under section 11</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-202__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>, Article XI of the
Oregon Constitution, from the Measure 5 imposed tax estimate.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-202__subsec_9">
            <num>(9)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Qualified taxing district obligations” means any portion of a local taxing
district levy that is used to repay:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="310-202__subsec_9__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Principal and interest for any bond issued before December 5, 1996, and secured
by a pledge or explicit commitment of ad valorem property taxes or a covenant
to levy or collect ad valorem property taxes;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-202__subsec_9__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Principal and interest for any other formal, written borrowing of moneys
executed before December 5, 1996, for which ad valorem property tax revenues have
been pledged or explicitly committed, or that are secured by a covenant to levy
or collect ad valorem property taxes;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-202__subsec_9__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Principal and interest for any bond issued to refund an obligation described in
paragraph</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-202__subsec_9__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-202__subsec_9__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this subsection; or</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-202__subsec_9__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Local government pension and disability plan obligations that commit ad valorem
property taxes and the ad valorem property taxes imposed to fulfill those
obligations.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-202__subsec_10">
            <num>(10)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Statutory rate limit on operating taxes” means the maximum rate of operating
taxes that may be imposed after supplemental statutory reduction under ORS
310.222</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-202__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-202__subsec_11">
            <num>(11)</num>
            <content>
              <p>“Urban renewal increment” has the meaning given the term “increment” in ORS
457.010.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_310-204">
          <num>310.204</num>
          <heading>“Hospital facility” defined</heading>
          <subsection eId="310-204__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>, Article XI of the Oregon Constitution, the term “hospital
facility” means a facility with an organized medical staff, with permanent
facilities that include inpatient beds, and with medical services, including
physician services and continuous nursing services under the supervision of
registered nurses, providing diagnosis and medical or surgical treatment
primarily for but not limited to acutely ill patients and accident victims. [1997
c.541 s266; 2005 c.94 s62]
Note: 310.204 was added
to and made a part of ORS chapter 310 by legislative action but was not added
to any smaller series therein. See Preface to Oregon Revised Statutes for
further explanation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_310-206">
          <num>310.206</num>
          <heading>1997-1998 tax certification notice</heading>
          <subsection eId="310-206__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding ORS 310.060, for the
tax year beginning July 1, 1997, the notice required under ORS 310.060 shall be
as provided in this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-206__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every city, school district or other public corporation authorized to levy or
impose a tax on property shall file a notice in writing of the ad valorem
property tax levy made by it and any other taxes on property imposed by it on
property subject to ad valorem property taxation that is required or authorized
to be placed on the assessment and tax roll for the current fiscal year. The
notice shall be accompanied by a copy of a lawfully adopted ordinance or
resolution that categorizes the tax, fee, charge, assessment or toll as subject
to or not subject to the limits of section 11b, Article XI of the Oregon
Constitution, identified by the categories set forth in ORS 310.150.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-206__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For any ad valorem property taxes levied by the taxing district, the notice
shall state as a separate item:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="310-206__subsec_3__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The total amount of money, prior to reduction under section 11</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-206__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>, Article XI
of the Oregon Constitution, that the taxing district would have been entitled
to levy under the property tax laws of this state as described in ORS 310.210</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-206__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>;</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="310-206__subsec_2__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the taxing district is a taxing district other than a city, county or school
district:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="310-206__subsec_2__subsec_b__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The amount of the levy that is used to support a hospital facility; and</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="310-206__subsec_2__subsec_b__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The amount of any levy certified in the tax year beginning July 1, 1995, that
was used to support a hospital facility;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-206__subsec_2__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The amount of any levy of ad valorem property taxes that is not subject to
constitutional reduction because the levy is described in section 11</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-206__subsec_7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <paragraph eId="310-206__subsec_7__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>,
Article XI of the Oregon Constitution;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-206__subsec_7__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The amount of any serial or one-year levy that replaces an existing serial or
one-year levy approved by a majority of the voters voting on the question in an
election held on or after December 5, 1996, and first imposed for a tax year
beginning on July 1, 1997, if the rate or the amount of the levy is not greater
than the rate or amount of the levy replaced;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-206__subsec_7__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The total rate or amount of the taxing district’s local option tax that is
imposed pursuant to ORS 280.040 to 280.145 or that is treated as a local option
tax under section 11</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-206__subsec_7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <paragraph eId="310-206__subsec_7__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>, Article XI of the Oregon Constitution, and the
date the local option tax was approved by voters;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-206__subsec_7__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The amount levied for the payment of exempt bonded indebtedness or interest
thereon that is not subject to limitation under section 11</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-206__subsec_11">
            <num>(11)</num>
            <content>
              <p>or section 11b,
Article XI of the Oregon Constitution;</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="310-206__subsec_11__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The amount levied to pay qualified taxing district obligations, identifying the
extent to which the amount levied is to be used to repay:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="310-206__subsec_11__subsec_g__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Principal and interest for any bond issued before December 5, 1996, and secured
by a pledge or explicit commitment of ad valorem property taxes or a covenant
to levy or collect ad valorem property taxes;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="310-206__subsec_11__subsec_g__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Principal and interest for any other formal, written borrowing of moneys
executed before December 5, 1996, for which ad valorem property tax revenues
have been pledged or explicitly committed, or that are secured by a covenant to
levy or collect ad valorem property taxes;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="310-206__subsec_11__subsec_g__subsec_C">
                <num>(C)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Principal and interest for any bond issued to refund an obligation described in
subparagraph</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="310-206__subsec_11__subsec_g__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>or</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="310-206__subsec_11__subsec_g__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>of this paragraph; or</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="310-206__subsec_11__subsec_g__subsec_D">
                <num>(D)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Local government pension and disability plan obligations that commit ad valorem
property taxes and the ad valorem property taxes imposed to fulfill those
obligations; and</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-206__subsec_11__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For any levy certified under paragraph</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-206__subsec_11__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this subsection, the amount
levied to pay the same qualified obligation (or a predecessor obligation that
has been refunded by the current qualified obligation) in the tax year
beginning July 1, 1995.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-206__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <paragraph eId="310-206__subsec_4__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the taxing district chooses not to levy the entire amount that the taxing
district would have been entitled to levy under subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-206__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <paragraph eId="310-206__subsec_3__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this
section, the taxing district shall state the amount as prescribed in subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-206__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <paragraph eId="310-206__subsec_3__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this section under the heading “For Permanent Rate Limit
Determination Only.”</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-206__subsec_3__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The taxing district shall then state the lesser amount that the district has
determined as the maximum amount to be raised for operating tax purposes for
the tax year beginning July 1, 1997, under the heading “1997-1998 Operating Tax
Amount.”</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-206__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <paragraph eId="310-206__subsec_5__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The notice shall also list each rate or amount subject to the limits of section
11b, Article XI of the Oregon Constitution, identified by the categories set
forth in ORS 310.150.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-206__subsec_5__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If an item as described in subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-206__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section is allocable to more
than one category under ORS 310.150, then notwithstanding subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-206__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of
this section, the notice shall list as a separate item each portion that is
allocable to a category.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-206__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The notice and the taxing district filing the notice shall comply with ORS
310.060</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-206__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_310-208">
          <num>310.208</num>
          <heading>1997-1998 urban renewal certification</heading>
          <subsection eId="310-208__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding ORS 457.440, for the
tax year beginning July 1, 1997, an urban renewal agency shall certify to the
assessor for each urban renewal plan the amount that would have been certified
under ORS 457.440 (1995 Edition) and the other laws of this state applicable to
the certification as set forth in Oregon Revised Statutes (1995 Edition) and as
further modified by the laws of this state applicable to the tax year beginning
July 1, 1997, other than:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="310-208__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Section 11, Article XI of the Oregon Constitution, and the other provisions of
House Joint Resolution 85</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-208__subsec_1997">
            <num>(1997)</num>
            <content>
              <p>(Ballot Measure 50</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-208__subsec_1997">
            <num>(1997)</num>
            <content>
              <p>); and</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="310-208__subsec_1997__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>ORS 310.212 to 310.242.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-208__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the urban renewal plan is an existing urban renewal plan, as defined in ORS
457.010, the urban renewal agency shall include in the certification a notice
of a potential special levy made by the municipality, as defined in ORS
457.010, as permitted under section 11</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-208__subsec_16">
            <num>(16)</num>
            <content>
              <p>, Article XI of the Oregon
Constitution, in an amount to be subsequently determined under ORS 310.240</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-208__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>.
If the urban renewal plan is not an existing urban renewal plan, no special
levy described in this subsection shall be made.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-208__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For purposes of making the certification described in this section, the real
market value of property shall be determined as provided in section 11</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-208__subsec_11">
            <num>(11)</num>
            <paragraph eId="310-208__subsec_11__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <subparagraph eId="310-208__subsec_11__subsec_a__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>, Article XI of the Oregon Constitution.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_310-210">
          <num>310.210</num>
          <heading>Measure 5 imposed tax estimate</heading>
          <subsection eId="310-210__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>After the assessor has received all
certifications of levy under ORS 310.206 for the tax year beginning July 1,
1997, the assessor shall first calculate the Measure 5 imposed tax estimate
under this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-210__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The assessor shall compute ad valorem property taxes on each property under the
property tax laws of this state as set forth in the Oregon Revised Statutes
(1995 Edition), including section 11, Article XI of the Oregon Constitution
(1995 Edition), as further modified by the property tax laws of this state
applicable to the tax year beginning July 1, 1997, except for the following
laws:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="310-210__subsec_2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Section 11, Article XI of the Oregon Constitution, and the other provisions of
House Joint Resolution 85</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-210__subsec_1997">
            <num>(1997)</num>
            <content>
              <p>(Ballot Measure 50</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-210__subsec_1997">
            <num>(1997)</num>
            <content>
              <p>);</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="310-210__subsec_1997__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>ORS 310.212 to 310.242; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-210__subsec_1997__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Any provision of law requiring an offset against a local taxing district levy.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-210__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The amount of taxes determined under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-210__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section for each
property shall be the property’s Measure 5 imposed tax estimate. The amount
determined for each district shall be the district’s Measure 5 imposed tax
estimate.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-210__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In calculating the Measure 5 imposed tax estimate, the assessor shall not take
into account any local option taxes that have been certified under ORS 310.206.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-210__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For purposes of calculating the Measure 5 imposed tax estimate under this
section, the real market value of property shall be determined as provided in
section 11</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-210__subsec_11">
            <num>(11)</num>
            <paragraph eId="310-210__subsec_11__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <subparagraph eId="310-210__subsec_11__subsec_a__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>, Article XI of the Oregon Constitution.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_310-212">
          <num>310.212</num>
          <heading>Measure 47 comparison taxes</heading>
          <subsection eId="310-212__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The assessor shall determine Measure
47 comparison taxes for each property under this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-212__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <paragraph eId="310-212__subsec_2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The assessor shall subtract the following taxes from the ad valorem property
taxes imposed on each property for the tax year beginning July 1, 1995:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="310-212__subsec_2__subsec_a__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Taxes imposed to pay principal and interest on exempt bonded indebtedness;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="310-212__subsec_2__subsec_a__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Urban renewal taxes; and</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="310-212__subsec_2__subsec_a__subsec_C">
                <num>(C)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Taxes imposed to pay qualified taxing district obligations, as calculated under
subsection</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-212__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section.</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="310-212__subsec_3__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The assessor shall calculate the dollar value of offsets against ad valorem
property taxes for the tax year beginning July 1, 1995, and shall add to the
amount determined under paragraph</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-212__subsec_3__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this subsection each property’s share
of such offsets if:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="310-212__subsec_3__subsec_a__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The county contains a taxing district with offsets from appeals for the tax
year beginning July 1, 1995, that exceed 10 percent of the district’s net levy
for the tax year beginning July 1, 1995; and</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="310-212__subsec_3__subsec_a__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The taxing district is not a school district, education service district,
community college or community college service district.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-212__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <paragraph eId="310-212__subsec_3__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The amount subtracted for qualified taxing district obligations under
subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-212__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <paragraph eId="310-212__subsec_2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <subparagraph eId="310-212__subsec_2__subsec_a__subsec_C">
                <num>(C)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>of this section shall be determined for each category
described in ORS 310.150.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-212__subsec_2__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For each category, the assessor shall multiply the total amount imposed by a
district on a property, less those taxes described in subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-212__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <paragraph eId="310-212__subsec_2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <subparagraph eId="310-212__subsec_2__subsec_a__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>and</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="310-212__subsec_2__subsec_a__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>of this section, by a ratio, the numerator of which is the total amount of
qualified obligations that were certified by the district for the tax year
beginning July 1, 1995, and the denominator of which is the total amount of the
district’s imposed taxes, other than taxes imposed to pay principal and
interest on exempt bonded indebtedness and urban renewal taxes, in the
category.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-212__subsec_2__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The total of the amounts determined under this subsection for all three
categories shall be the amount subtracted under subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-212__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <paragraph eId="310-212__subsec_2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <subparagraph eId="310-212__subsec_2__subsec_a__subsec_C">
                <num>(C)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>of this
section.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-212__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The assessor shall reduce the amount determined under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-212__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this
section by 10 percent.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-212__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The assessor shall determine for each property the value that has been added to
the assessment roll for the tax year beginning July 1, 1997, that is
attributable to changes in the value of the property for the tax year beginning
July 1, 1996, or July 1, 1997, as the result of:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="310-212__subsec_5__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>New property or improvements to property;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-212__subsec_5__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A partition or subdivision of property;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-212__subsec_5__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A rezoning of property and use of the property consistent with the rezoning;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-212__subsec_5__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Omitted property; or</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-212__subsec_5__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The disqualification of property from exemption, partial exemption or special
assessment.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-212__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The assessor shall divide the amount determined in subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-212__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this
section by the Measure 5 value in the code area on the assessment roll for the
tax year beginning July 1, 1997, reduced by the total value determined in the
code area under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-212__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section to arrive at a Measure 47
comparison tax rate.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-212__subsec_7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <paragraph eId="310-212__subsec_7__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The assessor shall multiply the total value determined for each property under
subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-212__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section by the Measure 47 comparison tax rate in the
code area determined under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-212__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section.</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="310-212__subsec_6__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The assessor shall add the amount determined under paragraph</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-212__subsec_6__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this
subsection to the amount determined in subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-212__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section to arrive
at the total amount of Measure 47 comparison taxes for each property.</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="310-212__subsec_4__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The assessor shall total the amounts determined under paragraph</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-212__subsec_4__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this
subsection for all property in the code area to determine the total Measure 47
comparison taxes for the code area.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-212__subsec_8">
            <num>(8)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The assessor shall allocate the Measure 47 comparison taxes to each taxing
district in the code area in the proportion that each taxing district’s share
of the Measure 5 imposed tax estimate in the code area (excluding taxes for
exempt bonded indebtedness and urban renewal and the amount certified for
qualified taxing district obligations) bears to the total Measure 5 imposed
taxes for the code area (excluding taxes for exempt bonded indebtedness and
urban renewal and the amount certified for qualified taxing district
obligations). The total of the amounts so allocated to a district from all of
the district’s code areas shall be the taxing district’s Measure 47 comparison
tax.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-212__subsec_9">
            <num>(9)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the taxing district is other than a city, county or school district and
supports a hospital facility through ad valorem property taxes, the Measure 47
comparison tax shall be further adjusted by subtracting the allocated portion
of taxes used to support a hospital facility from the total amount allocated to
the district under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-212__subsec_8">
            <num>(8)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-212__subsec_10">
            <num>(10)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Measure 47 comparison tax shall be further adjusted by subtracting the
allocated portion of taxes that are imposed pursuant to an operating tax levy
approved by voters prior to December 5, 1996, in an election and for which
property taxes are first imposed for the tax year beginning July 1, 1996, or
July 1, 1997, if the levy was approved by voters in an election:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="310-212__subsec_10__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In which at least 50 percent of registered voters eligible to vote in the
election cast a ballot; or</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-212__subsec_10__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>That was the general election in an even-numbered year.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_310-214">
          <num>310.214</num>
          <heading>Measure 47 comparison tax adjustments for certain nonschool taxing districts</heading>
          <subsection eId="310-214__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This section
applies to a taxing district if:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="310-214__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The district is not a school district, education service district, community
college district or community college service district;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-214__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The additions to value in the district under ORS 310.212</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-214__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>exceed 10 percent
of the Measure 5 value for the district (before the addition of any value
described in ORS 310.212</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-214__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>); and</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="310-214__subsec_5__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>There has been no voter approval of a new tax base under section 11, Article XI
of the Oregon Constitution (1995 Edition), or other tax levy that would first
take effect in a tax year beginning July 1 of 1995, 1996 or 1997 (other than
the approval of taxes to pay bonded indebtedness).</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-214__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding ORS 310.212, the Measure 47 comparison taxes of a taxing
district described in subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-214__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section shall be increased by
reducing the preliminary reduction percentage in ORS 310.218 by each percentage
point, or fraction thereof, that the additions to value in the district
identified in subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-214__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <paragraph eId="310-214__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this section exceed 10 percent.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_310-216">
          <num>310.216</num>
          <heading>Pre-reduction Measure 50 taxes</heading>
          <subsection eId="310-216__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The assessor shall determine
pre-reduction Measure 50 taxes under this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-216__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For each taxing district in the county, the assessor shall subtract from the
taxing district’s Measure 5 imposed tax estimate all of the following:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="310-216__subsec_2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The total amount imposed to pay principal and interest on exempt bonded
indebtedness;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-216__subsec_2__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The amount certified to pay qualified obligations of the taxing district;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-216__subsec_2__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The amount imposed to repay indebtedness of an urban renewal area;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-216__subsec_2__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the taxing district is other than a city, county or school district, the
amount imposed that is used to support a hospital facility; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-216__subsec_2__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The amount imposed pursuant to an operating tax levy approved by voters prior
to December 5, 1996, and for which property taxes are first imposed for the tax
year beginning July 1, 1996, or July 1, 1997, if the levy was approved by
voters in an election:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="310-216__subsec_2__subsec_e__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>In which at least 50 percent of registered voters eligible to vote in the
election cast a ballot; or</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="310-216__subsec_2__subsec_e__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>That was the general election in an even-numbered year.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-216__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The amount determined under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-216__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section shall be the taxing
district’s pre-reduction Measure 50 tax.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_310-218">
          <num>310.218</num>
          <heading>Preliminary reduction percentages</heading>
          <subsection eId="310-218__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The assessor shall compare the
pre-reduction Measure 50 tax for the district with the Measure 47 comparison
tax for the district, and determine the percentage by which the Measure 47
comparison tax is less than the pre-reduction Measure 50 tax for the district.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-218__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The percentage determined under this section shall be the preliminary reduction
percentage for the district.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_310-220">
          <num>310.220</num>
          <heading>Assessor certification to Department of Revenue; contents</heading>
          <subsection eId="310-220__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A preliminary reduction percentage determined under ORS 310.218;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-220__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The pre-reduction Measure 50 tax applicable to the district, as determined
under ORS 310.216;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-220__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Measure 47 comparison tax applicable to the district, as determined under
ORS 310.212;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-220__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The assessed value of the additions of value described in ORS 310.212</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-220__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <paragraph eId="310-220__subsec_5__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-220__subsec_5__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-220__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Measure 47 comparison taxes attributable to the additions of value, as
determined under ORS 310.212</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-220__subsec_7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <paragraph eId="310-220__subsec_7__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-220__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Taxes used to pay qualified obligations, if the qualified obligations consist
of local government pension and disability plan obligations;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-220__subsec_7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Urban renewal taxes other than urban renewal taxes used to pay principal and
interest on bonded indebtedness;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-220__subsec_8">
            <num>(8)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Operating tax levies approved by voters prior to December 5, 1996, and for
which property taxes are first imposed for the tax year beginning July 1, 1996,
or July 1, 1997, if the levy was approved by voters in an election:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="310-220__subsec_8__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In which at least 50 percent of registered voters eligible to vote in the
election cast a ballot; or</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-220__subsec_8__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>That was the general election in an even-numbered year; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-220__subsec_9">
            <num>(9)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any other information required by the department.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_310-222">
          <num>310.222</num>
          <heading>Computation of 1997 Measure 50 reduction and supplemental statutory reduction; certification to assessor</heading>
          <subsection eId="310-222__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Upon receipt of all certifications made under ORS
310.220, the Department of Revenue shall compute:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="310-222__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A statewide constitutional reduction percentage for pre-reduction Measure 50
taxes so as to achieve a statewide average reduction in Measure 50 taxes of 17
percent; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-222__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A supplemental statutory reduction percentage so as to achieve a statewide
average reduction of 17 percent in all of the following taxes:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="310-222__subsec_1__subsec_b__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Pre-reduction Measure 50 taxes;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="310-222__subsec_1__subsec_b__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Taxes used to pay qualified obligations of the taxing districts, if the
qualified obligations consist of local government pension and disability plan
obligations;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="310-222__subsec_1__subsec_b__subsec_C">
                <num>(C)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Urban renewal taxes other than urban renewal taxes used to pay principal and
interest on bonded indebtedness; and</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="310-222__subsec_1__subsec_b__subsec_D">
                <num>(D)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>An operating tax levy approved by voters prior to December 5, 1996, and for
which property taxes are first imposed for the tax year beginning July 1, 1996,
or July 1, 1997, if the levy was approved by voters in an election:</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-222__subsec_1__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In which at least 50 percent of registered voters eligible to vote in the
election cast a ballot; or
(ii)
That was the general election in an even-numbered year.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-222__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department shall compute a constitutional reduction percentage for Measure
50 taxes by comparing the total statewide pre-reduction Measure 50 tax amount
with the total statewide Measure 47 comparison tax amount and calculating the
statewide percentage by which the total Measure 47 comparison tax amount is
less than the total pre-reduction Measure 50 tax amount.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-222__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the statewide reduction percentage for Measure 50 taxes determined under
subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-222__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section equals 17 percent, the constitutional reduction
percentage for each district shall equal the percentage certified to the
district under ORS 310.220. The department shall proceed to calculate the
supplemental statutory reduction under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-222__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-222__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the statewide reduction percentage for Measure 50 taxes determined under
subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-222__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section is greater than 17 percent, each taxing district’s
preliminary reduction percentage shall be multiplied by a fraction, the
numerator of which is the percentage point difference between the statewide
reduction percentage and 17 percent, and the denominator of which is the
statewide reduction percentage. The product shall then be subtracted from the
preliminary reduction percentage to obtain the taxing district’s constitutional
reduction percentage. The department shall then calculate the supplemental
statutory reduction under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-222__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-222__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the statewide reduction percentage for Measure 50 taxes determined under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-222__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section is less than 17 percent, each taxing district’s preliminary
reduction percentage shall be multiplied by a fraction, the numerator of which
is the percentage point difference between the statewide reduction percentage
and 17 percent, and the denominator of which is the statewide reduction
percentage. The product shall then be added to the preliminary reduction
percentage to obtain the constitutional reduction percentage for the district.
The department shall then calculate the supplemental statutory reduction under
subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-222__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-222__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <paragraph eId="310-222__subsec_6__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Following the determination made under subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-222__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>,</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-222__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>or</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-222__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this
section, the department shall compute a supplemental statutory reduction
percentage so that the statewide total amount of all of the taxes described in
subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-222__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <paragraph eId="310-222__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this section is reduced by 17 percent, using the procedure
in this subsection.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-222__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall compute a statewide total amount of the taxes certified
under ORS 310.220</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-222__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>,</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-222__subsec_7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-222__subsec_8">
            <num>(8)</num>
            <content>
              <p>, and shall multiply this amount by 17
percent.</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="310-222__subsec_8__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The supplemental reduction shall be the percentage equivalent of a fraction,
the numerator of which is the amount calculated under paragraph</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-222__subsec_8__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this
section and the denominator of which is the statewide total pre-reduction
Measure 50 tax amount plus the total amount of taxes certified under ORS
310.220</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-222__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>,</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-222__subsec_7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-222__subsec_8">
            <num>(8)</num>
            <content>
              <p>.</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="310-222__subsec_8__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For each taxing district, the department shall:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="310-222__subsec_8__subsec_d__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Add the supplemental reduction percentage to the constitutional reduction
percentage determined for the district under subsection</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-222__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>,</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-222__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>or</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-222__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this
section to determine a total reduction percentage for taxes that are subject to
constitutional reduction; and
(B)
Reduce the district’s other taxes that were certified by the assessor under ORS
310.220</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-222__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>,</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-222__subsec_7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-222__subsec_8">
            <num>(8)</num>
            <content>
              <p>by the supplemental statutory reduction percentage.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-222__subsec_7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <paragraph eId="310-222__subsec_7__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the statewide constitutional reduction percentage no longer equals 17
percent after the department estimates compression of Measure 50 taxes on a
code area basis, the department shall recalculate the constitutional reduction
percentages as described in subsections</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-222__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-222__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section until the
statewide reduction percentage equals 17 percent. Constitutional reduction percentages
for each district shall be finally determined prior to any determination of
supplemental statutory reduction.</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="310-222__subsec_5__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The reduction percentages determined under this section shall be adjusted so
that the appropriate pre-compression rate is the rate used under ORS 310.236.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-222__subsec_8">
            <num>(8)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department shall certify to the assessor:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="310-222__subsec_8__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The constitutional reduction percentages and reduction amounts for each
district as determined under subsections</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-222__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>,</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-222__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-222__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section; and</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="310-222__subsec_5__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The statutory reduction percentages and reduction amounts determined under
subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-222__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_310-228">
          <num>310.228</num>
          <heading>Determination of state replacement obligation</heading>
          <subsection eId="310-228__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Based on the
constitutional reduction amounts computed under ORS 310.222, the Department of
Revenue shall determine the statewide total amount of constitutionally required
reduction certified under ORS 310.222</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-228__subsec_8">
            <num>(8)</num>
            <content>
              <p>, excluding statutory reduction
amounts, for:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="310-228__subsec_8__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>School districts;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-228__subsec_8__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Education service districts;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-228__subsec_8__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Community college districts; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-228__subsec_8__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Community college service districts.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-228__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Amounts appropriated to districts in the categories described in subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-228__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section for the fiscal year that equal the amounts determined under
subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-228__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section shall constitute the state’s replacement
obligation under section 11</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-228__subsec_9">
            <num>(9)</num>
            <content>
              <p>, Article XI of the Oregon Constitution.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_310-230">
          <num>310.230</num>
          <heading>Adjustment of Measure 47 comparison taxes and supplemental statutory reduction to account for certain additions of value</heading>
          <subsection eId="310-230__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the total statewide amount
of additions of value certified to the Department of Revenue under ORS 310.220</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-230__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>exceeds four percent of the assessed value of taxable property in this
state for the tax year beginning July 1, 1997 (not taking into account the additions
of value certified under ORS 310.220), the department shall subtract the
portion of the Measure 47 comparison taxes attributable to additions of value
in excess of four percent from the statewide total of Measure 47 comparison
taxes, prior to making the computation under ORS 310.222.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-230__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The supplemental statutory reduction percentage determined under ORS 310.222</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-230__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>shall be adjusted so as to achieve the same total reduction percentage for
the taxes described in ORS 310.222</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-230__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <paragraph eId="310-230__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>as is achieved for the statewide
constitutional reduction percentage following the calculation in subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-230__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_310-232">
          <num>310.232</num>
          <heading>Subtraction of urban renewal increment from assessed value</heading>
          <content>
            <p>The assessed
value of taxable property of a taxing district shall be further adjusted by the
assessor for purposes of determining the district’s amount of taxes before
compression under ORS 310.242 by subtracting any assessed value in the district
attributable to an urban renewal increment in the district.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_310-234">
          <num>310.234</num>
          <heading>Nonschool taxing district 1997-1998 operating tax adjustment for timber offsets</heading>
          <subsection eId="310-234__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>,</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-234__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>or</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-234__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>, whichever is applicable, shall be further
adjusted to reflect the amount of the offset. Except as provided in this
section, the adjusted rate shall not be used for any purpose under ORS 310.200
to 310.242 other than determination of the district’s ad valorem property taxes
for the tax year beginning July 1, 1997. [1997 c.541 s32a; 1999 c.1078 s71]
Note: 321.312 was
repealed by section 26, chapter 621, Oregon Laws 2003. The text of 310.234 was
not amended by enactment of the Legislative Assembly to reflect the repeal.
Editorial adjustment of 310.234 for the repeal of 321.312 has not been made.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_310-236">
          <num>310.236</num>
          <heading>Determination of taxing district 1997-1998 operating taxes and permanent and statutory rate limits for tax years after 1997-1998; 1997-1998 pre-compression consolidated rates for code areas and categories</heading>
          <subsection eId="310-236__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Upon receipt
of the reduction percentages for each district, the assessor shall determine
the district’s post-reduction Measure 50 taxes for the tax year beginning July
1, 1997, under this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-236__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The assessor shall multiply the certified constitutional reduction percentage
by the pre-reduction Measure 50 tax amount determined under ORS 310.216 and
then add to the product any of the following taxes applicable to the district:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="310-236__subsec_2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the taxing district is other than a city, county or school district, taxes
imposed to support a hospital facility; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-236__subsec_2__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Taxes imposed pursuant to an operating tax levy approved by voters prior to
December 5, 1996, for which property taxes are first imposed for the tax year
beginning July 1, 1996, or July 1, 1997, if the levy was approved by voters in
an election:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="310-236__subsec_2__subsec_b__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>In which at least 50 percent of registered voters eligible to vote in the
election cast a ballot; or</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="310-236__subsec_2__subsec_b__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>That was the general election in an even-numbered year.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-236__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The assessor shall then calculate the operating tax rate for the district by
dividing the amount determined under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-236__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section by the
assessed value of taxable property in the district determined under ORS
310.232. The rate so determined shall be the district’s permanent rate limit
for operating taxes.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-236__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <paragraph eId="310-236__subsec_4__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the taxing district is a district for which a supplemental statutory
reduction percentage has been certified to the assessor, the assessor shall
repeat the calculation described in subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-236__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section,
substituting the total reduction percentage for the constitutional reduction
percentage. Any district taxes that are described in subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-236__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <paragraph eId="310-236__subsec_2__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this
section shall be reduced by the supplemental reduction percentage in
determining the amount.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-236__subsec_2__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The assessor shall then calculate the operating tax rate for the district by
dividing the amount determined under paragraph</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-236__subsec_2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this subsection by the
assessed value of taxable property in the district determined under ORS
310.232. The rate so determined shall be the district’s statutory rate limit
for operating taxes.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-236__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If, in the written notice made under ORS 310.206, the district made a separate
certification for permanent rate limit purposes and for 1997 operating tax
purposes, and the rate determined under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-236__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section, or
subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-236__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section (if applicable), will produce operating taxes
greater than the amount certified for operating taxes, the rate determined
under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-236__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>or</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-236__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section shall be adjusted so as to produce
the amount certified by the district. Except as provided in ORS 310.234, the
adjusted rate shall not be used for any purpose under ORS 310.200 to 310.242
other than determination of the district’s ad valorem property taxes for the
tax year beginning July 1, 1997.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-236__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The assessor shall determine a rate per $1,000 of assessed value for any of the
following taxes applicable to the district:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="310-236__subsec_6__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Taxes imposed to pay qualified obligations of the district;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-236__subsec_6__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Local option taxes; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-236__subsec_6__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Taxes imposed to pay exempt bonded indebtedness.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-236__subsec_7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The rates per $1,000 of assessed value determined under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-236__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this
section shall be determined by dividing the amount of the tax for which a rate
is being determined by the assessed value of taxable property in the district
under ORS 310.232.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-236__subsec_8">
            <num>(8)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The assessor shall determine a total rate for the district and a rate for each
category described in ORS 310.150 for the district.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-236__subsec_9">
            <num>(9)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Based on the rates determined under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-236__subsec_8">
            <num>(8)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section, the
assessor shall determine a pre-compression consolidated rate for each code area
and a pre-compression consolidated rate per category described in ORS 310.150
for each code area.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_310-237">
          <num>310.237</num>
          <heading>Reallocation of Measure 47 comparison taxes and adjustment of rate limits for certain districts for 2000-2001 and later tax years</heading>
          <subsection eId="310-237__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This section
applies to a taxing district that is located in a county in which:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="310-237__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For the tax year beginning July 1, 1996, a taxing district imposed one or more
serial or one-year levies that expired before the tax year beginning July 1,
1997;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-237__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Between December 5, 1996, and July 1, 1997, voters approved one or more
temporary levies to replace the levies described in paragraph</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-237__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this
subsection and increased the amount being replaced;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-237__subsec_1__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Each levy described in paragraph</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-237__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this subsection is treated as a local
option tax under section 11</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-237__subsec_7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <paragraph eId="310-237__subsec_7__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>, Article XI of the Oregon Constitution;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-237__subsec_7__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The total amount of local option taxes described in paragraph</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-237__subsec_7__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this
subsection that were imposed by the taxing district for the tax year beginning
July 1, 1997, exceeded $1.2 million; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-237__subsec_7__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The total amount of replacement authority for the taxing district exceeds
$900,000.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-237__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For each taxing district described in subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-237__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section, the
Department of Revenue shall recompute the amount of property taxes that would
have been imposed by the taxing district for the tax year beginning July 1,
1997, making the following changes in the calculation of 1997-1998 operating
taxes for all taxing districts within the county in which the taxing district
is located:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="310-237__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The total Measure 5 imposed tax estimate determined under ORS 310.210 shall
consist of the total Measure 5 imposed tax estimate determined for the tax year
beginning July 1, 1997, plus that portion of any local option taxes that
represent replacement authority for a serial or one-year levy imposed for the
tax year beginning July 1, 1996, and described in subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-237__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <paragraph eId="310-237__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this
section;</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-237__subsec_1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A taxing district’s Measure 5 imposed tax estimate shall take the replacement
authority into account only if that taxing district imposed the serial or
one-year levy for the tax year beginning July 1, 1996; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-237__subsec_1__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Measure 47 comparison taxes shall be allocated to taxing districts in the
county based on the ratio described in ORS 310.212</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-237__subsec_8">
            <num>(8)</num>
            <content>
              <p>, substituting the
Measure 5 imposed tax estimate determined under paragraphs</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="310-237__subsec_8__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-237__subsec_8__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this
subsection.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-237__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The rate of tax that would have been achieved for the tax year beginning July
1, 1997, had the operating taxes of the taxing district been calculated as
provided for in this section, shall serve as the taxing district’s statutory
rate limit on operating taxes, to the extent the rate limit is less than or
equal to the lesser of the district’s permanent rate limit on operating taxes
or statutory rate limit on operating taxes as determined under ORS 310.200 to
310.242 (1997 Edition).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-237__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department shall recalculate taxes for each taxing district under this
section separately.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-237__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>As used in this section, “replacement authority” means that portion of the levy
described in subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-237__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <paragraph eId="310-237__subsec_1__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this section that would have been
incorporated into the permanent rate limit of the taxing district if the levy
described in subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-237__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <paragraph eId="310-237__subsec_1__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this section were treated as a levy described
in section 11</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-237__subsec_7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <paragraph eId="310-237__subsec_7__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>, Article XI of the Oregon Constitution. [1999 c.186 s1]
Note: 310.237 was added
to and made a part of 310.200 to 310.242 by legislative action but was not
added to any smaller series therein. See Preface to Oregon Revised Statutes for
further explanation.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_310-238">
          <num>310.238</num>
          <heading>Rate conversion; Measure 5 assessed value rate</heading>
          <subsection eId="310-238__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In order to
ensure that the consolidated rates for each code area do not exceed the $5 per
$1,000 of real market value limit for the public school system and $10 per
$1,000 of real market value limit for other government operations that is
guaranteed in section 11</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-238__subsec_11">
            <num>(11)</num>
            <content>
              <p>and 11b, Article XI of the Oregon Constitution,
the assessor shall, for each code area, convert the constitutional rate limit
for each category into a rate per $1,000 of assessed value by multiplying the
applicable rate limit by a fraction, the numerator of which is the code area
market value and the denominator of which is the code area assessed value.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-238__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The assessor shall add the rates determined under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-238__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this
section and the consolidated rate under ORS 310.236 for the exempt bonded
indebtedness category. The total shall be the Measure 5 assessed value rate.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_310-240">
          <num>310.240</num>
          <heading>Calculation of taxes imposed on urban renewal increment for 1997-1998; special levies</heading>
          <subsection eId="310-240__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the case of a code area in which urban renewal taxes are to be imposed
for the tax year beginning July 1, 1997, the assessor shall determine the rate
of taxes to be imposed on the urban renewal increment under this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-240__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The assessor shall use the lesser of the total consolidated rate for the code
area determined under ORS 310.236, or the total consolidated Measure 5 assessed
value rate, for purposes of the remainder of the calculation under this
section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-240__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The assessor shall multiply the rate determined under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-240__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this
section by the urban renewal increment for the code area. The assessor shall
determine the total amount under this subsection for all code areas within an
urban renewal plan to determine the total amount of taxes to be raised on the
urban renewal increment.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-240__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For each urban renewal plan, the assessor shall compare the amount determined
under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-240__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section with the amount certified by the urban
renewal agency under ORS 310.208. If the amount determined under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-240__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section is less than the amount certified, the assessor shall determine
a special levy in the amount of the difference.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-240__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The assessor shall determine a rate per $1,000 of assessed value for the
special levy described in subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-240__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section by dividing the amount
of the special levy by the assessed value of the municipality that activated
the urban renewal agency and all taxable property in the urban renewal area
lying outside the city or county, including the value of the urban renewal
increment, and shall add the rate to the pre-compression consolidated rate for
each code area in which the special levy is to be extended.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-240__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For tax years beginning on or after July 1, 1998, urban renewal tax increment calculations
shall be made as provided in ORS 457.420 to 457.470.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_310-242">
          <num>310.242</num>
          <heading>1997-1998 compression of consolidated rates</heading>
          <subsection eId="310-242__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For each property, the
assessor shall adjust the pre-compression consolidated rates for each category
determined under ORS 310.236 including any special levy under ORS 310.240</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-242__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>(and as further modified by ORS 310.234) to be rates per $1,000 of real market
value.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-242__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The assessor shall compare the pre-compression consolidated rates for each
category as modified under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-242__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section with the rate of $5
per $1,000 of real market value of the property for the public school system
category and $10 per $1,000 of real market value of the property for the other
government operations category.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-242__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If a pre-compression consolidated category rate for a property, as modified
under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-242__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section, exceeds the $5 or $10 per $1,000 category
rate limits set forth in subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-242__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section (whichever is
applicable), the consolidated category rate shall be compressed as provided in
subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-242__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>or</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-242__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-242__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <paragraph eId="310-242__subsec_4__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If local option taxes in the category for which compression is being determined
have been adopted by one or more taxing districts that impose taxes on the
property, the reduction ratio shall be calculated under this subsection and
applied only to the local option taxes imposed on the property.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-242__subsec_4__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The numerator of the reduction ratio shall be the amount obtained, but not less
than zero, by subtracting the property’s pre-compression consolidated category
rate of ad valorem property taxes that are not local option taxes from the
maximum rate of ad valorem property taxes for the category.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-242__subsec_4__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The denominator for the reduction ratio shall be the total rate of all local
option taxes for the category.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-242__subsec_4__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The assessor shall multiply the reduction ratio determined under this
subsection by the rate of each local option tax in the category to which the
property is subject. After reduction, the assessor shall recompute:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="310-242__subsec_4__subsec_d__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The rates per $1,000 of assessed value for the property;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="310-242__subsec_4__subsec_d__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The total amount of local option taxes to be raised in the code area; and</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="310-242__subsec_4__subsec_d__subsec_C">
                <num>(C)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The local option tax rates per $1,000 of assessed value for the code area and
incorporate those rates into the consolidated rate for the code area.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-242__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <paragraph eId="310-242__subsec_5__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If no local option taxes have been adopted by a taxing district in the category
in the code area or if all local option taxes have been eliminated as a result
of application of the reduction ratio calculated under subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-242__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this
section, and the pre-compression consolidated category rate as modified under
subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-242__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section or following further adjustment under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-242__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section exceeds the $5 or $10 per $1,000 category rate limits set
forth in subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-242__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section (whichever is applicable), the
reduction ratio shall be determined under this subsection.</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="310-242__subsec_2__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The numerator of the reduction ratio shall be the maximum rate permitted for
the category.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-242__subsec_2__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The denominator of the reduction ratio shall be the pre-compression
consolidated category rate as modified under subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-242__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section or
following further adjustment under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-242__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section, if
applicable.</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="310-242__subsec_4__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The assessor shall multiply the reduction ratio determined under this
subsection by each taxing district item of ad valorem property tax that is a
component of the consolidated category rate for the code area. The sum of the
rates so reduced within the category shall be the consolidated rate for the
category for the property. After reduction, the assessor shall recompute:</p>
              </content>
              <subparagraph eId="310-242__subsec_4__subsec_d__subsec_A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The rates per $1,000 of assessed value for the property;</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="310-242__subsec_4__subsec_d__subsec_B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The total amount of local option taxes to be raised in the code area; and</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
              <subparagraph eId="310-242__subsec_4__subsec_d__subsec_C">
                <num>(C)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The total amount of taxes in each category to be raised in the code area.</p>
                </content>
              </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_310-244">
          <num>310.244</num>
          <heading>Adjustment of city’s post-compression tax rate under certain circumstances</heading>
          <subsection eId="310-244__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This section
applies to a city with a Measure 5 tax estimate that was reduced by compression.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-244__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding ORS 310.200 to 310.242, the combination of the constitutional
and the statutory reductions determined under ORS 310.222 shall not cause a
city’s Measure 50 post-reduction taxes prior to additions made in ORS 310.236</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-244__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <paragraph eId="310-244__subsec_2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-244__subsec_2__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>, to be less than the lesser of:</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-244__subsec_2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The city’s Measure 47 comparison taxes; or</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-244__subsec_2__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The city’s Measure 50 pre-reduction taxes.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-244__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding ORS 310.200 to 310.242, in the case of a city whose voters
approved a local option tax in March 1997 of less than $100,000 per year and
whose Measure 47 comparison taxes plus the local option taxes exceed the city’s
Measure 50 pre-reduction taxes plus local option taxes, the city’s
post-reduction Measure 50 taxes shall not be less than $228,000.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-244__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Department of Revenue shall increase a city’s post-reduction tax rate by
the amount necessary to meet the requirements of subsections</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-244__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-244__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of
this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-244__subsec_5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department shall also adjust the post-reduction tax rates of each taxing
district, other than a school district, taxing the same property as a city
affected by subsections</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-244__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-244__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section to ensure that the district’s
tax revenue is not reduced by more than one-quarter of one percent by the
operation of this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-244__subsec_6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The calculations in this section shall be based on department estimates and
shall include the effects of code area compression, but shall not include the
effect of property-by-property compression.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-244__subsec_7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the statewide constitutional reduction percentage determined under ORS
310.222 no longer equals 17 percent after the department makes the
determinations described in this section, the department shall recalculate the
constitutional reduction percentages as described in ORS 310.222 until the
statewide reduction percentage equals 17 percent.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_310-246">
          <num>310.246</num>
          <heading>Adjustment of permanent rate limit to correct mistakes by June 30, 1998</heading>
          <subsection eId="310-246__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The
Department of Revenue may adjust the permanent rate limits for operating taxes
established under ORS 310.200 to 310.242 to correct for mistakes. All
adjustments by the department must be made by June 30, 1998.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-246__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No change to the assessment and tax roll shall be made as the result of an
adjustment under this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_310-585">
          <num>310.585</num>
          <heading>Distribution of certain property tax relief moneys to counties</heading>
          <content>
            <p>Property tax
relief money paid to the county treasurer pursuant to law, such as but not
limited to senior citizens’ property tax relief, inventory property tax relief,
local property tax relief and such other property tax relief as may be
hereafter enacted by the State of Oregon which do not require that the amounts
be offset against a particular type of district’s levy, shall be distributed by
the county treasurer with the assistance of the tax collector to the taxing
districts of the county in accordance with the schedule of percentages computed
under ORS 311.390.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_310-595">
          <num>310.595</num>
          <heading>Determination of apportionment to counties</heading>
          <subsection eId="310-595__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <paragraph eId="310-595__subsec_1__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>for each district shown in the
certificate filed with the tax collector under ORS 311.115 for such year.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_310-622">
          <num>310.622</num>
          <heading>Manufactured structures eligible as homesteads under tax laws of state</heading>
          <content>
            <p>A manufactured
structure assessed under the ad valorem tax laws of this state shall be
eligible to be a homestead for the purposes of all tax laws of this state
giving a right or privilege to a homestead. For those manufactured structures
assessed as real property, the manufactured structure homestead includes land
and improvements to the same extent that a homestead would be recognized if the
manufactured structure were a conventional home. [1971 c.529 s11; 1977 c.884 s16]
Note: The definition of
“manufactured structure” provided in 307.021 applies to ORS chapter 310.
(Floating
Homes)</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_310-623">
          <num>310.623</num>
          <heading>Floating home eligible as homestead</heading>
          <content>
            <p>A floating home, as defined in ORS
830.700, assessed under the property tax laws of this state shall be eligible
to be a homestead for the purposes of all tax laws of this state giving a right
or privilege to a homestead.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
        <section eId="sec_310-800">
          <num>310.800</num>
          <heading>Property tax work-off programs</heading>
          <subsection eId="310-800__subsec_1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>As used in this section:</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="310-800__subsec_1__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>“Authorized representative” means a senior citizen who is authorized by a
tax-exempt entity to perform charitable or public service on behalf of a senior
citizen who has entered into a contract under subsection</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-800__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section.</p>
            </content>
            <paragraph eId="310-800__subsec_2__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>“Homestead” means an owner-occupied principal residence.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-800__subsec_2__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>“Senior citizen” means a person who is 60 years of age or older.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-800__subsec_2__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>“Tax-exempt entity” means an entity that is exempt from federal income taxes
under section 501</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-800__subsec_2__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of the Internal Revenue Code as defined in ORS 305.842.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph eId="310-800__subsec_2__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>“Taxing unit” means any county, city or common or union high school district,
community college service district or community college district within this
state with authority to impose ad valorem property taxes.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-800__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A tax-exempt entity may establish a property tax work-off program pursuant to
which a senior citizen may contract to perform charitable or public service in
consideration of payment of property taxes extended against the homestead of
the senior citizen and billed to the senior citizen. For purposes of ORS
chapters 316 and 656, and notwithstanding ORS 670.600 or other law, a senior
citizen who enters into a contract under this subsection shall be considered an
independent contractor and not a worker or employee with respect to the
services performed pursuant to the contract. Nothing in this section precludes
a taxing unit from being considered an employer, for purposes of unemployment
compensation under ORS chapter 657, of a senior citizen who enters into a
contract under this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-800__subsec_3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A taxing unit may enter into an agreement with a tax-exempt entity that has
established a property tax work-off program. Pursuant to the agreement the
taxing unit may accept, as volunteer and public service, the services of a
senior citizen who has entered into a contract described in subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-800__subsec_2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of
this section or an authorized representative.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="310-800__subsec_4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A taxing unit may provide funds or make grants to any tax-exempt entity that
has established a property tax work-off program for use to carry out the
program.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>